<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Internet Histories on Sumandro</title>
    <link>https://ajantriks.net/tags/internet-histories/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Internet Histories on Sumandro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 20:09:56 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ajantriks.net/tags/internet-histories/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Civil Society Organisations and Internet Governance in Asia, 2000-2010</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.net/civil-society-organisations-and-internet-governance-in-asia-2000-2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.net/civil-society-organisations-and-internet-governance-in-asia-2000-2010/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;this-is-a-book-section-written-for-the-asia-internet-history-third-decade-2001-2010-volume-edited-by-prof-kilnam-chon-the-book-was-published-both-in-print-and-as-an-online-open-access-version-in-december-2015-access-the-book-here-https-sites-google-com-site-internethistoryasia-book3-https-sites-google-com-site-internethistoryasia-book3:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;This is a book section written for the &lt;em&gt;Asia Internet History - Third Decade (2001~2010)&lt;/em&gt; volume edited by Prof. Kilnam Chon. The book was published, both in print and as an online open access version, in December 2015. Access the book here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/internethistoryasia/book3&#34;&gt;https://sites.google.com/site/internethistoryasia/book3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparations-for-the-world-summit-on-the-information-society:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Preparations for the World Summit on the Information Society&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) conferences organized by the United Nations in Geneva (2003) and Tunis (2005) initiated crucial platforms and networks, some temporary and some ongoing, for various non-governmental actors to intensively and periodically take part in discussions of governance of the Internet and various related activities. Many of the civil society organisations taking part in WSIS conferences, as well as various regional and thematic preparatory meetings and seminars, had little prior experience in the topic of Internet governance. They were entering these conversations from various backgrounds, such as local developmental interventions, human and cultural rights activism, freedom and diversity of media, and gender and social justice. Members of such civil society organisations often faced difficult challenges in articulating their experiences, insights, positions, and suggestions in terms of the (then) emerging global discourse of Internet governance that was driven by inter-governmental dynamics of technology and infrastructure governance. At the WSIS, Asian Response Meeting in 2002, Susanna George, (then) Executive Director of Isis International, Manila, succinctly expressed this challenge being faced by the members of civil society organisations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some feminist activists, however, including myself, it has felt like trying to squeeze my concerns into a narrow definition of what gender concerns in ICTs are. I would like it to Cinderella’s ugly sister cutting off her toe to fit into the dainty slipper of gender concerns in ICTs. The development ball, it seems, can only accommodate some elements of what NGO activists, particularly those from the South, are concerned about in relation to new information and communications technologies &lt;code&gt;[George 2002]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seminar, held in Bangkok on 22-24 November 2002, was a crucial early meeting for the representatives from Asian civil society organisations to share and shape their understanding and positions before taking part in global conversations during the following years. The meeting was organized by Bread for All (Switzerland), Communication Rights in the Information Society Campaign (Netherlands), Forum Asia (Thailand), and World Association for Christian Communication (United Kingdom), as a preparatory meeting for the Asia Pacific Regional Conference of WSIS, with 34 organisations from 16 Asian countries taking part. The Final Document produced at the end of this seminar was quite remarkable. It highlighted the simultaneity of Asia as one of the global centres of the information economy and the everyday reality of widespread poverty across Asian countries, and went on to state that the first principle for the emerging global information society should be that &amp;lsquo;[c]ommunication rights are fundamental to democracy and human development&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2002]&lt;/code&gt;. It proposed the following action items for efforts towards a global inclusive information society: 1) strengthen community, 2) ensure access, 3) enhance the creation of appropriate content, 4) invigorate global governance, 5) uphold human rights, 6) extend the public domain, 7) protect and promote cultural and linguistic diversity, and 8) ensure public investment in infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately after this conference, several Asian civil society organisations attended the Asian Civil Society Forum, organized as part of the Conference of Non-governmental Organizations in Consultative Relations with the United Nations (CONGO), held in Bangkok on 9-13 December 2002. Representatives of Dhaka Ahsania Mission (Bangladesh), OneWorld South Asia (India), GLOCOM (Japan), Foundation for Media Alternative (Philippines), Korean Progressive Network – JINBONET (South Korea), Friedrich Naumann Foundation (Singapore), International Federation of University Women (Switzerland), and Forum Asia (Regional) drafted a Joint Statement emphasising that a &amp;lsquo;broad-based participation of civil society, especially from those communities which are excluded, marginalized and severely deprived, is critical in defining and building such a [true communicative, just and peaceful] society [that is being envisaged through initiating the WSIS process.]&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[Aizu 2002]&lt;/code&gt;. In the very next month, the Asia Pacific Regional Conference was held in Tokyo, during 13-15 January 2003, &amp;lsquo;to develop a shared vision and common strategies for the “Information Society” &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003d]&lt;/code&gt;. The conference was attended by representatives from 47 national governments, 22 international organisations, 54 private sector agencies, and 116 civil society organisations across the Asia-Pacific region. The Tokyo Declaration, the final document prepared at the conclusion of the Conference, recognised that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[T]he Information Society must &amp;hellip; facilitate full utilization of information and communication technologies (ICT) at all levels in society and hence enable the sharing of social and economic benefits by all, by means of ubiquitous access to information networks, while preserving diversity and cultural heritage &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003d]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, it highlighted the following priority areas of action: 1) infrastructure development, 2) securing affordable, universal access to ICTs, 3) preserving linguistic and cultural diversity and promoting local content, 4) developing human resources, 5) establishing legal, regulatory and policy frameworks, 6) ensuring balance between intellectual property rights (IPR) and public interest, 7) ensuring the security of ICTs, and 8) fostering partnerships and mobilizing resources. It is not difficult to see how the focus of necessary actions shifted from an emphasis on concerns of community and human rights, need for investments and to bridge digital divides, and the idea of the Internet as a public commons, towards legal and policy mechanisms, multi-partner delivery of services, and intellectual property rights. Several civil society organisations felt sidelined in this conference and decided to issue a joint statement to ensure that their positions are effectively presented. The first two topics mentioned in this document were: 1) &amp;lsquo;[c]ommunication rights should be fully recognized as a fundamental and universal human right to be protected and promoted in the information society,&amp;rsquo; and 2) &amp;lsquo;[t]he participation of civil society in the information society at all levels should be ensured and sustained, from policy planning to implementation, monitoring, and evaluation&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[UNSAJ 2003]&lt;/code&gt;. The joint statement was endorsed by 30 civil society organisations: UDDIPAN (Bangladesh); COMFREL (Cambodia); ETDA (East Timor); The Hong Kong Council of Social Services (Hong Kong); Food India, IT for Change (India); Indonesian Infocom Society (Indonesia); Active Learning, CPSR, Forum for Citizens&amp;rsquo; Television and Media, JTEC, Kyoto Journal, Ritsumeikan University Media Literacy Project, UNSAJ (Japan); Computer Association Nepal, Rural Area Development Programme (Nepal); APC Women&amp;rsquo;s Networking Support Programme, Foundation for Media Alternatives, ISIS International (Philippines); Citizens&amp;rsquo; Action Network, Korean Progressive Network – Jinbonet, Labor News Production, ZAK (South Korea); e-Pacificka Consulting (Samoa); National University of Singapore (Singapore); Public Television Service, Taiwan Association for Human Rights (Taiwan); Asian-South Pacific Bureau for Adult Education, Forum Asia, and TVE Asia Pacific (Regional) &lt;code&gt;[UNSAJ 2003]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;participation-in-the-wsis-process:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Participation in the WSIS Process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first WSIS conference was held in Geneva on 10-12 December 2003. Through the processes of organizing this conference, and the second conference in Tunis in 2005, the United Nations operationalized a much-appreciated mandate for facilitating wider participation of non-governmental actors from the private sector, civil society, academia, and media, along with governmental organisations, in international policy-setting processes. At the first meeting of the WSIS Preparatory Committee (PrepCom-1) in Geneva, during 1-5 July 2002, civil society organisations argued that they should be allowed to co-shape the key subjects of discussion during the first conference (2003). There was already an Inter-Governmental Subcommittee on Contents and Themes, but no equivalent platform for the civil society organisations was available. With the approval of the Civil Society Plenary (CSP), the Civil Society Subcommittee on Content and Themes (WSIS-SCT) was instituted during PrepCom-1 &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003b]&lt;/code&gt;. At the second WSIS Preparatory Committee meeting (PrepCom-2), held in Geneva during 17-28 February 2003, the WSIS-SCT produced a summary of the views of its members titled &amp;lsquo;Vision and Principles of Information and Communication Societies,&amp;rsquo; as well as a one-page brief titled &amp;lsquo;Seven Musts: Priority Principles Proposed by Civil Society&amp;rsquo; to be used for lobbying purposes &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003b]&lt;/code&gt;. This brief mentioned seven key principles of Internet governance identified by the civil society organisations taking part in the WSIS process: (1) sustainable development, (2) democratic governance, (3) literacy, education, and research, (4) human rights, (5) global knowledge commons, (6) cultural and linguistic diversity, and (7) information security &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asian civil society organisations that took part in the PrepCom-2 meeting included United Nations Association of China (China); CASP - Centre for Adivasee Studies and Peace, C2N - Community Communications Network (India); ICSORC - Iranian Civil Society Organizations Resource Center (Iran); GAWF - General Arab Women Federation (Iraq); Daisy Consortium, GLOCOM - Center for Global Communications (Japan); Association for Progressive Communication, Global Knowledge Partnership (Malaysia); Pakistan Christian Peace Foundation (Pakistan); WFEO - World Federation of Engineering Organization (Palestine); Asian South Pacific Bureau of Adult Education, Foundation for Media Alternatives, ISIS International – Manila (Philippines); Korean Progressive Network - Jinbonet (South Korea); IIROSA - International Islamic Relief Organization (Saudi Arabia); and Taking IT Global (India, Indonesia, Malaysia, Philippines, and Turkey) &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these efforts led to the development of the Civil Society Declaration to the World Summit on the Information Society, which was prepared and published by the Civil Society Plenary at the Geneva conference, on 8 December 2003. The Declaration was titled &amp;lsquo;Shaping Information Societies for Human Needs&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003c]&lt;/code&gt;. The Asian civil society organization that took part in the Geneva conference were BFES - Bangladesh Friendship Education Society, Drik, ICTDPB - Information &amp;amp; Communication Technology Development Program, Proshika - A Center for Human Development (Bangladesh); China Society for Promotion of the Guangcai Programme, Chinese People&amp;rsquo;s Association for Friendship with Foreign Countries, United Nations Association of China (China); The Hong Kong Council of Social Service (Hong Kong); CASP - Centre for Adivasee Studies and Peace, Childline India Foundation / Child Helpline International, DAWN - Development Alternatives with Women for a New Era (India); Communication Network of Women&amp;rsquo;s NGOs in Iran, Green Front of Iran, ICTRC - Iranian Civil Society Organizations Training and Research Center, Islamic Women&amp;rsquo;s Institute of Iran, Institute for Women&amp;rsquo;s Studies and Research, Organization for Defending Victims of Violence (Iran); ILAM - Center for Arab Palestinians in Israel (Israel); Citizen Digital Solutions, Forum for Citizens&amp;rsquo; Television and Media, GLOCOM - Center for Global Communications, JCAFE - Japan Computer Access for Empowerment, Soka Gakkai International (Japan); LAD-Nepal - Literary Academy for Dalit of Nepal (Nepal); Asia-Pacific Broadcasting Union, Global Knowledge Partnership (Malaysia); PAK Educational Society / Pakistan Development Network, SMEDA - Small &amp;amp; Medium Enterprize Development Authority (Pakistan); Palestine IT Association of Companies (Palestine); Isis International – Manila, Ugnayan ng Kababaihan sa Pulitika / Philippine Women&amp;rsquo;s Network in Politics and Governance (Philippines); Citizen&amp;rsquo;s Alliance for Consumer Protection of Korea, Korean Civil Society Network for WSIS (South Korea); Youth Challenge (Singapore); Association for Progressive Communications (India and Philippines), CITYNET - Regional Network of Local Authorities for the Management of Human Settlements (India. Mongolia, and Philippines), Taking IT Global (India and Philippines) &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003b]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the preparatory meetings and consultations towards the second WSIS conference advanced during the next year, civil society organizations from Asia attempted to engage more directly with the global Internet governance processes on one hand, and the national Internet and ICT policy situations on the other. Writing about their encounters at and before the second Preparatory Committee meeting for the Tunis conference, held in Geneva during 17-25 February 2005, Anita Gurumurthy and Parminder Jeet Singh made several early observations that have continued to resonate with the experiences of Asian civil society organizations throughout the decade &lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2005]&lt;/code&gt;. First, they indicated that the government agencies present in the dialogs tend to take diverging positions in international events and domestic contexts. Second, there was a marked absence of formal and informal discussions between the governmental and the civil society representatives of the same country present at the meeting. The government agencies were clearly disinterested in involving civil society organizations in the process. Third, the civil society actors present at the meeting were mostly from the ICT for Development sector, while the organizations working in more &amp;lsquo;traditional&amp;rsquo; sectors – such as education, health, governance reform, etc. – remained absent from the conversations. This is especially problematic in the case of such developing countries where there does not exist strategic linkages between civil society organizations focusing on topics of technologized developmental interventions, and those involved in more &amp;lsquo;traditional&amp;rsquo; development practices. Rekha Jain, in a separate report on the Indian experience of participating in the WSIS process, reiterated some of these points &lt;code&gt;[Jain 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. She highlighted that &amp;lsquo;[w]hile the Secretary, [Department of Telecommunications, Government of India] was involved in (PrepCom-1) drafting the initial processes for involvement of NGOs, at the national level, this mechanism was not translated into a process for involving the civil society or media.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general lack of interest of national governments, especially in Asian countries, to engage with civil society organizations on matters of policies and projects in Internet governance and ICTs for development &lt;code&gt;[Souter 2007]&lt;/code&gt;, further encouraged these organization to utilize the global discussion space opened up by the WSIS process to drive the agendas of democratization of Internet governance processes, protection of human rights, and advancement of social justice. The second WSIS conference held in Tunis during 16-18 November 2005, however, did not end on a positive note for the civil society organizations as a whole. The sentiment is aptly captured in the title of the Civil Society Statement issued after the Tunis Conference: &amp;lsquo;Much more could have been achieved&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2005b]&lt;/code&gt;. Apart from producing this very important critical response to the WSIS process, within a month of its conclusion, civil society organizations played a key role in shaping one of the more longer-term impacts of the process – the establishment of the Internet Governance Forum (IGF). After the publication of the Report of the Working Group on Internet Governance &lt;code&gt;[Desai 2005]&lt;/code&gt; in June 2005, the Center for Global Communications (GLOCOM), Japan, acting on behalf of the Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus, came forward with public support for &amp;lsquo;the establishment of a new forum to address the broad agenda of Internet governance issues, provided it is truly global, inclusive, and multi-stakeholder in composition allowing all stakeholders from all sectors to participate as equal peers&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2005]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;asian-civil-society-organizations-at-the-igfs:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Asian Civil Society Organizations at the IGFs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, the WSIS Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus was reformed and established as a permanent &amp;lsquo;forum for discussion, advocacy, action, and for representation of civil society contributions in Internet governance processes&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[Civil 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. Representatives from Asian civil society organizations have consistently played critical roles in the functionings of this Caucus. Youn Jung Park of the Department of Technology and Society, SUNY Korea, co-founded and co-coordinated the original caucus in 2003. Adam Peake of the Center for Global Communications (GLOCOM), International University of Japan, was co-coordinator of the original caucus from 2003 to 2006. Parminder Jeet Sing of IT for Change, India, was elected as one of the co-coordinators of the newly reformed caucus in 2006, and held the position till 2008. Izumi Aizu of the Institute for HyperNetwork Society and the Institute for InfoSocinomics, Tama University, served as the co-coordinator of the caucus during 2010-2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first IGF, held in Athens during 30 October - 2 November 2006, saw participation from only a few Asian civil society organizations, mostly from Bangladesh and Japan &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. The second Internet Governance Forum in Rio de Janeiro, during 12-15 November 2007, had a larger representation from Asian civil society organizations: Bangladesh NGOs Network for Radio and Communication, BFES - Bangladesh Friendship Education Society, VOICE – Voices for Interactive Choice and Empowerment (Bangladesh); China Association for Science and Technology, Internet Society of China (China); University of Hong Kong (Hong Kong); Alternative Law Forum (via Association for Progressive Communications - Women&amp;rsquo;s Networking Support Programme), Indian Institute of Technology in Delhi, IT for Change (India); GLOCOM, Kumon Center, Tama University (Japan); Sustainable Development Networking Programme (Jordan); Kuwait Information Technology Society (Kuwait); Association of Computer Engineers – Nepal, Rural Area Development Programme, Nepal Rural Information Technology Development Society (Nepal); Bytesforall – APC / Pakistan, Pakistan Christian Peace Foundation (Pakistan); Foundation for Media Alternatives, Philippine Resources for Sustainable Development Inc. (Philippines); and LIRNEasia (Sri Lanka). At the Open IGF Consultations in Geneva, on 26 February 2008, the Internet Governance Caucus made two significant submissions: 1) that, although structuring the IGF sessions in Athens and Rio de Janeiro around the large themes of access, openness, diversity, and security have been useful to open up the multi-stakeholder dialogues, it is necessary to begin focused discussions of specific public policy issues to take the IGF process forward &lt;code&gt;[Civil 2008]&lt;/code&gt;, and 2) that the Multi-Stakeholder Advisory Group (MAG), which drives the IGF process and events, should be made more proactive and transparent, and expanded in size so as to better include the different stakeholder groups who may self-identify their representatives for the MAG &lt;code&gt;[Civil 2008b]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one hand, the IGF Hyderabad, held during 3-6 December 2008, experienced a decline in the percentage of participants from civil society organizations and a rather modest increase in the percentage of participants from Asian countries, especially since this was the first major international Internet governance summit held in an Asian country. See Table 6-2 for further information. On the other hand, the Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus succeeded to bring forth the term &amp;lsquo;enhanced cooperation,&amp;rsquo; as mentioned in the Tunis Agenda, to be addressed and discussed in one of the main sessions of the Forum &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2008]&lt;/code&gt;. The next IGF held in Sharm El Sheikh, during 15-18 November 2009, saw a further decline of participation from both the representatives of civil society organizations and attendees from Asian countries. See Table 6-2 for further information. The fall in participation reflects a feeling among civil society organizations that the IGF process is not allowing specific and effective dialogues about critical policy and governance concerns around Internet and digital media. In this context, Youn Jung Park made the following statement in the Stock Taking session of the summit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a co-founder of WSIS Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus in 2003, I would like to remind you &amp;hellip; [that] Internet Governance Forum was created as a compromise between those who supported the status quo Internet governance institution under one nation&amp;rsquo;s status provision, and those who requested for more balanced roles for governments under international supervision of the Internet. While IGF has achieved a great success of diluting of such political tension between those who have different views of how to institutionalize Internet governance, ironically Internet governance forum became a forum without governance&amp;hellip; [We] have to admit [that] IGF failed to deliver another mandate of the U.N. WSIS: Continuing discussion of how to design Internet governance institutions&amp;hellip; The current IGF continues to function as knowledge transfer of ICANN&amp;rsquo;s values to other stakeholders, while those who want to discuss and negotiate on how to design Internet governance institutions should have another platform for that specific U.N. WSIS mandate &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2009]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Asia Pacific regional Internet Governance Forum (APrIGF) was held in Hong Kong on 14-16 June 2010. The organising committee included three civil society / academic organizations – Center for Global Communications (GLOCOM), Internet Society Hong Kong, and National University of Singapore – and three independent experts – Kuo-Wei Wu (Taiwan), Norbert Klein (Cambodia), and Zahid Jamil (Pakistan). Though the forum was largely attended by governmental and private sector participants, several representatives from Asian civil societies and academic organizations spoke at the main sessions: Ang Peng Hwa (Singapore Internet Research Centre, Nanyang Technological University), Charles Mok (Internet Society Hong Kong), Christine Loh (Civic Exchange), Chong Chan Yau (Hong Kong Blind Union), Clarence Tsang (Christian Action), Ilya Eric Lee (Taiwan E-Learning and Digital Archives Program, and Research Center for Information Technology Innovation), Izumi Aizu (Institute for HyperNetwork Society, and Institute for InfoSocinomics, Kumon Center, Tama University), Oliver &amp;lsquo;Blogie&amp;rsquo; Robillo (Mindanao Bloggers Community), Parminder Jeet Singh (IT for Change), Priscilla Lui (Against Child Abuse in Hong Kong), Tan Tin Wee (Centre for Internet Research, National University of Singapore), and Yap Swee Seng (Asian Forum for Human Rights and Development). As Ang Peng Hwa noted at the beginning of the summit, its key objective was to provide a formal space for various stakeholders from the Asia-Pacific region to discuss and provide inputs to the IGF process &lt;code&gt;[APrIGF 2010]&lt;/code&gt;. The regional forum was successful in enabling newer civil society entrants from the Asia-Pacific region to familiarize themselves with the IGF process, and to contribute to it. For example, IGF Vilnius, held during 14-17 September 2010, was the first IGF summit attended by Oliver &amp;lsquo;Blogie&amp;rsquo; Robillo, where he presented the recommendations from Southeast Asian civil society organizations. In his speech, he emphasized the following topics: 1) openness and freedom of expression are the basis of democracy, and state-driven censorship of the Internet in the region is an immediate threat to such global rights; 2) coordinated international efforts need to address and resolve not only global digital divides, but also the divides at regional, national, and sub-nationals scales; 3) the right to privacy is an integral part of cybersecurity, as well as a necessary condition for exercising human rights; 4) global Internet governance efforts must ensure that national governments do not control or restrict abilities of citizens to express through digital means, and this should be aligned with the universal human rights agenda, and 5) even after 5 years of the IGF process, a wider participation of civil society organizations, especially from the Asia-Pacific regions, remains an unachieved goal, which can only be achieved if specific resources are allocated and processes are implemented &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2010]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;internet-censorship-and-civil-society-responses:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Internet Censorship and Civil Society Responses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the decade of 2001-2010, censorship of the Internet and restriction of digital expression remained crucial Internet rights concerns across the world and especially in Asian countries. One of the earliest global reports on the topic was brought out by Reporters without Borders. In 2006, they published a list of sixteen countries marked as &amp;lsquo;Internet Enemies,&amp;rsquo; out of which eleven were from Asia: China, Iran, Maldives, Myanmar, Nepal, North Korea, Saudi Arabia, Syria, Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan, and Vietnam &lt;code&gt;[Reporters 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. The list was updated in 2007, and three of these countries – Libya, Maldives, and Nepal – were removed. The unique contradictions of the Internet and ICTs landscape of the Asian region were insightfully highlighted in the 2006-07 report on Internet censorship by OpenNet Initiative:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the most and least connected countries in the world are located in Asia: Japan, South Korea, and Singapore all have Internet penetration rates of over 65 percent, while Afghanistan, Myanmar, and Nepal remain three of thirty countries with less than 1 percent of its citizens online. Among the countries in the world with the most restricted access, North Korea allows only a small community of elites and foreigners online. Most users must rely on Chinese service providers for connectivity while the limited number North Korean–sponsored Web sites are hosted abroad&amp;hellip; [T]hough India’s Internet community is the fifth largest in the world, users amounted to only about 4 percent of the country’s population in 2005. Afghanistan, Myanmar, and Nepal are among the world’s least-developed countries. Despite the constraints on resources and serious developmental and political challenges, however, citizens are showing steadily increasing demand for Internet services such as Voice over Internet Protocol (VoIP), blogging, and chat &lt;code&gt;[Wang 2007]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report further described the strategy used by various Asian governments of &amp;lsquo;delegation of policing and monitoring responsibilities to ISPs, content providers, private corporations, and users themselves&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[Wang 2007]&lt;/code&gt;. This is an effective method of enforcing self-surveillance and self-censorship under the threats of loss of commercial license, denial of services, and even criminal liability. Defamation suits and related civil and criminal liability have also been used by several Asian governments to silence influential critics and protesters. Direct technical filtering of Internet traffic (especially incoming traffic) and blocking of URLS via government directives sent to Internet Service Providers (ISPs) have been common practices in several Asian countries &lt;code&gt;[Wang 2007]&lt;/code&gt;. Expectedly, such experiences of oppression led to widespread campaigns by the Asian civil society organizations, as can be surmised from the submission mentioned above by Oliver &amp;lsquo;Blogie&amp;rsquo; Robillo at IGF Vilnius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among Asian countries, the comprehensive technologies of censorship developed and deployed by China have been studied extensively. The Golden Shield Project was initiated by the Ministry of Public Security of China in 1998 to undertake blanket blocking of incoming Internet traffic based on specific URLs and terms. Evidence of the project being operationalised became available in 2003 &lt;code&gt;[Garden 2004]&lt;/code&gt;. Censorship of Internet in China, however, has not only been implemented using such macro-scale technological systems, non-automated mechanisms have also been used at the ground level. In 2003, it was made mandatory for all residents of Lhasa, Tibet, to use a specific combination of user name and password, which was directly linked to their names and address, to access the Internet. An Internet ID card was issued by the government to implement this &lt;code&gt;[International 2004]&lt;/code&gt;. Tibet Action Institute has been a key civil society organization at the forefront of the cyber offense of the Chinese government. A recent documentary by the institute, titled &amp;lsquo;Tibet: Frontline of the New Cyberwar,&amp;rsquo; narrates how it has worked closely with Citizen Lab, Munk School of Global Affairs, University of Toronto, to identify, trace, and resist malware and other cyber-attacks experienced by the civil society actors and websites in favor of independence of Tibet &lt;code&gt;[Tibet 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. The Tibetan case is not an exceptional one. Digital security training has emerged as an important aspect of the life of civil society organizations during the decade. Asian organizations such as Bytes for All (Pakistan) and Myanmar ICT for Development Organization (Myanmar), as well as international organizations including Front Line Defenders and Citizen Lab have educated and supported civil society activities much beyond the Internet governance sphere with tools and techniques for effectively using digital channels of communications, and defending themselves against cyber-threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combination of traditional forms of civil society mobilizations and digital techniques has often been used to resist attempts by Asian governments to control the online communication space. In Pakistan, as the government took harsh steps towards control of both traditional and online media in 2007-2008, Huma Yusuf extensively studied the emergence of hybrid media strategies among citizen journaalists and civil society activits, using both old media channels such as newspapers and new media channels like blogs and video sharing platforms &lt;code&gt;[Yusuf 2009]&lt;/code&gt;. She has carefully traced how possibilities of new forms of information and media sharing enabled by the Internet were initially identified and implemented by citizen journalists and student activists, which was quickly learned and re-deployed by more formal organisations, such as print and electronic news companies, and civil society organizations like those involved in election monitoring. Malaysia also experienced fast-accelerating conflict between the government and a civil society during 2007-2010, as the former started intervening directly into censoring blogs and newspaper websites. On one hand, the government took legal actions against critical bloggers, either directly or indirectly, and on the other it instructed ISPs to block &amp;lsquo;offensive content.&amp;rsquo; It also borrowed the &amp;lsquo;Singapore-model&amp;rsquo; to mandate registration of bloggers with government authorities, if they are identified as writing on socio-political topics. Civil society actors responded to these oppressive steps by setting up a new blog dedicated to coverage of the defamation cases (filed against prominent bloggers), and publicly sharing instructions for circumvention of the blocks imposed by ISPs. The National Alliance of Bloggers was soon formed, which organized the Blogs and Digital Democracy Forum on 3 October 2007 [Thien 2011]. Similarly, the Bloggers Against Censorship campaign took shape in India in 2006 as the government first directed ISPs to block specific blogs hosted on Blogspot, TypePad, and Yahoo! Geocities, and then sought complete blocking of Yahoo! Geocities as the ISPs failed to block specific sub-domains of the platform &lt;code&gt;[Bloggers 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. Learning from this experience, the following year the Indian government decided to work directly with Orkut to take down &amp;lsquo;defamatory content&amp;rsquo; about a politician &lt;code&gt;[Economic 2007]&lt;/code&gt;. This is common for other Asian governments too, as they have continued to develop more legally binding and technically sophisticated measures to monitor and control online expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &amp;lsquo;Internet Enemies Report 2012,&amp;rsquo; Reporters without Borders listed 12 countries as &amp;lsquo;enemies of the Internet,&amp;rsquo; out of which 10 were from Asia – Bahrain, China, Iran, Myanmar, North Korea, Saudi Arabia, Syria, Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan, and Vietnam – and it named 14 countries that were conducting surveillance on its citizens, out of which 7 were from Asia – India, Kazakhstan, Malaysia, South Korea, Sri Lanka, Thailand, and United Arab Emirates &lt;code&gt;[Reporters 2012]&lt;/code&gt;. At the APrIGF held in Tokyo during 18-20 July 2012, a group of delegates from civil society organizations working in the South-East Asian region issued a joint statement with a clear call for global action on the shrinking space for freedom of (digital) expression in the region &lt;code&gt;[Thai 2012]&lt;/code&gt;. They specifically noted the following national acts as examples of the legislative mechanisms being used by different Asian governments to criminalize online speech and/or to harass public dissenters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burma – The 2004 Electronic Transactions Act&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cambodia – The 2012 Draft Cyber-Law, the 1995 Press Law, and the 2010 Penal Code&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malaysia – The 2012 Amendment to the Evidence Act and the 2011 Computing Professionals Bill&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indonesia – The 2008 Law on Information and Electronic Transaction and the 2008 Law on Pornography&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Philippines – The 2012 Data Privacy Act&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thailand – The 2007 Computer Crimes Act, the Article 112 of the Penal Code, and the 2004 Special Case Investigation Act&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vietnam – The 1999 Penal Code, the 2004 Publishing Law, the 2000 State Secrets Protection Ordinance, and the 2012 Draft Decree on Internet Management. (Ibid.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statement was co-signed by Thai Netizen Network, Thai Media Policy Centre, The Institute for Policy Research and Advocacy (ELSAM), Southeast Asian Press Alliance (SEAPA), Southeast Asian Centre for e-Media (SEACeM), Victorius (Ndaru) Eps, Community Legal Education Center (CLEC), Sovathana (Nana) Neang, and Asian Forum for Human Rights and Development (Forum Asia), and was endorsed by ICT Watch (Indonesian ICT Partnership Association).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;annexe-tables:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Annexe – Tables&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;table-1-participation-from-asian-countries-and-of-representatives-from-asian-civil-society-organisations-in-igfs-2006-2010:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Table 1: Participation from Asian Countries and of representatives from Asian civil society organisations in IGFs, 2006-2010&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Event&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Participants from Asian Countries&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Participants from Civil Society Organizations&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IGF Athens 2006&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;29%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IGF Rio de Janeiro 2007&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;32%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IGF Hyderabad 2008&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;56% from India, and 15% from other Asian countries&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;25%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IGF Sharm El Sheikh 2009&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IGF Vilnius 2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not Available&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not Available&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: Reports available on &lt;a href=&#34;http://igf.wgig.org/cms&#34;&gt;Internet Governance Forum website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;table-2-internet-society-chapters-in-asia:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Table 2: Internet Society Chapters in Asia&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Chapter&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year of Establishment&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;URL&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Afghanistan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;In formation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not available&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bahrain&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bis.org.bh/&#34;&gt;http://www.bis.org.bh/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bangladesh&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.org.bd/dhaka/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.org.bd/dhaka/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hong Kong&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2005&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.hk/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.hk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;India (Bangalore)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocbangalore.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocbangalore.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;India (Chennai)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocindiachennai.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocindiachennai.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;India (Delhi)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2002. Rejuvenated in 2008.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocdelhi.in/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocdelhi.in/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;India (Kolkata)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://isockolkata.in/&#34;&gt;http://isockolkata.in/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;India (Trivandrum)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not available&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Indonesia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.or.id/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.or.id/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Israel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1995&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.org.il/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.org.il/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Japan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1994&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.jp/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.jp/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lebanon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.org.lb/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.org.lb/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Malaysia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.my/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.my/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nepal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.internetsociety.org.np/&#34;&gt;http://www.internetsociety.org.np/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pakistan (Islamabad)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocibd.org.pk/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocibd.org.pk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Palestine&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2002&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.ps/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.ps/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philippines&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1999. Rejuvenated in 2009.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/isoc.ph/&#34;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/isoc.ph/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Qatar&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.qa/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.qa/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Republic of Korea&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not available&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Singapore&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://isoc.sg/&#34;&gt;http://isoc.sg/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sri Lanka&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.lk/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.lk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Taipei&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1996&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.org.tw/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.org.tw/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thailand&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1996&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc-th.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc-th.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;United Arab Emirates&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocuae.com/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocuae.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yemen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://isoc.ye/&#34;&gt;http://isoc.ye/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: Details of chapters available on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.internetsociety.org/&#34;&gt;Internet Society website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgment:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to Anita Gurumurthy and Parminder Jeet Singh for their generous sharing of information and insights. Raman Jit Singh Cheema, Pranesh Prakash, and Sunil Abraham have also provided crucial suggestions. Extensive background research by P.P. Sneha has significantly enriched my efforts. The Wayback Machine of the Internet Archive deserves a very special thanks. Last but not the least, I am thankful to Kilnam Chon for this wonderful opportunity and his patient support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reference:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Aizu 2002]&lt;/code&gt; Aizu, Izumi et al. 2002. Joint Statement from Asia Civil Society Forum Participants on World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS). December 13. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsisasia.org/wsis-acsf2002/wsis-acsfdec13f.doc&#34;&gt;http://www.wsisasia.org/wsis-acsf2002/wsis-acsfdec13f.doc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[APrIGF 2010]&lt;/code&gt; Asia Pacific Regional Internet Governance Forum (APrIGF). 2010. APrIGF Roundtable – June 15th, 2010: Session 1 – Welcome Remarks and Introduction – Real Time Transcript. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://2010.rigf.asia/aprigf-roundtable-june-15th-2010-session-1/&#34;&gt;http://2010.rigf.asia/aprigf-roundtable-june-15th-2010-session-1/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Bloggers 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Bloggers Collective Group. 2006. Bloggers Against Censorship. Last updated on April 30, 2009‎. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://censorship.wikia.com/wiki/Bloggers_Against_Censorship&#34;&gt;http://censorship.wikia.com/wiki/Bloggers_Against_Censorship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Civil 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus. 2006. Internet Governance Caucus Charter. October 14. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC-charter_final-061014.html&#34;&gt;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC-charter_final-061014.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Civil 2008]&lt;/code&gt; Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus. 2008. Inputs for the Open IGF Consultation, Geneva, 26th February, 2008 – Statement II: Main Session Themes for IGF, Hyderabad. February 26. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC%20-%20Main%20themes%20for%20IGF%20Hyd.pdf&#34;&gt;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC%20-%20Main%20themes%20for%20IGF%20Hyd.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Civil 2008b]&lt;/code&gt; Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus. 2008. Inputs for the Open IGF Consultation, Geneva, 26th February, 2008 – Statement III: Renewal / Restructuring of Multi-stakeholder Advisory Group. February 26. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC%20-%20MAG%20Rotation.pdf&#34;&gt;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC%20-%20MAG%20Rotation.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Desai 2005]&lt;/code&gt; Desai, Nitin, et al. 2005. Report of the Working Group on Internet Governance. United June. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wgig.org/docs/WGIGREPORT.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.wgig.org/docs/WGIGREPORT.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Economic 2007]&lt;/code&gt; The Economic Times. 2007. Orkut&amp;rsquo;s Tell-All Pact with Cops. May 01. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2007-05-01/news/28459689_1_orkut-ip-addresses-google-spokesperson&#34;&gt;http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2007-05-01/news/28459689_1_orkut-ip-addresses-google-spokesperson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Garden 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Garden Networks for Freedom of Information. 2004. Breaking through the “Golden Shield.” Open Society Institute. November 01. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.opensocietyfoundations.org/sites/default/files/china-internet-censorship-20041101.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.opensocietyfoundations.org/sites/default/files/china-internet-censorship-20041101.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[George 2002]&lt;/code&gt; George, Susanna. 2002. Women and New Information and Communications Technologies: The Promise of Empowerment. Presented at The World Summit on the Information Society: An Asian Response Meeting, November 22-24. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsisasia.org/materials/susanna.doc/&#34;&gt;http://www.wsisasia.org/materials/susanna.doc/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2005]&lt;/code&gt; Gurumurthy, Anita, &amp;amp; Parminder Jeet Singh. 2005. WSIS PrepCom 2: A South Asian Perspective. Association for Progressive Communications. April 01. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apc.org/en/news/hr/world/wsis-prepcom-2-south-asian-perspective&#34;&gt;https://www.apc.org/en/news/hr/world/wsis-prepcom-2-south-asian-perspective&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum (IGF). 2006. Athens 2006 – List of Participants. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intgovforum.org/PLP.html&#34;&gt;http://www.intgovforum.org/PLP.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2008]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum (IGF). 2008. Arrangements for Internet Governance, Global and National/Regional. IGF Hyderabad, India. December 5. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20130621205004/http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/hyderabad_prog/AfIGGN.html&#34;&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20130621205004/http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/hyderabad_prog/AfIGGN.html&lt;/a&gt; [Original URL: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/hyderabad_prog/AfIGGN.html&#34;&gt;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/hyderabad_prog/AfIGGN.html&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum (IGF). 2009. Taking Stock and Looking Forward – On the Desirability of the Continuation of the Forum, Part II. IGF Sharm El Sheikh, Egypt. November 18. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/2009/sharm_el_Sheikh/Transcripts/Sharm%20El%20Sheikh%2018%20November%202009%20Stock%20Taking%20II.txt&#34;&gt;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/2009/sharm_el_Sheikh/Transcripts/Sharm%20El%20Sheikh%2018%20November%202009%20Stock%20Taking%20II.txt&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2010]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum (IGF). 2010. Taking Stock of Internet Governance and the Way Forward. IGF Vilnius, Lithuania. September 17. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://igf.wgig.org/cms/component/content/article/102-transcripts2010/687-taking-stock&#34;&gt;http://igf.wgig.org/cms/component/content/article/102-transcripts2010/687-taking-stock&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[International 2004]&lt;/code&gt; International Campaign for Tibet. 2004. Chinese Authorities Institute Internet ID Card System in Tibet for Online Surveillance. April 30. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.savetibet.org/chinese-authorities-institute-internet-id-card-system-in-tibet-for-online-surveillance/&#34;&gt;http://www.savetibet.org/chinese-authorities-institute-internet-id-card-system-in-tibet-for-online-surveillance/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003]&lt;/code&gt; International Telecommunication Union (ITU). 2003. PrepCom-2 / 17-28 February 2003 – Final List of Participants. February 28. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/participation/prepcom2/prepcom2-cl.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/participation/prepcom2/prepcom2-cl.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003b]&lt;/code&gt; International Telecommunication Union (ITU). 2003. Geneva Phase of the WSIS: List of Participants. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/summit_participants.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/summit_participants.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Jain 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Jain, Rekha. 2006. Participation of Developing Countries in the World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) Process: India Case Study. Association for Progressive Communications. March. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://rights.apc.org/documents/wsis_india.pdf&#34;&gt;http://rights.apc.org/documents/wsis_india.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Reporters 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Reporters without Borders. 2006. List of the 13 Internet Enemies. Last updated on August 28, 2007. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.rsf.org/list-of-the-13-internet-enemies-07-11-2006,19603&#34;&gt;http://en.rsf.org/list-of-the-13-internet-enemies-07-11-2006,19603&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Reporters 2012]&lt;/code&gt; Reporters without Borders. 2012. Internet Enemies Report 2012. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.rsf.org/IMG/pdf/rapport-internet2012_ang.pdf&#34;&gt;http://en.rsf.org/IMG/pdf/rapport-internet2012_ang.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Souter 2007]&lt;/code&gt; Souter, David. 2007. WSIS and Civil Society. In: Whose Summit? Whose Information Society? Developing Countries and Civil Society at the World Summit on the Information Society. With additional research by Abiodun Jagun. Association for Progressive Communications. Pp. 72-89. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://rights.apc.org/documents/whose_summit_EN.pdf&#34;&gt;http://rights.apc.org/documents/whose_summit_EN.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Thai 2012]&lt;/code&gt; Thai Netizen Network et al. 2012. Southeast Asian Civil Society Groups Highlight Increasing Rights Violations Online, Call for Improvements to Internet Governance Processes in the Region. Statement of Civil Society Delegates from Southeast Asia to 2012 Asia-Pacific Regional Internet Governance Forum (APrIGF). July 31. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;https://freedomhouse.org/sites/default/files/AprIGF-Joint%20Statement-FINAL.pdf&#34;&gt;https://freedomhouse.org/sites/default/files/AprIGF-Joint%20Statement-FINAL.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Thien 2011]&lt;/code&gt; Thien, Vee Vian. 2011. The Struggle for Digital Freedom of Speech: The Malaysian Sociopolitical Blogosphere’s Experience. In: Ronald Deibert et al. (eds.) Access Contested. OpenNet Initiative. Pp. 43-63. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://access.opennet.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/accesscontested-chapter-03.pdf&#34;&gt;http://access.opennet.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/accesscontested-chapter-03.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Tibet 2015]&lt;/code&gt; Tibet Action Institute. 2015. Tibet: Frontline of the New Cyberwar. YouTube. January 27. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yE3AQqbGVkk&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yE3AQqbGVkk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[UNSAJ 2003]&lt;/code&gt; UNSAJ et al. 2003. Civil Society Observations and Response to the Tokyo Declaration. Asia-Pacific Regional Conference on the World Summit on the Information Society. January 15. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsisasia.org/wsis-tokyo/tokyo-statement.html&#34;&gt;http://www.wsisasia.org/wsis-tokyo/tokyo-statement.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Wang 2007]&lt;/code&gt; Wang, Stephanie. 2007. Internet Filtering in Asia in 2006-2007. OpenNet Initiative. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://opennet.net/studies/asia2007&#34;&gt;https://opennet.net/studies/asia2007&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2002]&lt;/code&gt; The World Summit on the Information Society: An Asian Response. 2002. Final Document. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsisasia.org/materials/finalversion.doc&#34;&gt;http://www.wsisasia.org/materials/finalversion.doc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Civil Society Subcommittee on Content and Themes. 2003. “Seven Musts”: Priority Principles Proposed by Civil Society. February 25. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.movimientos.org/es/foro_comunicacion/show_text.php3%3Fkey%3D1484&#34;&gt;http://www.movimientos.org/es/foro_comunicacion/show_text.php3%3Fkey%3D1484&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003b]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Civil Society Subcommittee on Content and Themes. 2003. Final Report on Prepcom-2 Activities of the Civil Society on Content and Themes. March 27. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/pcip/misc/cs_sct.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/pcip/misc/cs_sct.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003c]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Civil Society Plenary. 2003. “Shaping Information Societies for Human Needs” – Civil Society Declaration to the World Summit on the Information Society. December 8. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/civil-society-declaration.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/civil-society-declaration.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003d]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Executive Secretariat. 2003. Report of the Asia-Pacific Regional Conference for WSIS (Tokyo, 13-15 January 2003). WSIS. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/dms_pub/itu-s/md/03/wsispc2/doc/S03-WSISPC2-DOC-0006!!PDF-E.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/dms_pub/itu-s/md/03/wsispc2/doc/S03-WSISPC2-DOC-0006!!PDF-E.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2005]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus. 2005. Initial Reactions to the WGIG Report. Contribution from GLOCOM on behalf of the WSIS Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus. July 19. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from www.itu.int/wsis/%20docs2/pc3/contributions/co23.doc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2005b]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Civil Society Plenary. 2005. “Much more could have been achieved” – Civil Society Statement on the World Summit on the Information Society. December 18. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/contributions/co13.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/contributions/co13.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Yusuf 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Yusuf, Huma. 2009. Old and New Media: Converging during the Pakistan Emergency (March 2007 - February 2008). MIT Centre for Civic Media. January 12. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://civic.mit.edu/blog/humayusuf/old-and-new-media-converging-during-the-pakistan-emergency-march-2007-february-2008&#34;&gt;https://civic.mit.edu/blog/humayusuf/old-and-new-media-converging-during-the-pakistan-emergency-march-2007-february-2008&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Civil Society Organisations and Internet Governance in India, 2000-2010</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.net/civil-society-organisations-and-internet-governance-in-india-2000-2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.net/civil-society-organisations-and-internet-governance-in-india-2000-2010/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;this-is-a-book-section-written-for-the-asia-internet-history-third-decade-2001-2010-volume-edited-by-prof-kilnam-chon-the-book-was-published-both-in-print-and-as-an-online-open-access-version-in-december-2015-read-the-book-online-here-https-sites-google-com-site-internethistoryasia-book3-https-sites-google-com-site-internethistoryasia-book3:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;This is a book section written for the &lt;em&gt;Asia Internet History - Third Decade (2001~2010)&lt;/em&gt; volume edited by Prof. Kilnam Chon. The book was published, both in print and as an online open access version, in December 2015. Read the book online here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/internethistoryasia/book3&#34;&gt;https://sites.google.com/site/internethistoryasia/book3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#early-days:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Early Days&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#key-organizations:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Key Organizations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#global-and-national-events:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Global and National Events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#internet-policies-and-censorship:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Internet Policies and Censorship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#acknowledgment:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#reference:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Reference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;early-days:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Early Days&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overarching context of development interventions and rights-based approaches has shaped the space of civil society organizations working on the topics of information and communication technologies (ICTs) and Internet governance in India. Early members of this space came from diverse backgrounds. Satish Babu was working with the South Indian Federation of Fishermen Societies (SIFFS) in the mid-1990s, when he set up a public mailing list called &amp;lsquo;FishNet,&amp;rsquo; connected to the Internet via the IndiaLink email network, (then) run by India Social Institute to inter-connect development practitioners in India. He went on to become the President of Computer Society of India during 2012-2013; he also co-founded the Society for Promotion of Alternative Computing and Employment (SPACE) in 2003, where he served as the Executive Secretary during 2003-2010 &lt;code&gt;[Wikipedia 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. Anita Gurumurthy, Executive Director of IT for Change and one of the key actors from Indian civil society organizations that took part in the World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) process, had previously worked extensively on topics related to public health and women&amp;rsquo;s rights &lt;code&gt;[ITfC 2015b]&lt;/code&gt;, which deeply shaped the perspectives she and IT for Change have brought into the Internet governance sphere, globally as well as nationally &lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2001]&lt;/code&gt;. Arun Mehta initiated a mailing list titled &amp;lsquo;India-GII&amp;rsquo; in 2002 to discuss &amp;lsquo;India&amp;rsquo;s bumpy progress on the global infohighway&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[India-GII 2005]&lt;/code&gt;. This list played a critical role in curating an early community of non-governmental actors interested in the topics of telecommunication policy, spectrum licensing, Internet governance, and consumer and communication rights. As Frederick Noronha documented, the mailing list culture grew slowly in India during the late 1990s and early 2000s. However, they had a great impact on organizing early online communities, sometimes grouped around a topical focus, sometimes functioning as a bridge among family members living abroad, and sometimes curating place-specific groups &lt;code&gt;[Noronha 2002]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inaugural conference of the Free Software Foundation of India (FSFI) in Thiruvananthapuram, on 20 July 2001, galvanized the Free/Libre and Open Source Software (FLOSS) community in India. The conference was titled &amp;lsquo;Freedom First,&amp;rsquo; and Richard Stallman was invited as the chief guest. It was a vital gathering of actors from civil society organizations, software businesses, academia, and media, as well as the Secretary of the Department of Information Technology, Government of Kerala (the state where the conference was held). The conference laid the basis for sustained collaborations between the free software community, civil society organizations, emerging software firms in the state, and the Government of Kerala for the years to come. Two early initiatives that brought together free software developers and state government agencies were the Kerala Transportation Project and the IT@School project, which not only were awarded to firms promoting use of FLOSS in electronic governance projects, but also facilitated a wider public dialogue regarding the need to think critically about the making of an information society in India &lt;code&gt;[Kumar 2007]&lt;/code&gt;. The inter-connected communities and overlapping practices of the FLOSS groups, civil society organizations involved in ICT for Development initiatives, telecommunication policy analysts and advocates, and legal-administrative concerns regarding life in the information society – from digital security and privacy, to freedom of online expressions, to transparency in electronic governance infrastructures – have, hence, continued to shape the sub-spherer of civil society organizations in India that are discussing, responding to, and contributing to policies and practices around the Internet governance in India and elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-organizations:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Key Organizations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IT for Change was established in 2000, in Bengaluru, as a non-governmental organization that &amp;lsquo;works for the innovative and effective use of information and communication technologies (ICTs) to promote socio-economic change in the global south, from an equity, social justice and gender equality point of view&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[ITfC 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. It has since made important contributions in the field of ICTs for Development, especially in integrating earlier communication rights practices organized around old media forms with newer possibilities of production and distribution of electronic content using digital media and the Internet &lt;code&gt;[ITfC 2015e]&lt;/code&gt;, and in the field of the Internet governance, especially through their participation in the WSIS and Internet Governance Forum (IGF) processes and by co-shaping the Internet governance discourse in and from the global south &lt;code&gt;[ITfC 2015d]&lt;/code&gt;. It has also done significant works in the area of women&amp;rsquo;s rights in the information society, and has been a core partner in a multi-country feminist action research project on using digital media to enhance the citizenship rights and experiences of marginalized women in India, Brazil, and South Africa &lt;code&gt;[ITfC 2015c]&lt;/code&gt;. IT for Change co-led the formation of Just Net Coalition in February 2014 &lt;code&gt;[JNC 2015]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF) was founded by Osama Manzar in New Delhi in 2002, with a &amp;lsquo;deep understanding that marginalized communities living in socio-economic backwardness and information poverty can be empowered to improve their lives almost on their own, simply by providing them access to information and knowledge using digital tools&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[DEF 2015c]&lt;/code&gt;. DEF has contributed to setting up Community Information Resource Centres from 19 states and 53 districts in India, with computers, printers, scanners, and Internet connectivity &lt;code&gt;[DEF 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. DEF organizes one of the biggest competitions in Asia to identify, foreground and honor significant contributions in the area of ICT for Development &lt;code&gt;[DEF 2015d]&lt;/code&gt;. This annual competition series, titled the &amp;lsquo;Manthan Award&amp;rsquo; (&amp;lsquo;manthan&amp;rsquo; means &amp;lsquo;churning&amp;rsquo; in Sanskrit), started in 2004. It has allowed DEF to create a detailed database of ICT for Development activities and actors in the South Asia and Asia Pacific region. Since 2011, DEF has been working with Association for Progressive Communications on a project titled &amp;lsquo;Internet Rights&amp;rsquo; to move forward the agenda of &amp;lsquo;Internet access for all&amp;rsquo; in India &lt;code&gt;[DEF 2015b]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Society for Knowledge Commons was formed in New Delhi 2007 by &amp;lsquo;scientists, technologists, researchers, and activists to leverage the tremendous potential of the “collaborative innovation” model for knowledge generation that has lead to the growth of the Free and Open Source Software community (FOSS) around the world&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[SKC 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. It has championed integration of FOSS into public sector operations in India – from electronic governance systems to the use of software in educational institutes – and has continuously intervened in Internet governance issues from the perspective of the critical importance of shared knowledge properties and practices for a more democratic information society. It is a part of the Free Software Movement of India &lt;code&gt;[FSMI 2015]&lt;/code&gt;, an alliance of Indian organizations involved in advocating awareness and usage of FOSS, as well as a founding member of the Just Net Coalition &lt;code&gt;[JNC 2015]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre for Internet and Society (CIS) was established in Bengaluru in 2008 with a research and advocacy focus on topics of accessibility of digital content for differently-abled persons, FOSS and policies on intellectual property rights, open knowledge and Indic language Wikipedia projects, digital security and privacy, freedom of expression and Internet governance, and socio-cultural and historical studies of Internet in India &lt;code&gt;[CIS 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. In one of the key early projects, CIS contributed to the creation of web accessibility policy for government websites in India, which was being drafted by the Department of Information Technology, Government of India &lt;code&gt;[CIS 2008]&lt;/code&gt;. In the following years it took part in Internet Governance Forum summits; submitted responses and suggestions to various policies being introduced by the government, especially the Information Technology (Amendment) Act, 2008, National Identification Authority of India (NIA) Bill, 2010, and the Approach Paper for Legislation on Privacy, 2010; produced a report on the state of open government data in India &lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2011b]&lt;/code&gt;; and undertook an extensive study on the experiences of young people in Asia with Internet, digital media, and social change &lt;code&gt;[Shah 2011]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Software Freedom Law Centre has undertaken research and advocacy interventions, since 2011, on the topics of digital privacy, software patents, and cyber-surveillance &lt;code&gt;[SFLC 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. The Internet Democracy Project, an initiative of Point of View, has organized online and offline discussions, participated in global summits, and produced reports on the topics of freedom of expression, cyber security and human rights, and global Internet governance architecture since 2012 &lt;code&gt;[IDP 2015]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Internet Society chapter to be established in India was in Delhi. The chapter began in 2002 but went through a period of no activity before being revived in 2008 &lt;code&gt;[Delhi 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. The Chennai chapter started in 2007 &lt;code&gt;[Chennai 2015]&lt;/code&gt;, the Kolkata one in 2009 &lt;code&gt;[Kolkata 2015]&lt;/code&gt;, and the Bengaluru chapter came into existence in 2010 &lt;code&gt;[Bangalore 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. Asia Internet Symposium have been organized in India twice: 1) the Kolkata one, held on on 1 December 2014, focused on &amp;lsquo;Internet and Human Rights: Empowering the Users,&amp;rsquo; and 2) the Chennai symposium, held on 2 December 2014, discussed &amp;lsquo;India in the Open and Global Internet.&amp;rsquo; The newest Internet Society chapter in India is in the process of formation in Trivandrum &lt;code&gt;[Trivandrum 2015]&lt;/code&gt;, led by the efforts of Satish Babu (mentioned above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;global-and-national-events:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Global and National Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) conference held on 10-12 December 2003 in Geneva, was not attended by many civil society organizations from India. Several Indian participants in the conference were part of a team of representatives from different global civil society organizations, including Digital Partners, Development Alternatives with Women for a New Era (DAWN), and International Centre for New Media &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003]&lt;/code&gt;. Between the first and the second conference, engagement with the WSIS process increased among Indian civil society organizations, and was especially led by IT for Change. In early 2005, before the second Preparatory Committee meeting for the Tunis conference, IT for Change organized a discussion event titled &amp;lsquo;Gender Perspectives on the Information Society: South Asia Pre-WSIS Seminar&amp;rsquo; in partnership with DAWN and the Indian Institute of Management, Bangalore, which was supported by UNIFEM and the UNDP Asia-Pacific Development Information Programme &lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. In a separate note, Anita Gurumurthy and Parminder Jeet Singh of IT for Change noted their experience as a South Asian civil society organization engaging with the WSIS process &lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2005]&lt;/code&gt;. The second WSIS conference in Tunis, held on 16-18 November 2005, however, did not see significant participation from Indian civil society organizations, except for Ambedkar Centre for Justice and Peace, Childline India Foundation / Child Helpline International, and IT for Change &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2005]&lt;/code&gt;. This contrasted sharply with the over 60 delegates from various Indian government agencies that took part in the conference &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2005]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two important events took place in India in early 2005 that substantially contributed to the civil society discourses in India around information technology and its socio-legal implications and possibilities. The firt was a conference titled &amp;lsquo;Contested Commons, Trespassing Publics&amp;rsquo; organized by the Sarai Programme at the Centre for the Study of Developing Societies, Alternative Law Forum, and Public Service Broadcasting Trust, in Delhi on 6-8 January 2005. This conference attempted to look into the terms of intellectual property rights (IPR) debates from the perspectives of experiences in countries in Asia, Latin America, and Africa. It was based on research carried out by the Sarai Programme and Alternative Law Forum on contemporary realities of media production and distribution, and the ways in which law and legal instruments enter into the most intimate spheres of social and cultural life to operationalize IPRs. The conference combined academic discussions with parallel demonstrations by media practitioners, and knowledge sharing by FLOSS communities &lt;code&gt;[Sarai 2005]&lt;/code&gt;. The second event was the first Asia Source workshop, which took place in Bengaluru during 28 January - 4 February 2005. It brought together more than 100 representatives from South and South-East Asian civil society organizations and technology practitioners working with them, along with several leading practitioners from Africa, Europe, North America, and Latin America, to promote adoption and usage of FLOSS across the developmental sector in the region. The workshop was organized by Mahiti (Bengaluru) and Tactical Technology Collective (Amsterdam), with intellectual and practical support from an advisory group of representatives from FLOSS communities and civil society organizations, and financial support from Hivos, the Open Society Institute, and International Open Source Network &lt;code&gt;[Asia 2015]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the participation of representatives from Indian civil society organizations at the IGFs in Athens (2006) and Rio de Janeiro (2007) was minimal, the IGF Hyderabad, held on 3-6 December 2008, provided a great opportunity for Indian civil society actors to participate in and familiarize themselves with the global Internet governance process. Apart from various professionals, especially lawyers, who attended the Hyderabad conference as individuals, the leading civil society organizations participating in the event included: Ambedkar Center for Justice and Peace, Centre for Internet and Society, Centre for Science, Development and Media Studies, Digital Empowerment Foundation, Internet Society Chennai chapter, IT for Change, and Mahiti. The non-governmental participants from India at the event, however, were predominantly from private companies and academic institutes &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2008]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IT for Change made a critical intervention into the discourse of global Internet governance during the Hyderabad conference by bringing back the term &amp;lsquo;enhanced cooperation&amp;rsquo;, as mentioned in the Tunis Agenda for the Information Society &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2005b]&lt;/code&gt;. At IGF Sharm El Sheikh, held during 15-18 November 2009, Parminder Jeet Singh of IT for Change explained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[E]nhanced cooperation consists of two parts. One part is dedicated to creating globally applicable policy principles, and there is an injunction to the relevant organizations to create the conditions for doing that. And I have a feeling that the two parts of that process have been conflated into one. And getting reports from the relevant organizations is going on, but we are not able to go forward to create a process which addresses the primary purpose of enhanced cooperation, which was to create globally applicable public policy principles and the proof of that is that I don&amp;rsquo;t see any development of globally applicable public policy principles, which remains a very important need &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2009]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This foregrounding of the principle of &amp;lsquo;enhanced cooperation&amp;rsquo; has since substantially contributed to rethinking of not only the global Internet governance mechanisms and its reconfigurations, but also the Indian government&amp;rsquo;s perspectives towards the same. It eventually led to the proposal made by a representative of Government of India at the UN General Assembly session on 26 October 2011 regarding the establishment of a UN Committee for Internet-Related Policies &lt;code&gt;[Singh 2011]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;internet-policies-and-censorship:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Internet Policies and Censorship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the earliest instances of censorship of online content in India was the blocking of several websites offering Voice over IP (VoIP) software, which can be downloaded to make low-cost international calls, during the late 1990s. The India-GII mailing list initiated by Arun Mehta, as mentioned above, started largely as a response to this blocking move by Videsh Sanchar Nigam Limited (VSNL), the government-owned Internet Service Provider (ISP). Additionally, Mehta filed a case against VSNL for blocking these e-commerce websites, which might be identified as the first case of legal activism for Internet-related rights in India &lt;code&gt;[India-GII 2001]&lt;/code&gt;. During the war between India and Pakistan in 1999, the Indian government instructed VSNL to block various Pakistani media websites, including that of Dawn. As in the case of websites offering VoIP services, this blocking did not involve direct intervention with the websites concerned but only the ability of Indian users to access them &lt;code&gt;[Tanna 2004]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first well-known case of the Government of India blocking digital content for political reasons occurred in 2003 when a mailing list titled &amp;lsquo;Kynhun&amp;rsquo; was banned. The Department of Telecommunications instructed all the ISPs to stop Indian users from accessing the list, hosted don Yahoo! Group, but the previously deployed URL-blocking strategy did not work in this new situation. Blocking the URL of the list did not stop its members from continuing to share emails through it. The Government of India then approached Yahoo! directly to ensure that the mailing list was taken down, which Yahoo! declined to implement. This resulted in the imposition of a blanket block on all Yahoo! Groups pages across ISPs in India in September 2003. By November, Yahoo! decided to close down the mailing list, and the blanket block was repealed &lt;code&gt;[Tanna 2004]&lt;/code&gt;. Further blocking of several blogs and websites continued through 2006 and 2007, where the government decided to work in collaboration with various platforms offering hosted blog and personal web page services to remove access to specific sub-domains. In resistance to this series of blocking orders by the government, there emerged an important civil society campaign titled &amp;lsquo;Bloggers Against Censorship&amp;rsquo; led by the Bloggers Collective Group, a distributed network of bloggers from all across India &lt;code&gt;[Bloggers 2006]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks after the IGF Hyderabad, the Government of India passed the Information Technology (Amendment) Act 2008 on 22 December 2008 &lt;code&gt;[MoLaJ 2009]&lt;/code&gt;, although it was notified and enforced much later on 27 October 2009 &lt;code&gt;[MoCaIT 2009]&lt;/code&gt;. This amendment attempted to clarify various topics left under-defined in the Information Technology Act of 2000. However, as Pranesh Prakash of the Centre for Internet and Society noted, the casual usage of the term &amp;lsquo;offensive content&amp;rsquo; in the amendment opened up serious threats of broad curbing of freedom of online expression under the justification that it caused &amp;lsquo;annoyance&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;inconvenience&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2009]&lt;/code&gt;. Sections 66 and 67 of the amended Information Technology Act, which respectively address limits to online freedom of expression and legally acceptable monitoring of digital communication by government agencies, have since been the objects of strong protests by civil society organizations across India for enabling broad-brushed censorship and surveillance of the Internet in India. Section 66A has, in particular, allowed the government to make a series of arrests of Internet users for posting and sharing &amp;lsquo;offensive content&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[Pahwa 2015]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, the Government of India introduced another critical piece of policy instrument for controlling online expressions – the Information Technology (Intermediary Guidelines) Rules, 2011 &lt;code&gt;[MoCaIT 2011]&lt;/code&gt; – targeted at defining the functions of the intermediaries associated with Internet-related services and communication, and how they are to respond to the government&amp;rsquo;s directives towards taking down and temporarily blocking digital content. The draft rules were published in early 2011 and comments were invited from the general public. One of the responses, submitted by Privacy India and the Centre for Internet and Society, explicitly highlighted the draconian implications of the (then) proposed rules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This rule requires an intermediary to take immediately steps to remove access to information merely upon receiving a written request from “any authority mandated under the law”. Thus, for example, any authority can easily immunize itself from criticism on the internet by simply sending a written notice to the intermediary concerned. This is directly contrary to, and completely subverts the legislative intent expressed in Section 69B which lays down an elaborate procedure to be followed before any information can be lawfully blocked &lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2011]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy apparatus of controlling online expression in India took full form by the beginning of the decade under study here. The &amp;lsquo;chilling effect&amp;rsquo; of this apparatus was made insightfully evident by a study conducted by Rishabh Dara at the Centre for Internet and Society, where fake takedown notices (regarding existing digital content) were sent to seven important Internet intermediaries operating in India, and their responses were studied. The results of this experiment demonstrated that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[T]he Rules create uncertainty in the criteria and procedure for administering the takedown, thereby inducing the intermediaries to err on the side of caution and over-comply with takedown notices in order to limit their liability, and as a result suppress legitimate expressions. Additionally, the Rules do not establish sufficient safeguards to prevent misuse and abuse of the takedown process to suppress legitimate expressions &lt;code&gt;[Dara 2012]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgment:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to Anita Gurumurthy and Parminder Jeet Singh for their generous sharing of information and insights. Raman Jit Singh Cheema, Pranesh Prakash, and Sunil Abraham have also provided crucial suggestions. Extensive background research by P.P. Sneha has significantly enriched my efforts. The Wayback Machine of the Internet Archive deserves a very special thanks. Last but not the least, I am thankful to Kilnam Chon for this wonderful opportunity and his patient support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reference:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Bloggers 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Bloggers Collective Group, Bloggers Against Censorship. Last updated on April 30, 2009‎. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://censorship.wikia.com/wiki/Bloggers_Against_Censorship&#34;&gt;http://censorship.wikia.com/wiki/Bloggers_Against_Censorship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Dara 2012]&lt;/code&gt; Dara, Rishabh, Intermediary Liability in India: Chilling Effects on Free Expression on the Internet. The Centre for Internet and Society. April 27. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/chilling-effects-on-free-expression-on-internet&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/chilling-effects-on-free-expression-on-internet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[DEF]&lt;/code&gt; Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF). Community Information Resource Centre. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://defindia.org/circ-2/&#34;&gt;http://defindia.org/circ-2/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[DEF b]&lt;/code&gt; Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF). Internet Rights. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://internetrights.in/&#34;&gt;http://internetrights.in/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[DEF c]&lt;/code&gt; Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF). Our Story. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://defindia.org/about-def/&#34;&gt;http://defindia.org/about-def/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[DEF d]&lt;/code&gt; Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF). Manthan Awards. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://defindia.org/manthan-award-south-asia-masa/&#34;&gt;http://defindia.org/manthan-award-south-asia-masa/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[FSFI]&lt;/code&gt; Free Software Foundation of India. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://fsf.org.in/&#34;&gt;http://fsf.org.in/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[FSMI]&lt;/code&gt; Free Software Movement of India. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fsmi.in/node&#34;&gt;http://www.fsmi.in/node&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2001]&lt;/code&gt; Gurumurthy, Anita, A Gender Perspective to ICTs and Development: Reflections towards Tunis. January 15. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldsummit2003.de/en/web/701.htm&#34;&gt;http://www.worldsummit2003.de/en/web/701.htm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2005]&lt;/code&gt; Gurumurthy, Anita, and Parminder Jeet Singh, WSIS PrepCom 2: A South Asian Perspective. Association for Progressive Communications. April 01. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apc.org/en/news/hr/world/wsis-prepcom-2-south-asian-perspective&#34;&gt;https://www.apc.org/en/news/hr/world/wsis-prepcom-2-south-asian-perspective&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Gurumuthy, Anita et al (eds.), Gender in the Information Society: Emerging Issues. UNDP Asia-Pacific Development Information Programme. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genderit.org/sites/default/upload/GenderIS.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.genderit.org/sites/default/upload/GenderIS.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[India-GII 2001]&lt;/code&gt; India-GII, Status of VSNL Censorship of IP-Telephony Sites. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://members.tripod.com/~india_gii/statusof.htm&#34;&gt;http://members.tripod.com/~india_gii/statusof.htm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[India-GII 2005]&lt;/code&gt; India-GII. 2005. Last modified on May 24. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://india-gii.org/&#34;&gt;http://india-gii.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IDP]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Democracy Project. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://internetdemocracy.in/&#34;&gt;http://internetdemocracy.in/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003]&lt;/code&gt; International Telecommunication Union (ITU), Geneva Phase of the WSIS: List of Participants. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/summit_participants.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/summit_participants.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITU 2005]&lt;/code&gt; International Telecommunication Union (ITU), List of Participants (WSIS) – Update 5 Dec 2005. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/final-list-participants.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/final-list-participants.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITU 2005 b]&lt;/code&gt; International Telecommunication Union (ITU), Tunis Agenda for the Information Society. November 18. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/off/6rev1.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/off/6rev1.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2008]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum, Hyderabad Provisional List of Participants. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/index.php/component/content/article/385-hyderabad-provisional-list-of-participants&#34;&gt;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/index.php/component/content/article/385-hyderabad-provisional-list-of-participants&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum, Managing Critical Resources. IGF Sharm El Sheikh, Egypt . November 16. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/2009/sharm_el_Sheikh/Transcripts/Sharm%20El%20Sheikh%2016%20November%202009%20Managing%20Critical%20Internet%20Resources.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/2009/sharm_el_Sheikh/Transcripts/Sharm%20El%20Sheikh%2016%20November%202009%20Managing%20Critical%20Internet%20Resources.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Bangalore]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Society Bangalore Chapter. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocbangalore.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocbangalore.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Delhi]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Society Delhi Chapter. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocbangalore.org&#34;&gt;http://www.isocbangalore.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Chennai]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Society Chennai Chapter. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocbangalore.org&#34;&gt;http://www.isocbangalore.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Kolkata]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Society Kolkata Chapter. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://isockolkata.in/&#34;&gt;http://isockolkata.in/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Trivandrum]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Society Trivandrum Chapter. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.internetsociety.org/what-we-do/where-we-work/chapters/india-trivandrum-chapter&#34;&gt;http://www.internetsociety.org/what-we-do/where-we-work/chapters/india-trivandrum-chapter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITfC]&lt;/code&gt; IT for Change, About IT for Change. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itforchange.net/aboutus&#34;&gt;http://www.itforchange.net/aboutus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITfC b]&lt;/code&gt; IT for Change, Anita Gurumurthy. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itforchange.net/Anita&#34;&gt;http://www.itforchange.net/Anita&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITfC c]&lt;/code&gt; IT for Change, Gender and Citizenship in the Information Society: Southern Feminist Dialogues in Practice and Theory. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gender-is-citizenship.net/&#34;&gt;http://www.gender-is-citizenship.net/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITfC d]&lt;/code&gt; IT for Change, Internet Governance. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itforchange.net/Techgovernance&#34;&gt;http://www.itforchange.net/Techgovernance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITfC e]&lt;/code&gt; IT for Change, Our Field Centre. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itforchange.net/field_centre&#34;&gt;http://www.itforchange.net/field_centre&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[JNC]&lt;/code&gt; Just Net Coalition (JNC). Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://justnetcoalition.org/&#34;&gt;http://justnetcoalition.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Kumar 2007]&lt;/code&gt; Kumar, Sasi V. 2007. The Story of Free Software in Kerala, India. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://swatantryam.blogspot.in/2007/08/story-of-free-software-in-kerala-india.html&#34;&gt;http://swatantryam.blogspot.in/2007/08/story-of-free-software-in-kerala-india.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[MoLaJ 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Ministry of Law and Justice (MoLaJ), The Information Technology (Amendment) Act, 2008. The Gazette of India. February 05. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/downloads/itact2000/it_amendment_act2008.pdf&#34;&gt;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/downloads/itact2000/it_amendment_act2008.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[MoCaIT 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Ministry of Communications and Information Technology (MoCaIT), Notification. The Gazette of India. October 27. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/downloads/itact2000/act301009.pdf&#34;&gt;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/downloads/itact2000/act301009.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[MoCaIT 2011]&lt;/code&gt; Ministry of Communications and Information Technology (MoCaIT), Information Technology (Intermediaries Guidelines) Rules, 2011. The Gazette of India. April 11. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/GSR314E_10511%281%29.pdf&#34;&gt;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/GSR314E_10511%281%29.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Noronha 2002]&lt;/code&gt; Noronha, Frederick, Linking a Diverse Country: Mailing Lists in India. The Digital Development Network. May 22. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.comminit.com/ict-4-development/content/linking-diverse-country-mailing-lists-india&#34;&gt;http://www.comminit.com/ict-4-development/content/linking-diverse-country-mailing-lists-india&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Pahwa 2015]&lt;/code&gt; Pahwa, Nikhil, A List of Section 66A Arrests in India through the Years. Medianama. March 24. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medianama.com/2015/03/223-section-66a-arrests-in-india/&#34;&gt;http://www.medianama.com/2015/03/223-section-66a-arrests-in-india/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Prakash, Pranesh, Short Note on IT Amendment Act, 2008 . The Centre for Internet and Society. February. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/publications/it-act/short-note-on-amendment-act-2008/&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/publications/it-act/short-note-on-amendment-act-2008/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2011]&lt;/code&gt; Prakash, Pranesh, CIS Para-wise Comments on Intermediary Due Diligence Rules, 2011. The Centre for Internet and Society. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/blog/intermediary-due-diligence&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/blog/intermediary-due-diligence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2011 b]&lt;/code&gt; Prakash, Pranesh, et al, Open Government Data Study. The Centre for Internet and Society. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/openness/blog/open-government-data-study&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/openness/blog/open-government-data-study&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[SFLC]&lt;/code&gt; Software Freedom Law Centre (SFLC). Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://sflc.in/&#34;&gt;http://sflc.in/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Shah 2011]&lt;/code&gt; Shah, Nishant. 2011. Digital AlterNatives with a Cause? The Centre for Internet and Society. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/digital-natives/blog/dnbook&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/digital-natives/blog/dnbook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Singh 2011]&lt;/code&gt; Singh, Dushyant, India&amp;rsquo;s Proposal for a United Nations Committee for Internet-Related Policies. Sixty Sixth Session of the UN General Assembly, New York. October 26. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itforchange.net/sites/default/files/ItfC/india_un_cirp_proposal_20111026.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itforchange.net/sites/default/files/ItfC/india_un_cirp_proposal_20111026.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[SKC]&lt;/code&gt; Society for Knowledge Commons. About Us. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.knowledgecommons.in/about-us/&#34;&gt;http://www.knowledgecommons.in/about-us/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Asia Source]&lt;/code&gt; Tactical Technology Collective, Asia Source. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://tacticaltech.org/asiasource&#34;&gt;https://tacticaltech.org/asiasource&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Tanna 2004]&lt;/code&gt; Tanna, Ketan, Internet Censorship in India: Is It Necessary and Does It Work?. Sarai-CSDS Independent Fellowship. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ketan.net/INTERNET_CENSORSHIP_IN_INDIA.html&#34;&gt;http://www.ketan.net/INTERNET_CENSORSHIP_IN_INDIA.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[CIS]&lt;/code&gt; The Centre for Internet and Society. About Us. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/about/&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/about/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[CIS 2008]&lt;/code&gt; The Centre for Internet and Society. 2008. Annual Report. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/accessibility/annual-report-2008.pdf&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/accessibility/annual-report-2008.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Sarai 2005]&lt;/code&gt; The Sarai Programme, Contested Commons, Trespassing Publics. January 12. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://sarai.net/contested-commons-trespassing-publics/&#34;&gt;http://sarai.net/contested-commons-trespassing-publics/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Wikipedia 2015]&lt;/code&gt; Satish Babu. Wikipedia. Last modified on June 25. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satish_Babu&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satish_Babu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>