<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sumandro</title>
    <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sumandro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 20:09:56 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Protecting the Territory, Killing the Map</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/protecting-the-territory-killing-the-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/protecting-the-territory-killing-the-map/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;co-authored-with-adya-garg-published-by-the-wire-http-thewire-in-2016-05-16-before-geospatial-bill-a-long-history-of-killing-the-map-in-order-to-protect-the-territory-36453:26906d7510c4a6c3ffdbbbee2ba326c2&#34;&gt;Co-authored with Adya Garg. Published by &lt;a href=&#34;http://thewire.in/2016/05/16/before-geospatial-bill-a-long-history-of-killing-the-map-in-order-to-protect-the-territory-36453/&#34;&gt;The Wire&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The global history of cartography is intimately linked with political needs and economic interests, from the public depiction of sovereign territories to navigating treacherous seas to (wrongly) ‘discover’ the land of spices. In India, the politics of making and using maps has taken a sudden and complex turn with the publication of the draft Geospatial Information Regulation Bill, 2016. Contrary to the expectations arising out of several government schemes that are promoting the development of the new digital economy in India – from start-ups to the ongoing expansion of connectivity network – the bill seems to be undoing various economic and humanitarian efforts, and other opportunities involving maps, by imposing strict guidelines and harsh penalties on the use of maps by private actors, commercial or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://mha.nic.in/sites/upload_files/mha/files/GeospatialBill_05052016_eve.pdf&#34;&gt;introductory note to the bill&lt;/a&gt; clearly states its primary objective is to ensure the protection of ‘security, sovereignty and integrity of India.’ The concern around ‘security’ is not new when it comes to regulating cartographic activities. It is prominently addressed across the current set of policies and guidelines that govern mapping in India: 1) the National Map Policy, 2005 (“NMP”) and associated guidelines issued by the Survey of India, 2) the Remote Sensing Data Policy, 2011 that regulates satellite-based mapping, and 3) the Civil Aviation Requirement, 2012, which regulates mapping and photography using flights and drones. Protection of ‘sovereignty and integrity,’ however, does not find a mention in any of these map-related policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have of course been several incidents where the government has taken steps (including the temporary blocking of service) against companies that have represented Indian national boundaries that are not in accordance with official maps. Such companies include &lt;em&gt;Google&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Economist&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Al Jazeera&lt;/em&gt;. Two companies that have gotten away with no consequences after publicly showing maps of India without certain border regions, interestingly, are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scoopwhoop.com/news/kashmir-missing-from-india-map/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Facebook&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://thewire.in/2015/05/14/chinese-state-owned-television-shows-india-map-sans-jammu-kashmir-arunachal-1698/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;CCTV&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the absence of such provisions in the existing map-related policies, thus far, the government has pursued legal action against such ‘anti-national’ depiction of  Indian territory under  Section 69A of the IT Act, 2000, the Official Secrets Act, 1923 (restricting the collection and sharing of information about ‘prohibited places’), the Customs Act, 1962 (prohibiting the export and import of certain maps), and the Criminal Law (Amendment) Act,1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though this present bill has come into public attention rather suddenly, the Indian State has been planning for a comprehensive legal framework for both enabling and restricting mapping, since the coming of the NMP itself. The first avatar of this effort was the Indian Survey Act that was heard about in 2007, but  was never made public. More recently, the first report towards the National Geospatial Information Policy (now called the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dst.gov.in/sites/default/files/Draft-NGP-Ver%201%20ammended_05May2016.pdf&#34;&gt;National Geospatial Policy&lt;/a&gt;) came out in 2012. Instead of waiting for this comprehensive policy to be discussed and notified, the bill seems to have come in a hurry to propose a narrowly designed legal instrument. As is often the problem with such precise devices that also want to be exhaustive, the bill promises much more collateral damage than actual solutions – it ends up killing the map in the name of protecting the territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick look at case law on map-related disputes informs us about the motivations of the state in enacting this bill. A major controversy around ‘sovereignty’ in the field of mapping has been about the depiction of international boundaries of India by Google. After several incidents of conflicts between Google’s map makers and the Indian State regarding the depiction of India’s national boundary, the Survey of India filed a police complaint in 2014. As a result, Google presently shows different map tiles to users from India (according to the boundary specified by the Indian State) and different tiles to users from elsewhere. This geo-targeted solution to the depiction of international borders under dispute has been practiced by Google in the case of other countries too, most notably for &lt;a href=&#34;http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/02/28/the-first-google-maps-war/&#34;&gt;Nicaragua, Costa Rica&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://jtl.columbia.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2016/03/Merel_54-CJTL-425.pdf&#34;&gt;Ukraine and (independent) Crimea&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internal security concerns have also fuelled conflicts with mapping companies. In 2013, the ‘mapathon’ organised by Google faced a lawsuit for not asking for prior permission from the Survey of India for this exercise in user-contributed mapping. This was preceded by a petition filed by J. Mohanraj in the Madras High Court seeking a complete ban on the Google Earth and Bhuvan (run by ISRO) map applications on the ground that they were both  providing information that could be used for planning acts of terror. The petitioner’s argument referred to the provisions of the NMP, and also alleged that such mapping practices violated the individual rights of a person under Article 21 of the Constitution. The court, however, held (2008) that the petitioner was unable to produce any specific “Guidelines/Rules/Law laid down by the Central/State Governments, prohibiting the private organisations or any other individuals to Interactive Mapping Program, covering vast majority of the Planet”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trouble with Google re-opened earlier this year as the Pathankot air base was attacked. Incidentally, Vishal Saini, the winner of the 2013 mapathon by Google, contributed to mapping the features of the very same city. Promptly after the attack in January, Lokesh Kumar Sharma filed a case in the Delhi High Court alleging that the availability of sensitive information (from an internal security point-of-view) on Google Maps created security vulnerabilities. In a rather curious manner, the court disposed of the case on February 24, claiming that it has learned from the Additional Solicitor General that ‘steps are in progress to regulate the publication of aerial/satellite geospatial data.’ In hindsight, we see that this was in reference to the draft bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bill, evidently, is a product of the Indian State’s inefficient attempts at regulating the making and circulation of maps and geospatial data in digital times. The bill ends up disregarding the actual features of digital geospatial data and how it forms a fundamental basis (and asset) for today’s digital economy, and, instead, decides to settle for a form of regulation that is much better suited (if at all) to a pre-digital and pre-liberalisation condition. The regulatory measures proposed by the bill do not only cause worry but also bewilderment. Take for example Section 3 that states that ‘no person shall acquire geospatial imagery or data including value addition of any part of India’ without being expressly given permission for the same or being vetted by the nodal agency set up by the Bill. If implemented strictly, this may mean that you will have to ask for permission and/or security vetting before dropping a pin on the map and sharing your coordinates with your friend or a taxi service. Both involve creating/acquiring geospatial information, and potentially adding value to the map/taxi service as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take an even more bizarre hypothetical situation – the Security Vetting Agency being asked to go through the entire geospatial data chest of Google everyday (or as soon as it is updated) and it taking up to ‘ three months from the date of receipt’ of the data to complete this checking so that Google Maps can tell you how crowded a particular street was three months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, a key term that the bill does not talk about is ‘big data.’ The static or much-slowly-changing geospatial data such as national boundaries and which-military-institute-is-located-where are really the tiny minority of the global geospatial information. The much larger and crucial part is of course the fast-moving big geospatial data – from geo-referenced tweets, to GPS systems of cars, to mobile phones moving through the cities and regions. Addressing such networked data systems, where all data can quite easily be born-georeferenced, and the security and privacy concerns that are engendered by them, should be the ultimate purpose of, and challenge for, a future-looking Geospatial Information Regulation Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The present bill imposes an undesirable bureaucratic structure of licenses and permits upon the GIS industry in the country in particular, and on all sections of the economy using networked devices in general. This will only end up restricting the size of the GIS industry to a few dominant players. For all creators and users of maps for non-commercial, developmental, and humanitarian interests, this bill appears to be an imminent threat, even if it is never actually applied.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Buying into the Aakash Dream: A Tablet’s Tale of Mass Education</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/buying-into-the-aakash-dream/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2016 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/buying-into-the-aakash-dream/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;co-authored-with-jahnavi-phalkey-http-www-kcl-ac-uk-sspp-sga-kii-people-jahnaviphalkey-index-aspx-published-by-economic-and-political-weekly-http-www-epw-in-journal-2016-17-web-exclusives-buying-aakash-dream-html:dcf794d4d237a70396527a795b3ef51c&#34;&gt;Co-authored with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kcl.ac.uk/sspp/sga/kii/people/jahnaviphalkey/index.aspx&#34;&gt;Jahnavi Phalkey&lt;/a&gt;. Published by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.epw.in/journal/2016/17/web-exclusives/buying-aakash-dream.html&#34;&gt;Economic and Political Weekly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research note is based on a project conducted as part of the Max Weber Foundation’s Transnational Research Group on &amp;ldquo;Poverty and Education in India,&amp;rdquo; and draws from a &lt;a href=&#34;../aakash-tablet-and-technological-imaginaries-of-mass-education/&#34;&gt;paper recently published&lt;/a&gt; by the authors in &lt;em&gt;History and Technology&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction:dcf794d4d237a70396527a795b3ef51c&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Aakash tablet, hailed as the vanguard of India&amp;rsquo;s “tablet revolution,” was unveiled at the United Nations. It was to showcase India&amp;rsquo;s technological prowess but was quickly lamented as a failed “dream,” and as India&amp;rsquo;s “object lesson” in how not to do technological innovation. The so-called failure of the device became a metonym for the government that backed it, and for the technology establishment of the country. While our longer paper (Phalkey and Sumandro 2016) questions this notion of “failure,” in this article we wish to highlight the role played by the discourse and experiments in technologies of mass education in creating the practical context and the market conditions for low-cost tablets in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 2011 report by the Ministry of Human Resource Development (MHRD) claimed that although the initiation of the Aakash tablet project met with “skepticism and scorn,” over time it not only developed an affordable device aimed at students in India, but has produced an entirely new market niche of sub-US$100 tablets. This ambitious statement appears to be vindicated by a recent report by the International Data Corporation (IDC), an economic intelligence company, on the tablet market in India. The report notes that the market has grown in the previous year at an annual rate of 8.2%. More importantly, the two companies leading in market share are DataWind (20.7%) and Samsung (15.8%). Incidentally, after the first quarter of 2014, Samsung had the largest (22.5%) and DataWind the 4th largest (6.8%) share. What is noteworthy here is not the rise of DataWind as the leading seller of tablets alone, but that it is the MHRD that heralded this creation of a market niche in India for affordable tablets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;from-satellite-to-internet-in-education:dcf794d4d237a70396527a795b3ef51c&#34;&gt;From Satellite to Internet in Education&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 30 May, 1974, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) launched an ATS-6 satellite that formed the central infrastructural component of the Satellite Instructional Television Experiment (SITE), one of the early initiatives to harness communication technology for primary and adult education. The SITE project involved broadcasting educational and informational audiovisual content, produced by the All India Radio (AIR), across 2400 selected villages located in Andhra Pradesh, Bihar, Karnataka, Madhya Pradesh, Odisha (erstwhile Orissa), and Rajasthan. Operating from 1 August 1975 to 31 July 31 1976, the experiment was led by the Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO), and was supported by UNESCO, United Nations Development Programme (UNDP), United Negro College Fund (UNCF), and the International Telecommunication Union (ITU).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective of the SITE project was inspired directly by the importance given to skill-development oriented higher education and adult education in the report of the first Education Commission (1964–1966). However, Asif Siddiqi (2015) notes that the project performed a crucial task of establishing the Indian space research programme through a direct alliance with NASA, which held special geopolitical significance given the Chinese nuclear tests of 1964.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experiment paved the way for the development of the Indian National Satellite System (INSAT,) the first Indian satellite. The entanglement of the Indian space programme with the idea of national-level technological infrastructure for education has continued since. The EDUSAT, launched in 2004, was a collaborative project between ISRO and MHRD to drive satellite-based education across disadvantaged and remote regions of the country. In an audit report in 2013, however, the Department of Space declared that the project has failed, and highlighted three lacks in particular– network connectivity, content generation, and management structure (Union Government 2013).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earliest initiatives in India to put computers in schools, supplementing and supplanting television screens, began in the 1980s. These efforts pre-dated extensive terrestrial communication fibre networks and relied almost completely upon the success of the Indian space programme. The University Grants Commission (UGC) Countrywide Classroom, Computer Literacy and Studies in Schools, and Computer Literacy and Awareness Programme are the key examples from this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revised Programme of Action of the National Policy on Education (1986) reiterated the need for increased attention to upgrading education technology infrastructure, as well as the development of electronic content for the same. This led to the initiation of the ICT@Schools scheme beginning with the 8th Five Year Plan (1993–1998). Even after 20 years of the introduction of computers in schools across India, a 2006 report on education technology by the National Council of Educational Research and Training (NCERT) noted that computer-based teaching and learning in an actual classroom setting remains more of a “spectator sport.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the advent of the internet, the MHRD started experimenting with internet-based delivery of distance education from 2003, beginning with the National Programme on Technology Enhanced Learning (NPTEL). It did so alongside satellite-based distribution of educational content. NPTEL involved five Indian Institutes of Technology (IIT) (Bombay, Delhi, Kanpur, Kharagpur, and Madras) developing openly available course materials for more than 100 undergraduate courses in five engineering subjects, as well as courses in basic science. These course materials were later made part of the online learning portal called “Sakshat,” which eventually became one of the pillars of the National Mission on Education through Information and Communication Technologies (NMEICT), initiated during the 11th Five Year Plan (2007–2012). This portal marked the completion of a conceptual and technological shift from the satellite-based models of delivery of educational content, to an internet-based one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-and-unmaking-of-the-aakash-tablet:dcf794d4d237a70396527a795b3ef51c&#34;&gt;Making and Unmaking of the Aakash Tablet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With NMEICT, large-scale education technology initiatives of the Indian state moved away from the earlier emphasis on primary education and school-oriented computer literacy, to that on higher education and aids for self-learning. The plan for an affordable tablet computer was announced in mid-2010 as part of this mission. This “low-cost access-cum-computing device” was aimed at bypassing the institutional, bureaucratic, and infrastructural barriers to access to quality higher education. Its main audience were students in disadvantaged regions and non-elite institutions, as well as self-learners. The actualisation of the device, however, was continuously delayed and blocked by conflicts between the governmental and non-governmental actors, strong skepticism from the media, and several changes in the state&amp;rsquo;s approach to the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first approach to the project was an international company that approached the MHRD in 2006, with a proposal to sell educational laptops for school students at 100 US$ each. NK Sinha, then mission director of NMEICT, argued against the purchase. The MHRD saw this as an opportunity for developing an indigenous low-cost computer, and initiated a competition among the IITs to come up with a prototype for this device, which was won by the IIT Kanpur team led by Prem Kumar Kalra, then professor and head of the department of Electrical Engineering. The first publicly exhibited (2010) prototype of the device was the one developed in IIT Kanpur, which was priced initially at 35 US$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MHRD, however, soon decided to buy the device from a commercial manufacturer. The responsibility of procurement and testing went to IIT Rajasthan, under the leadership of Kalra who joined the newly established institution as its first director. After the contract with HCL Infosystems was called off in January 2011, DataWind, a Canada and UK based company specialising in internet-access devices, won the new tender to produce the first version of the device. On 5 October 2011, the first version of tablet was launched, priced at Rs 2,500, and co-branded as Aakash and Ubislate—respectively for those bought and redistributed at a subsidised rate by MHRD, and those sold commercially by DataWind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An early controversy about the tablet, apart from its technical capabilities, was around the claim that they were produced and assembled in China. DataWind rejected the allegations and claimed that all the devices were assembled by Quad Electronics in its factory in Secunderabad, Telangana (then Andhra Pradesh). Within a year, however, DataWind got involved in serious conflict with IIT Rajasthan on one hand, and Quad Electronics on the other. The MHRD intervened again to change the approach by bringing in IIT Bombay (March 2012) as the new procuring and testing agency, thus removing IIT Rajasthan from the project. DataWind also found a new partner in VMC Systems, who started assembling the “kits” imported from China in its establishments in Amritsar and Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With M M Pallam Raju becoming the Minister of Human Resource Development in late 2012 by succeeding Kapil Sibal, one might say, the Aakash project gradually moved to what we know as its final form. At first, it was suggested that the state should entirely move out of the business of providing low-cost tablets as there is already a vibrant market. Later on, and with thought leadership from Rajat Moona, director general of the Centre for Development of Advanced Computing (CDAC), and others, it was decided that “Aakash” would become a brand name available for commercial manufacturers of affordable tablets that satisfy a minimum set of technical specifications. The first draft of the specifications list was published in June 2013. The tendering process, however, got delayed, and eventually came to a near-permanent pause with the general elections in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of November 2015, the MHRD has again shown interest in the idea of a state-subsidised tablet computer for education. The tablet was now called Udaan, and aimed at girl students at the higher secondary level, priced at Rs 10,000 (against Rs 2,500 of Aakash), and distributed only to 1,000 students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-device-desire:dcf794d4d237a70396527a795b3ef51c&#34;&gt;Creating Device Desire&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an interview in late 2013, Kapil Sibal (then Union Minister of Communication and Information Technology, former Union Minister of Human Resource Development) shared that “[the] Aakash tablet was [his] dream but it was not fulfilled.” Sibal, undoubtedly the key political driver of the project, in his admission to failure, raises deep concerns about the present state and the future of the technological infrastructure—and the imagination—for mass education in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tracing the transition of these technologies from SITE to Aakash, we continuously find it difficult to delineate the state’s transforming and transformative agenda of mass education from that of building technological capability. At times, though, we wondered if the agenda for mass education did not become one that served the purpose of generating, for lack of a better phrase, a certain familiarity and literacy about personal technological devices among the population. The motivations and goals that informed these mammoth projects become more and more difficult to decipher when we look at the relatively poor attention given to the production of content. Careful monitoring and documentation of how such content is being received and utilised by the actual learners and their educators was not prioritised; and whenever undertaken, such exercises revealed the deep lack of pedagogic concerns at the heart of these education technology programmes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the overwhelming narrative of failure, however, we cannot ignore the remarkable, but quiet, success of the project in normalising and framing the tablet computer as familiar, and almost essential, object for personal learning and development. Apart from presenting the tablet computer as an everyday media object, almost similar to the way television entered the households, the NMEICT and the Aakash project played a crucial role in normalising the notion of online self-learning, and thus that of the online, in the Indian public imagination. In an insightful comment, Suneet Singh Tuli, the CEO of DataWind, remarked that the Aakash tablet was not an “iPad for the poor,” it was the “the computer and Internet of the masses”—it was not selling a demo version of the real thing, it was shaping the very imagination (Kurup 2011).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stories, together, conspire to make us wonder if all this eventually amounts to create desires for devices; and if the educational and developmental rhetoric helped frame electronic devices as everyday and household objects. The consequences, as we see, cannot exactly be called unintended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references:dcf794d4d237a70396527a795b3ef51c&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All URLs accessed on 21 April 2016.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government of India (2011): “The Newsletter on Higher Education,” Issue 6, Department of Higher Education, &lt;a href=&#34;http://mhrd.gov.in/sites/upload_files/mhrd/files/document-reports/Newsletter-062011.pdf&#34;&gt;http://mhrd.gov.in/sites/upload_files/mhrd/files/document-reports/Newsletter-062011.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kurup, Saira (2011): “&amp;rsquo;We Want to Target the Billion Indians Who are Cut Off&amp;rsquo;,” Times of India, 9 October, &lt;a href=&#34;http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/home/sunday-times/deep-focus/We-want-to-target-the-billion-Indians-who-are-cut-off/articleshow/10284832.cms&#34;&gt;http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/home/sunday-times/deep-focus/We-want-to-target-the-billion-Indians-who-are-cut-off/articleshow/10284832.cms&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phalkey, Jahnavi and Sumandro Chattapadhyay (2016): “The Aakash Tablet and Technological Imaginaries of Mass Education in Contemporary India,” History and Technology, Vol 31, No 4, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/07341512.2015.1136142?journalCode=ghat20&#34;&gt;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/07341512.2015.1136142?journalCode=ghat20&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Siddiqi, Asif (2015): “Making Space for the Nation: Satellite Television, Indian Scientific Elites, and the Cold War,” Comparative Studies of South Asia, Africa and the Middle East, Vol 35, No 1, pp 35–49, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cssaame.dukejournals.org/content/35/1/35.abstract&#34;&gt;http://cssaame.dukejournals.org/content/35/1/35.abstract&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Union Government (2013): “Report of the Comptroller and Auditor General of India for the year ended March 2012,” Scientific and Environmental Ministries/Departments, Report No. 22 of 2013 (Compliance Audit), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cag.gov.in/sites/default/files/audit_report_files/Union_Compliance_Scientific_Department_Audit_22_2013.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.cag.gov.in/sites/default/files/audit_report_files/Union_Compliance_Scientific_Department_Audit_22_2013.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welfare is the Message, Surveillance is the Medium</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/welfare-is-the-message-surveillance-is-the-medium/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2016 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/welfare-is-the-message-surveillance-is-the-medium/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;published-by-the-wire-http-thewire-in-2016-04-19-the-last-chance-for-a-welfare-state-doesnt-rest-in-the-aadhaar-system-30256:fdeadc845334f57050ce5e7050d1e1c7&#34;&gt;Published by &lt;a href=&#34;http://thewire.in/2016/04/19/the-last-chance-for-a-welfare-state-doesnt-rest-in-the-aadhaar-system-30256/&#34;&gt;The Wire&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, a king desired that his parrot should be taught all the ancient knowledge of the kingdom. The priests started feeding the pages of the great books to the parrot with much enthusiasm. One day, the king asked the priests if the parrot’s education has completed. The priests poked the belly of the parrot but it made no sound. Only the rustle of undigested pages inside the belly could be heard. The priests declared that the parrot is indeed a learned one now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fate of the welfare system in our country is quite similar to this parrot from Tagore’s parable. It has been forcefully fed identification cards and other official documents (often four copies of the same) for years, and always with the same justification of making it more effective and fixing the leaks. These identification regimes are in effect killing off the welfare system. And some may say that that has been the actual plan in any case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Aadhaar number has been recently offered as &lt;a href=&#34;http://indianexpress.com/article/opinion/columns/aadhaar-project-uidai-last-chance-for-a-welfare-state/&#34;&gt;the ‘last chance’ for the ailing welfare system&lt;/a&gt; – a last identification regime that it needs to gulp down to survive. This argument wilfully overlooks the acute problems with the Aadhaar project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the ‘last chance’ for a welfare state in India is not provided by implementing a new and improved identification regime (Aadhaar numbers or otherwise), but by enabling citizens to effectively track, monitor, and ensure delivery of welfare, services, and benefits. This ‘opening up’ of the welfare bureaucracy has been most effectively initiated by the Right to Information Act. Instead of a centralised biometrics-linked identity verification platform, which gives the privilege of tracking and monitoring welfare flows only to a few expert groups, an effective welfare state requires the devolution of such privilege and responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should harness the tracking capabilities of electronic financial systems to disclose how money belonging to the Consolidated Fund of India travel around state agencies and departmental levels. Instead, the Aadhaar system effectively stacks up a range of entry barriers to accessing welfare – from malfunctioning biometric scanners, to connectivity problems, to the burden of keeping one’s fingerprint digitally legible under all labouring and algorithmic circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, authentication of welfare recipients by Aadhaar number neither make the welfare delivery process free of techno-bureaucratic hurdles, nor does it exorcise away corruption. Anumeha Yadav has recently documented the emerging &lt;a href=&#34;http://scroll.in/article/805909/in-rajasthan-there-is-unrest-at-the-ration-shop-because-of-error-ridden-aadhaar&#34;&gt;‘unrest at the ration shop’ across Rajasthan&lt;/a&gt;, as authentication processes face technical and connectivity delays, people get ‘locked out’ of public services for not having or having Aadhaar number with incorrect demographic details, and no mechanisms exist to provide rapid and definitive recourse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RTI activists at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.snsindia.org/&#34;&gt;Satark Nagrik Sangathan&lt;/a&gt; have highlighted that the Delhi ration shops, using Aadhaar-based authentication, maintain only two columns of data to describe people who have come to the shop – those who received their ration, and those who did not (without any indication of the reason). This leads to erasure-by-design of evidence of the number of welfare-seekers who are excluded from welfare services when the Aadhaar-based authentication process fails (for valid reasons, or otherwise).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reetika Khera has made it very clear that using Aadhaar Payments Bridge to directly transfer cash to a beneficiary’s account, in the best case scenario, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.epw.in/journal/2013/05/commentary/cost-benefit-analysis-uid.html&#34;&gt;may only take care of one form of corruption&lt;/a&gt;: deception (a different person claiming to be the beneficiary). But it does not address the other two common forms of public corruption: collusion (government officials approving undue benefits and creating false beneficiaries) and extortion (forceful rent seeking after the cash has been transferred to the beneficiary’s account). Evidently, going after only deception does not make much sense in an environment where collusion and extortion are commonplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the ‘relevant privacy question’ for Aadhaar is not limited to how UIDAI protects the data collected by it, but expands to usage of Aadhaar numbers across the public and private sectors. The privacy problem created by the Aadhaar numbers does &lt;em&gt;begin&lt;/em&gt; but surely not &lt;em&gt;end&lt;/em&gt; with internal data management procedures and responsibilities of the UIDAI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one hand, the Aadhaar Bill 2016 has reduced the personal data sharing restrictions of the NIAI Bill 2010, and has &lt;a href=&#34;http://scroll.in/article/806297/no-longer-a-black-box-why-does-the-revised-aadhar-bill-allow-sharing-of-identity-information&#34;&gt;allowed for sharing of all data except core biometrics (fingerprints and iris scan)&lt;/a&gt; with all agencies involved in authentication of a person through her/his Aadhaar number. These agencies have been asked to seek consent from the person who is being authenticated, and to inform her/him of the ways in which the provided data (by the person, and by UIDAI) will be used by the agency. In careful wording, the Bill only asks the agencies to &lt;em&gt;inform&lt;/em&gt; the person about “alternatives to submission of identity information to the requesting entity” (Section 8.3) but not to &lt;em&gt;provide&lt;/em&gt; any such alternatives. This facilitates and legalises a much wider collection of personal demographic data for offering of services by public agencies “or any body corporate or person” (Section 57), which is way beyond the scope of data management practices of UIDAI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the Aadhaar number is being &lt;em&gt;seeded&lt;/em&gt; to all government databases – from lists of HIV patients, of rural citizens being offered 100 days of work, of students getting scholarships meant for specific social groups, of people with a bank account. Now in some sectors, such as banking, inter-agency sharing of data about clients is strictly regulated. But we increasingly have non-financial agencies playing crucial roles in the financial sector – from mobile wallets to peer-to-peer transaction to innovative credit ratings. Seeding of Aadhaar into all government and private databases would allow for easy and direct joining up of these databases by anyone who has access to them, and not at all by security agencies only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it becomes publicly acceptable that &lt;a href=&#34;http://indianexpress.com/article/opinion/columns/aadhaar-project-uidai-last-chance-for-a-welfare-state/&#34;&gt;the &lt;em&gt;money bill route&lt;/em&gt; was a ‘remedial’ instrument&lt;/a&gt; to put the Rajya Sabha ‘back on track’, one cannot not wonder about what was being remedied by avoiding a public debate about the draft bill before it was presented in Lok Sabha. The answer is simple: &lt;em&gt;welfare is the message, surveillance is the medium&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acceptance and adoption of all medium requires a message, a content. The users are interested in the message. The message, however, is not the business. Think of Free Basics. Facebook wants people with none or limited access to internet to enjoy parts of the internet at zero data cost. Facebook does not provide the content that the users consume on such internet. The content is created by the users themselves, and also provided by other companies. Facebook own and control the medium, and makes money out of all content, including interactions, passing through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UIDAI has set up a biometric data bank and related infrastructure to offer authentication-as-a-service. As the Bill clarifies, almost all agencies (public or private, national or global) can use this service to verify the identity of Indian residents. Unlike Facebook, the content of these services do not flow through the Aadhaar system. Nonetheless, Aadhaar keeps track of all ‘authentication records’, that is records of whose identity was authenticated by whom, when, and where. This database is gold (data) mine for security agencies in India, and elsewhere. Further, as more agencies use authentication based on Aadhaar numbers, it becomes easier for them to combine and compare databases with other agencies doing the same, by linking each line of transaction across databases using Aadhaar numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welfare is the message that the Aadhaar system is riding on. The message is only useful for the medium as far as it ensures that the majority of the user population are subscribing to it. Once the users are enrolled, or on-boarded, the medium enables flow of all kinds of messages, and tracking and monetisation (perhaps not so much in the case of UIDAI) of all those flows. It does not matter if the Aadhaar system is being introduced to remedy the broken parliamentary process, or the broken welfare distribution system. What matters is that the UIDAI is establishing the infrastructure for a universal surveillance system in India, and without a formal acknowledgement and legal framework for the same.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Tools, Tutorials, and Readings</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/mapping-tools-tutoials-readings/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Mar 2016 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/mapping-tools-tutoials-readings/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tools:0187c389405e59a61ff0cc16e14ce279&#34;&gt;Tools&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.openstreetmap.org/&#34;&gt;OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt; – Contribute and download map data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/JOSM&#34;&gt;Java OpenStreetMap Editor (JOSM Editor)&lt;/a&gt; – A desktop application to work with data downloaded from OpenStreetMap and/or collected from GPS devices. Can be used to clean and manage map data, as well as to upload that to OpenStreetMap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://fieldpapers.org/&#34;&gt;Field Papers&lt;/a&gt; – A tool to print out parts of OpenStreetMap, add data to it by hand (using black pen), and to upload a scanned/photographed copy of it that gets automatically geo-referenced and aligned into OpenStreetMap. The hand-written data, however, would require manual digitisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://maperitive.net/&#34;&gt;Maperitive&lt;/a&gt; – Desktop application to download data from OpenStreetMap in PNG and SVG formats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.google.com/earth/&#34;&gt;Google Earth&lt;/a&gt; – Trace over satellite imagery to create map data, save it as .KML, convert it to .SVG and use it in design softwares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gpsvisualizer.com/&#34;&gt;GPS Visualizer&lt;/a&gt; – Convert .KML files (and more) to .SVG (and more).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://latlong.net/&#34;&gt;LatLong.net&lt;/a&gt; – Search for places and find out the latitude and longitude of the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ushahidi.com/&#34;&gt;Ushahidi&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://crowdmap.com/&#34;&gt;Crowdmap&lt;/a&gt; - Crowdsource geo-referenced information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://cartodb.com/&#34;&gt;CartoDB&lt;/a&gt; - Plot and analyse geospatial data using a menu-driven interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openheatmap.com/&#34;&gt;OpenHeatMap&lt;/a&gt; - Generate simple heatmaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mapbox.com/studio&#34;&gt;Mapbox Studio&lt;/a&gt; – Plot geospatial data and create custom designed map tiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://leafletjs.com/&#34;&gt;Leaflet&lt;/a&gt; – A simple JavaScript library to create web-based interactive maps. Basemaps from different services (Google, Bing, OpenStreetMap, etc.) can be displayed along with various data layers (simple vector, GeoJSON, image, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://qgis.org/en/site/&#34;&gt;Quantum GIS&lt;/a&gt; – A free and open source GIS software, for map data management, analysis etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gadm.org/&#34;&gt;GADM Database of Global Administrative Areas&lt;/a&gt; - Download geospatial data of administrative boundaries of countries across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tutorials:0187c389405e59a61ff0cc16e14ce279&#34;&gt;Tutorials&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OpenStreetMap – &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Beginners%27_Guide&#34;&gt;Beginniners’ Guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LearnOSM – &lt;a href=&#34;http://learnosm.org/en/&#34;&gt;Learn OpenStreetMap Step by Step&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maperitive – &lt;a href=&#34;http://maperitive.net/docs/&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20150627104919/http://geojournalism.org/category/maps/&#34;&gt;GeoJournalism Handbook&lt;/a&gt; – The Handbook has a set of tutorials on various mapping tools (as well as other data collection/visualisation tools).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Switch2OSM – &lt;a href=&#34;http://switch2osm.org/using-tiles/getting-started-with-leaflet/&#34;&gt;Getting Started with Leaflet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy Maloney – &lt;a href=&#34;http://asmaloney.com/2014/01/code/creating-an-interactive-map-with-leaflet-and-openstreetmap/&#34;&gt;Creating an Interactive Map with Leaflet and OpenStreetMap&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quantum GIS - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.qgistutorials.com/en/&#34;&gt;Tutorials and Tips&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;readings:0187c389405e59a61ff0cc16e14ce279&#34;&gt;Readings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Floating Sheep Collective - &lt;a href=&#34;http://manifesto.floatingsheep.org/&#34;&gt;Manifesto: What would a Floating Sheep Map?&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Krygier &amp;amp; Denis Wood – &lt;a href=&#34;http://makingmaps.files.wordpress.com/2009/08/ce_n_est_pas_le_monde.pdf&#34;&gt;Ce n’est pas le monde (This is not the world)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeremy W. Crampton &amp;amp; John Krygier – &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.acme-journal.org/vol4/JWCJK.pdf&#34;&gt;An Introduction to Critical Cartography&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denis Wood &amp;amp; John Krygier – &lt;a href=&#34;http://makingmaps.owu.edu/elsevier_geog_criticalcartography.pdf&#34;&gt;Cartography: Critical Cartography&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Krygier – &lt;a href=&#34;http://makingmaps.net/2011/12/05/map-art-exhibitions-2010-11/&#34;&gt;Map Art Exhibitions 2010-11&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&#34;http://makingmaps.net/2014/05/12/map-art-exhibitions-2012-13/&#34;&gt;Map Art Exhibitions 2012-13&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christian Nold (ed.) – &lt;a href=&#34;http://emotionalcartography.net/&#34;&gt;Emotional Cartography – Technologies of the Self&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Counter Cartographies Collective – &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.countercartographies.org/blog/&#34;&gt;Blog&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.countercartographies.org/downloads/?dl_cat=1&#34;&gt;Maps&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.countercartographies.org/downloads/?dl_cat=2&#34;&gt;Papers&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.countercartographies.org/downloads/?dl_cat=3&#34;&gt;Presentations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Denis Wood – &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guernicamag.com/art/mapping-marginality/&#34;&gt;Interview – Mapping Marginality&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alexis Madrigal – &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2012/09/how-google-builds-its-maps-and-what-it-means-for-the-future-of-everything/261913&#34;&gt;How Google Builds Its Maps – and What It Means for the Future of Everything&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Civil Society Organisations and Internet Governance in Asia, 2000-2010</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/civil-society-organisations-and-internet-governance-in-asia-2000-2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/civil-society-organisations-and-internet-governance-in-asia-2000-2010/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;this-is-a-book-section-written-for-the-asia-internet-history-third-decade-2001-2010-volume-edited-by-prof-kilnam-chon-the-book-was-published-both-in-print-and-as-an-online-open-access-version-in-december-2015-access-the-book-here-https-sites-google-com-site-internethistoryasia-book3-https-sites-google-com-site-internethistoryasia-book3:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;This is a book section written for the &lt;em&gt;Asia Internet History - Third Decade (2001~2010)&lt;/em&gt; volume edited by Prof. Kilnam Chon. The book was published, both in print and as an online open access version, in December 2015. Access the book here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/internethistoryasia/book3&#34;&gt;https://sites.google.com/site/internethistoryasia/book3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparations-for-the-world-summit-on-the-information-society:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Preparations for the World Summit on the Information Society&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) conferences organized by the United Nations in Geneva (2003) and Tunis (2005) initiated crucial platforms and networks, some temporary and some ongoing, for various non-governmental actors to intensively and periodically take part in discussions of governance of the Internet and various related activities. Many of the civil society organisations taking part in WSIS conferences, as well as various regional and thematic preparatory meetings and seminars, had little prior experience in the topic of Internet governance. They were entering these conversations from various backgrounds, such as local developmental interventions, human and cultural rights activism, freedom and diversity of media, and gender and social justice. Members of such civil society organisations often faced difficult challenges in articulating their experiences, insights, positions, and suggestions in terms of the (then) emerging global discourse of Internet governance that was driven by inter-governmental dynamics of technology and infrastructure governance. At the WSIS, Asian Response Meeting in 2002, Susanna George, (then) Executive Director of Isis International, Manila, succinctly expressed this challenge being faced by the members of civil society organisations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some feminist activists, however, including myself, it has felt like trying to squeeze my concerns into a narrow definition of what gender concerns in ICTs are. I would like it to Cinderella’s ugly sister cutting off her toe to fit into the dainty slipper of gender concerns in ICTs. The development ball, it seems, can only accommodate some elements of what NGO activists, particularly those from the South, are concerned about in relation to new information and communications technologies &lt;code&gt;[George 2002]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seminar, held in Bangkok on 22-24 November 2002, was a crucial early meeting for the representatives from Asian civil society organisations to share and shape their understanding and positions before taking part in global conversations during the following years. The meeting was organized by Bread for All (Switzerland), Communication Rights in the Information Society Campaign (Netherlands), Forum Asia (Thailand), and World Association for Christian Communication (United Kingdom), as a preparatory meeting for the Asia Pacific Regional Conference of WSIS, with 34 organisations from 16 Asian countries taking part. The Final Document produced at the end of this seminar was quite remarkable. It highlighted the simultaneity of Asia as one of the global centres of the information economy and the everyday reality of widespread poverty across Asian countries, and went on to state that the first principle for the emerging global information society should be that &amp;lsquo;[c]ommunication rights are fundamental to democracy and human development&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2002]&lt;/code&gt;. It proposed the following action items for efforts towards a global inclusive information society: 1) strengthen community, 2) ensure access, 3) enhance the creation of appropriate content, 4) invigorate global governance, 5) uphold human rights, 6) extend the public domain, 7) protect and promote cultural and linguistic diversity, and 8) ensure public investment in infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately after this conference, several Asian civil society organisations attended the Asian Civil Society Forum, organized as part of the Conference of Non-governmental Organizations in Consultative Relations with the United Nations (CONGO), held in Bangkok on 9-13 December 2002. Representatives of Dhaka Ahsania Mission (Bangladesh), OneWorld South Asia (India), GLOCOM (Japan), Foundation for Media Alternative (Philippines), Korean Progressive Network – JINBONET (South Korea), Friedrich Naumann Foundation (Singapore), International Federation of University Women (Switzerland), and Forum Asia (Regional) drafted a Joint Statement emphasising that a &amp;lsquo;broad-based participation of civil society, especially from those communities which are excluded, marginalized and severely deprived, is critical in defining and building such a [true communicative, just and peaceful] society [that is being envisaged through initiating the WSIS process.]&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[Aizu 2002]&lt;/code&gt;. In the very next month, the Asia Pacific Regional Conference was held in Tokyo, during 13-15 January 2003, &amp;lsquo;to develop a shared vision and common strategies for the “Information Society” &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003d]&lt;/code&gt;. The conference was attended by representatives from 47 national governments, 22 international organisations, 54 private sector agencies, and 116 civil society organisations across the Asia-Pacific region. The Tokyo Declaration, the final document prepared at the conclusion of the Conference, recognised that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[T]he Information Society must &amp;hellip; facilitate full utilization of information and communication technologies (ICT) at all levels in society and hence enable the sharing of social and economic benefits by all, by means of ubiquitous access to information networks, while preserving diversity and cultural heritage &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003d]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, it highlighted the following priority areas of action: 1) infrastructure development, 2) securing affordable, universal access to ICTs, 3) preserving linguistic and cultural diversity and promoting local content, 4) developing human resources, 5) establishing legal, regulatory and policy frameworks, 6) ensuring balance between intellectual property rights (IPR) and public interest, 7) ensuring the security of ICTs, and 8) fostering partnerships and mobilizing resources. It is not difficult to see how the focus of necessary actions shifted from an emphasis on concerns of community and human rights, need for investments and to bridge digital divides, and the idea of the Internet as a public commons, towards legal and policy mechanisms, multi-partner delivery of services, and intellectual property rights. Several civil society organisations felt sidelined in this conference and decided to issue a joint statement to ensure that their positions are effectively presented. The first two topics mentioned in this document were: 1) &amp;lsquo;[c]ommunication rights should be fully recognized as a fundamental and universal human right to be protected and promoted in the information society,&amp;rsquo; and 2) &amp;lsquo;[t]he participation of civil society in the information society at all levels should be ensured and sustained, from policy planning to implementation, monitoring, and evaluation&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[UNSAJ 2003]&lt;/code&gt;. The joint statement was endorsed by 30 civil society organisations: UDDIPAN (Bangladesh); COMFREL (Cambodia); ETDA (East Timor); The Hong Kong Council of Social Services (Hong Kong); Food India, IT for Change (India); Indonesian Infocom Society (Indonesia); Active Learning, CPSR, Forum for Citizens&amp;rsquo; Television and Media, JTEC, Kyoto Journal, Ritsumeikan University Media Literacy Project, UNSAJ (Japan); Computer Association Nepal, Rural Area Development Programme (Nepal); APC Women&amp;rsquo;s Networking Support Programme, Foundation for Media Alternatives, ISIS International (Philippines); Citizens&amp;rsquo; Action Network, Korean Progressive Network – Jinbonet, Labor News Production, ZAK (South Korea); e-Pacificka Consulting (Samoa); National University of Singapore (Singapore); Public Television Service, Taiwan Association for Human Rights (Taiwan); Asian-South Pacific Bureau for Adult Education, Forum Asia, and TVE Asia Pacific (Regional) &lt;code&gt;[UNSAJ 2003]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;participation-in-the-wsis-process:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Participation in the WSIS Process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first WSIS conference was held in Geneva on 10-12 December 2003. Through the processes of organizing this conference, and the second conference in Tunis in 2005, the United Nations operationalized a much-appreciated mandate for facilitating wider participation of non-governmental actors from the private sector, civil society, academia, and media, along with governmental organisations, in international policy-setting processes. At the first meeting of the WSIS Preparatory Committee (PrepCom-1) in Geneva, during 1-5 July 2002, civil society organisations argued that they should be allowed to co-shape the key subjects of discussion during the first conference (2003). There was already an Inter-Governmental Subcommittee on Contents and Themes, but no equivalent platform for the civil society organisations was available. With the approval of the Civil Society Plenary (CSP), the Civil Society Subcommittee on Content and Themes (WSIS-SCT) was instituted during PrepCom-1 &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003b]&lt;/code&gt;. At the second WSIS Preparatory Committee meeting (PrepCom-2), held in Geneva during 17-28 February 2003, the WSIS-SCT produced a summary of the views of its members titled &amp;lsquo;Vision and Principles of Information and Communication Societies,&amp;rsquo; as well as a one-page brief titled &amp;lsquo;Seven Musts: Priority Principles Proposed by Civil Society&amp;rsquo; to be used for lobbying purposes &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003b]&lt;/code&gt;. This brief mentioned seven key principles of Internet governance identified by the civil society organisations taking part in the WSIS process: (1) sustainable development, (2) democratic governance, (3) literacy, education, and research, (4) human rights, (5) global knowledge commons, (6) cultural and linguistic diversity, and (7) information security &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asian civil society organisations that took part in the PrepCom-2 meeting included United Nations Association of China (China); CASP - Centre for Adivasee Studies and Peace, C2N - Community Communications Network (India); ICSORC - Iranian Civil Society Organizations Resource Center (Iran); GAWF - General Arab Women Federation (Iraq); Daisy Consortium, GLOCOM - Center for Global Communications (Japan); Association for Progressive Communication, Global Knowledge Partnership (Malaysia); Pakistan Christian Peace Foundation (Pakistan); WFEO - World Federation of Engineering Organization (Palestine); Asian South Pacific Bureau of Adult Education, Foundation for Media Alternatives, ISIS International – Manila (Philippines); Korean Progressive Network - Jinbonet (South Korea); IIROSA - International Islamic Relief Organization (Saudi Arabia); and Taking IT Global (India, Indonesia, Malaysia, Philippines, and Turkey) &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these efforts led to the development of the Civil Society Declaration to the World Summit on the Information Society, which was prepared and published by the Civil Society Plenary at the Geneva conference, on 8 December 2003. The Declaration was titled &amp;lsquo;Shaping Information Societies for Human Needs&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003c]&lt;/code&gt;. The Asian civil society organization that took part in the Geneva conference were BFES - Bangladesh Friendship Education Society, Drik, ICTDPB - Information &amp;amp; Communication Technology Development Program, Proshika - A Center for Human Development (Bangladesh); China Society for Promotion of the Guangcai Programme, Chinese People&amp;rsquo;s Association for Friendship with Foreign Countries, United Nations Association of China (China); The Hong Kong Council of Social Service (Hong Kong); CASP - Centre for Adivasee Studies and Peace, Childline India Foundation / Child Helpline International, DAWN - Development Alternatives with Women for a New Era (India); Communication Network of Women&amp;rsquo;s NGOs in Iran, Green Front of Iran, ICTRC - Iranian Civil Society Organizations Training and Research Center, Islamic Women&amp;rsquo;s Institute of Iran, Institute for Women&amp;rsquo;s Studies and Research, Organization for Defending Victims of Violence (Iran); ILAM - Center for Arab Palestinians in Israel (Israel); Citizen Digital Solutions, Forum for Citizens&amp;rsquo; Television and Media, GLOCOM - Center for Global Communications, JCAFE - Japan Computer Access for Empowerment, Soka Gakkai International (Japan); LAD-Nepal - Literary Academy for Dalit of Nepal (Nepal); Asia-Pacific Broadcasting Union, Global Knowledge Partnership (Malaysia); PAK Educational Society / Pakistan Development Network, SMEDA - Small &amp;amp; Medium Enterprize Development Authority (Pakistan); Palestine IT Association of Companies (Palestine); Isis International – Manila, Ugnayan ng Kababaihan sa Pulitika / Philippine Women&amp;rsquo;s Network in Politics and Governance (Philippines); Citizen&amp;rsquo;s Alliance for Consumer Protection of Korea, Korean Civil Society Network for WSIS (South Korea); Youth Challenge (Singapore); Association for Progressive Communications (India and Philippines), CITYNET - Regional Network of Local Authorities for the Management of Human Settlements (India. Mongolia, and Philippines), Taking IT Global (India and Philippines) &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003b]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the preparatory meetings and consultations towards the second WSIS conference advanced during the next year, civil society organizations from Asia attempted to engage more directly with the global Internet governance processes on one hand, and the national Internet and ICT policy situations on the other. Writing about their encounters at and before the second Preparatory Committee meeting for the Tunis conference, held in Geneva during 17-25 February 2005, Anita Gurumurthy and Parminder Jeet Singh made several early observations that have continued to resonate with the experiences of Asian civil society organizations throughout the decade &lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2005]&lt;/code&gt;. First, they indicated that the government agencies present in the dialogs tend to take diverging positions in international events and domestic contexts. Second, there was a marked absence of formal and informal discussions between the governmental and the civil society representatives of the same country present at the meeting. The government agencies were clearly disinterested in involving civil society organizations in the process. Third, the civil society actors present at the meeting were mostly from the ICT for Development sector, while the organizations working in more &amp;lsquo;traditional&amp;rsquo; sectors – such as education, health, governance reform, etc. – remained absent from the conversations. This is especially problematic in the case of such developing countries where there does not exist strategic linkages between civil society organizations focusing on topics of technologized developmental interventions, and those involved in more &amp;lsquo;traditional&amp;rsquo; development practices. Rekha Jain, in a separate report on the Indian experience of participating in the WSIS process, reiterated some of these points &lt;code&gt;[Jain 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. She highlighted that &amp;lsquo;[w]hile the Secretary, [Department of Telecommunications, Government of India] was involved in (PrepCom-1) drafting the initial processes for involvement of NGOs, at the national level, this mechanism was not translated into a process for involving the civil society or media.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general lack of interest of national governments, especially in Asian countries, to engage with civil society organizations on matters of policies and projects in Internet governance and ICTs for development &lt;code&gt;[Souter 2007]&lt;/code&gt;, further encouraged these organization to utilize the global discussion space opened up by the WSIS process to drive the agendas of democratization of Internet governance processes, protection of human rights, and advancement of social justice. The second WSIS conference held in Tunis during 16-18 November 2005, however, did not end on a positive note for the civil society organizations as a whole. The sentiment is aptly captured in the title of the Civil Society Statement issued after the Tunis Conference: &amp;lsquo;Much more could have been achieved&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2005b]&lt;/code&gt;. Apart from producing this very important critical response to the WSIS process, within a month of its conclusion, civil society organizations played a key role in shaping one of the more longer-term impacts of the process – the establishment of the Internet Governance Forum (IGF). After the publication of the Report of the Working Group on Internet Governance &lt;code&gt;[Desai 2005]&lt;/code&gt; in June 2005, the Center for Global Communications (GLOCOM), Japan, acting on behalf of the Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus, came forward with public support for &amp;lsquo;the establishment of a new forum to address the broad agenda of Internet governance issues, provided it is truly global, inclusive, and multi-stakeholder in composition allowing all stakeholders from all sectors to participate as equal peers&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2005]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;asian-civil-society-organizations-at-the-igfs:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Asian Civil Society Organizations at the IGFs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, the WSIS Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus was reformed and established as a permanent &amp;lsquo;forum for discussion, advocacy, action, and for representation of civil society contributions in Internet governance processes&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[Civil 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. Representatives from Asian civil society organizations have consistently played critical roles in the functionings of this Caucus. Youn Jung Park of the Department of Technology and Society, SUNY Korea, co-founded and co-coordinated the original caucus in 2003. Adam Peake of the Center for Global Communications (GLOCOM), International University of Japan, was co-coordinator of the original caucus from 2003 to 2006. Parminder Jeet Sing of IT for Change, India, was elected as one of the co-coordinators of the newly reformed caucus in 2006, and held the position till 2008. Izumi Aizu of the Institute for HyperNetwork Society and the Institute for InfoSocinomics, Tama University, served as the co-coordinator of the caucus during 2010-2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first IGF, held in Athens during 30 October - 2 November 2006, saw participation from only a few Asian civil society organizations, mostly from Bangladesh and Japan &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. The second Internet Governance Forum in Rio de Janeiro, during 12-15 November 2007, had a larger representation from Asian civil society organizations: Bangladesh NGOs Network for Radio and Communication, BFES - Bangladesh Friendship Education Society, VOICE – Voices for Interactive Choice and Empowerment (Bangladesh); China Association for Science and Technology, Internet Society of China (China); University of Hong Kong (Hong Kong); Alternative Law Forum (via Association for Progressive Communications - Women&amp;rsquo;s Networking Support Programme), Indian Institute of Technology in Delhi, IT for Change (India); GLOCOM, Kumon Center, Tama University (Japan); Sustainable Development Networking Programme (Jordan); Kuwait Information Technology Society (Kuwait); Association of Computer Engineers – Nepal, Rural Area Development Programme, Nepal Rural Information Technology Development Society (Nepal); Bytesforall – APC / Pakistan, Pakistan Christian Peace Foundation (Pakistan); Foundation for Media Alternatives, Philippine Resources for Sustainable Development Inc. (Philippines); and LIRNEasia (Sri Lanka). At the Open IGF Consultations in Geneva, on 26 February 2008, the Internet Governance Caucus made two significant submissions: 1) that, although structuring the IGF sessions in Athens and Rio de Janeiro around the large themes of access, openness, diversity, and security have been useful to open up the multi-stakeholder dialogues, it is necessary to begin focused discussions of specific public policy issues to take the IGF process forward &lt;code&gt;[Civil 2008]&lt;/code&gt;, and 2) that the Multi-Stakeholder Advisory Group (MAG), which drives the IGF process and events, should be made more proactive and transparent, and expanded in size so as to better include the different stakeholder groups who may self-identify their representatives for the MAG &lt;code&gt;[Civil 2008b]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one hand, the IGF Hyderabad, held during 3-6 December 2008, experienced a decline in the percentage of participants from civil society organizations and a rather modest increase in the percentage of participants from Asian countries, especially since this was the first major international Internet governance summit held in an Asian country. See Table 6-2 for further information. On the other hand, the Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus succeeded to bring forth the term &amp;lsquo;enhanced cooperation,&amp;rsquo; as mentioned in the Tunis Agenda, to be addressed and discussed in one of the main sessions of the Forum &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2008]&lt;/code&gt;. The next IGF held in Sharm El Sheikh, during 15-18 November 2009, saw a further decline of participation from both the representatives of civil society organizations and attendees from Asian countries. See Table 6-2 for further information. The fall in participation reflects a feeling among civil society organizations that the IGF process is not allowing specific and effective dialogues about critical policy and governance concerns around Internet and digital media. In this context, Youn Jung Park made the following statement in the Stock Taking session of the summit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a co-founder of WSIS Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus in 2003, I would like to remind you &amp;hellip; [that] Internet Governance Forum was created as a compromise between those who supported the status quo Internet governance institution under one nation&amp;rsquo;s status provision, and those who requested for more balanced roles for governments under international supervision of the Internet. While IGF has achieved a great success of diluting of such political tension between those who have different views of how to institutionalize Internet governance, ironically Internet governance forum became a forum without governance&amp;hellip; [We] have to admit [that] IGF failed to deliver another mandate of the U.N. WSIS: Continuing discussion of how to design Internet governance institutions&amp;hellip; The current IGF continues to function as knowledge transfer of ICANN&amp;rsquo;s values to other stakeholders, while those who want to discuss and negotiate on how to design Internet governance institutions should have another platform for that specific U.N. WSIS mandate &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2009]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Asia Pacific regional Internet Governance Forum (APrIGF) was held in Hong Kong on 14-16 June 2010. The organising committee included three civil society / academic organizations – Center for Global Communications (GLOCOM), Internet Society Hong Kong, and National University of Singapore – and three independent experts – Kuo-Wei Wu (Taiwan), Norbert Klein (Cambodia), and Zahid Jamil (Pakistan). Though the forum was largely attended by governmental and private sector participants, several representatives from Asian civil societies and academic organizations spoke at the main sessions: Ang Peng Hwa (Singapore Internet Research Centre, Nanyang Technological University), Charles Mok (Internet Society Hong Kong), Christine Loh (Civic Exchange), Chong Chan Yau (Hong Kong Blind Union), Clarence Tsang (Christian Action), Ilya Eric Lee (Taiwan E-Learning and Digital Archives Program, and Research Center for Information Technology Innovation), Izumi Aizu (Institute for HyperNetwork Society, and Institute for InfoSocinomics, Kumon Center, Tama University), Oliver &amp;lsquo;Blogie&amp;rsquo; Robillo (Mindanao Bloggers Community), Parminder Jeet Singh (IT for Change), Priscilla Lui (Against Child Abuse in Hong Kong), Tan Tin Wee (Centre for Internet Research, National University of Singapore), and Yap Swee Seng (Asian Forum for Human Rights and Development). As Ang Peng Hwa noted at the beginning of the summit, its key objective was to provide a formal space for various stakeholders from the Asia-Pacific region to discuss and provide inputs to the IGF process &lt;code&gt;[APrIGF 2010]&lt;/code&gt;. The regional forum was successful in enabling newer civil society entrants from the Asia-Pacific region to familiarize themselves with the IGF process, and to contribute to it. For example, IGF Vilnius, held during 14-17 September 2010, was the first IGF summit attended by Oliver &amp;lsquo;Blogie&amp;rsquo; Robillo, where he presented the recommendations from Southeast Asian civil society organizations. In his speech, he emphasized the following topics: 1) openness and freedom of expression are the basis of democracy, and state-driven censorship of the Internet in the region is an immediate threat to such global rights; 2) coordinated international efforts need to address and resolve not only global digital divides, but also the divides at regional, national, and sub-nationals scales; 3) the right to privacy is an integral part of cybersecurity, as well as a necessary condition for exercising human rights; 4) global Internet governance efforts must ensure that national governments do not control or restrict abilities of citizens to express through digital means, and this should be aligned with the universal human rights agenda, and 5) even after 5 years of the IGF process, a wider participation of civil society organizations, especially from the Asia-Pacific regions, remains an unachieved goal, which can only be achieved if specific resources are allocated and processes are implemented &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2010]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;internet-censorship-and-civil-society-responses:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Internet Censorship and Civil Society Responses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the decade of 2001-2010, censorship of the Internet and restriction of digital expression remained crucial Internet rights concerns across the world and especially in Asian countries. One of the earliest global reports on the topic was brought out by Reporters without Borders. In 2006, they published a list of sixteen countries marked as &amp;lsquo;Internet Enemies,&amp;rsquo; out of which eleven were from Asia: China, Iran, Maldives, Myanmar, Nepal, North Korea, Saudi Arabia, Syria, Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan, and Vietnam &lt;code&gt;[Reporters 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. The list was updated in 2007, and three of these countries – Libya, Maldives, and Nepal – were removed. The unique contradictions of the Internet and ICTs landscape of the Asian region were insightfully highlighted in the 2006-07 report on Internet censorship by OpenNet Initiative:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the most and least connected countries in the world are located in Asia: Japan, South Korea, and Singapore all have Internet penetration rates of over 65 percent, while Afghanistan, Myanmar, and Nepal remain three of thirty countries with less than 1 percent of its citizens online. Among the countries in the world with the most restricted access, North Korea allows only a small community of elites and foreigners online. Most users must rely on Chinese service providers for connectivity while the limited number North Korean–sponsored Web sites are hosted abroad&amp;hellip; [T]hough India’s Internet community is the fifth largest in the world, users amounted to only about 4 percent of the country’s population in 2005. Afghanistan, Myanmar, and Nepal are among the world’s least-developed countries. Despite the constraints on resources and serious developmental and political challenges, however, citizens are showing steadily increasing demand for Internet services such as Voice over Internet Protocol (VoIP), blogging, and chat &lt;code&gt;[Wang 2007]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report further described the strategy used by various Asian governments of &amp;lsquo;delegation of policing and monitoring responsibilities to ISPs, content providers, private corporations, and users themselves&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[Wang 2007]&lt;/code&gt;. This is an effective method of enforcing self-surveillance and self-censorship under the threats of loss of commercial license, denial of services, and even criminal liability. Defamation suits and related civil and criminal liability have also been used by several Asian governments to silence influential critics and protesters. Direct technical filtering of Internet traffic (especially incoming traffic) and blocking of URLS via government directives sent to Internet Service Providers (ISPs) have been common practices in several Asian countries &lt;code&gt;[Wang 2007]&lt;/code&gt;. Expectedly, such experiences of oppression led to widespread campaigns by the Asian civil society organizations, as can be surmised from the submission mentioned above by Oliver &amp;lsquo;Blogie&amp;rsquo; Robillo at IGF Vilnius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among Asian countries, the comprehensive technologies of censorship developed and deployed by China have been studied extensively. The Golden Shield Project was initiated by the Ministry of Public Security of China in 1998 to undertake blanket blocking of incoming Internet traffic based on specific URLs and terms. Evidence of the project being operationalised became available in 2003 &lt;code&gt;[Garden 2004]&lt;/code&gt;. Censorship of Internet in China, however, has not only been implemented using such macro-scale technological systems, non-automated mechanisms have also been used at the ground level. In 2003, it was made mandatory for all residents of Lhasa, Tibet, to use a specific combination of user name and password, which was directly linked to their names and address, to access the Internet. An Internet ID card was issued by the government to implement this &lt;code&gt;[International 2004]&lt;/code&gt;. Tibet Action Institute has been a key civil society organization at the forefront of the cyber offense of the Chinese government. A recent documentary by the institute, titled &amp;lsquo;Tibet: Frontline of the New Cyberwar,&amp;rsquo; narrates how it has worked closely with Citizen Lab, Munk School of Global Affairs, University of Toronto, to identify, trace, and resist malware and other cyber-attacks experienced by the civil society actors and websites in favor of independence of Tibet &lt;code&gt;[Tibet 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. The Tibetan case is not an exceptional one. Digital security training has emerged as an important aspect of the life of civil society organizations during the decade. Asian organizations such as Bytes for All (Pakistan) and Myanmar ICT for Development Organization (Myanmar), as well as international organizations including Front Line Defenders and Citizen Lab have educated and supported civil society activities much beyond the Internet governance sphere with tools and techniques for effectively using digital channels of communications, and defending themselves against cyber-threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combination of traditional forms of civil society mobilizations and digital techniques has often been used to resist attempts by Asian governments to control the online communication space. In Pakistan, as the government took harsh steps towards control of both traditional and online media in 2007-2008, Huma Yusuf extensively studied the emergence of hybrid media strategies among citizen journaalists and civil society activits, using both old media channels such as newspapers and new media channels like blogs and video sharing platforms &lt;code&gt;[Yusuf 2009]&lt;/code&gt;. She has carefully traced how possibilities of new forms of information and media sharing enabled by the Internet were initially identified and implemented by citizen journalists and student activists, which was quickly learned and re-deployed by more formal organisations, such as print and electronic news companies, and civil society organizations like those involved in election monitoring. Malaysia also experienced fast-accelerating conflict between the government and a civil society during 2007-2010, as the former started intervening directly into censoring blogs and newspaper websites. On one hand, the government took legal actions against critical bloggers, either directly or indirectly, and on the other it instructed ISPs to block &amp;lsquo;offensive content.&amp;rsquo; It also borrowed the &amp;lsquo;Singapore-model&amp;rsquo; to mandate registration of bloggers with government authorities, if they are identified as writing on socio-political topics. Civil society actors responded to these oppressive steps by setting up a new blog dedicated to coverage of the defamation cases (filed against prominent bloggers), and publicly sharing instructions for circumvention of the blocks imposed by ISPs. The National Alliance of Bloggers was soon formed, which organized the Blogs and Digital Democracy Forum on 3 October 2007 [Thien 2011]. Similarly, the Bloggers Against Censorship campaign took shape in India in 2006 as the government first directed ISPs to block specific blogs hosted on Blogspot, TypePad, and Yahoo! Geocities, and then sought complete blocking of Yahoo! Geocities as the ISPs failed to block specific sub-domains of the platform &lt;code&gt;[Bloggers 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. Learning from this experience, the following year the Indian government decided to work directly with Orkut to take down &amp;lsquo;defamatory content&amp;rsquo; about a politician &lt;code&gt;[Economic 2007]&lt;/code&gt;. This is common for other Asian governments too, as they have continued to develop more legally binding and technically sophisticated measures to monitor and control online expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &amp;lsquo;Internet Enemies Report 2012,&amp;rsquo; Reporters without Borders listed 12 countries as &amp;lsquo;enemies of the Internet,&amp;rsquo; out of which 10 were from Asia – Bahrain, China, Iran, Myanmar, North Korea, Saudi Arabia, Syria, Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan, and Vietnam – and it named 14 countries that were conducting surveillance on its citizens, out of which 7 were from Asia – India, Kazakhstan, Malaysia, South Korea, Sri Lanka, Thailand, and United Arab Emirates &lt;code&gt;[Reporters 2012]&lt;/code&gt;. At the APrIGF held in Tokyo during 18-20 July 2012, a group of delegates from civil society organizations working in the South-East Asian region issued a joint statement with a clear call for global action on the shrinking space for freedom of (digital) expression in the region &lt;code&gt;[Thai 2012]&lt;/code&gt;. They specifically noted the following national acts as examples of the legislative mechanisms being used by different Asian governments to criminalize online speech and/or to harass public dissenters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burma – The 2004 Electronic Transactions Act&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cambodia – The 2012 Draft Cyber-Law, the 1995 Press Law, and the 2010 Penal Code&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malaysia – The 2012 Amendment to the Evidence Act and the 2011 Computing Professionals Bill&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indonesia – The 2008 Law on Information and Electronic Transaction and the 2008 Law on Pornography&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Philippines – The 2012 Data Privacy Act&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thailand – The 2007 Computer Crimes Act, the Article 112 of the Penal Code, and the 2004 Special Case Investigation Act&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vietnam – The 1999 Penal Code, the 2004 Publishing Law, the 2000 State Secrets Protection Ordinance, and the 2012 Draft Decree on Internet Management. (Ibid.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statement was co-signed by Thai Netizen Network, Thai Media Policy Centre, The Institute for Policy Research and Advocacy (ELSAM), Southeast Asian Press Alliance (SEAPA), Southeast Asian Centre for e-Media (SEACeM), Victorius (Ndaru) Eps, Community Legal Education Center (CLEC), Sovathana (Nana) Neang, and Asian Forum for Human Rights and Development (Forum Asia), and was endorsed by ICT Watch (Indonesian ICT Partnership Association).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;annexe-tables:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Annexe – Tables&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;table-1-participation-from-asian-countries-and-of-representatives-from-asian-civil-society-organisations-in-igfs-2006-2010:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Table 1: Participation from Asian Countries and of representatives from Asian civil society organisations in IGFs, 2006-2010&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Event&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Participants from Asian Countries&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Participants from Civil Society Organizations&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IGF Athens 2006&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;29%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IGF Rio de Janeiro 2007&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;32%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IGF Hyderabad 2008&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;56% from India, and 15% from other Asian countries&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;25%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IGF Sharm El Sheikh 2009&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IGF Vilnius 2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not Available&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not Available&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: Reports available on &lt;a href=&#34;http://igf.wgig.org/cms&#34;&gt;Internet Governance Forum website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;table-2-internet-society-chapters-in-asia:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Table 2: Internet Society Chapters in Asia&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Chapter&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year of Establishment&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;URL&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Afghanistan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;In formation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not available&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bahrain&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bis.org.bh/&#34;&gt;http://www.bis.org.bh/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bangladesh&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.org.bd/dhaka/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.org.bd/dhaka/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hong Kong&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2005&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.hk/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.hk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;India (Bangalore)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocbangalore.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocbangalore.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;India (Chennai)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocindiachennai.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocindiachennai.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;India (Delhi)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2002. Rejuvenated in 2008.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocdelhi.in/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocdelhi.in/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;India (Kolkata)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://isockolkata.in/&#34;&gt;http://isockolkata.in/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;India (Trivandrum)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not available&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Indonesia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.or.id/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.or.id/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Israel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1995&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.org.il/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.org.il/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Japan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1994&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.jp/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.jp/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lebanon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.org.lb/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.org.lb/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Malaysia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.my/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.my/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nepal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.internetsociety.org.np/&#34;&gt;http://www.internetsociety.org.np/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pakistan (Islamabad)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocibd.org.pk/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocibd.org.pk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Palestine&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2002&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.ps/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.ps/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philippines&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1999. Rejuvenated in 2009.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/isoc.ph/&#34;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/isoc.ph/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Qatar&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.qa/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.qa/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Republic of Korea&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not available&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Singapore&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://isoc.sg/&#34;&gt;http://isoc.sg/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sri Lanka&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.lk/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.lk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Taipei&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1996&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.org.tw/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.org.tw/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thailand&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1996&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc-th.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc-th.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;United Arab Emirates&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocuae.com/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocuae.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yemen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://isoc.ye/&#34;&gt;http://isoc.ye/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: Details of chapters available on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.internetsociety.org/&#34;&gt;Internet Society website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgment:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to Anita Gurumurthy and Parminder Jeet Singh for their generous sharing of information and insights. Raman Jit Singh Cheema, Pranesh Prakash, and Sunil Abraham have also provided crucial suggestions. Extensive background research by P.P. Sneha has significantly enriched my efforts. The Wayback Machine of the Internet Archive deserves a very special thanks. Last but not the least, I am thankful to Kilnam Chon for this wonderful opportunity and his patient support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reference:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Aizu 2002]&lt;/code&gt; Aizu, Izumi et al. 2002. Joint Statement from Asia Civil Society Forum Participants on World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS). December 13. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsisasia.org/wsis-acsf2002/wsis-acsfdec13f.doc&#34;&gt;http://www.wsisasia.org/wsis-acsf2002/wsis-acsfdec13f.doc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[APrIGF 2010]&lt;/code&gt; Asia Pacific Regional Internet Governance Forum (APrIGF). 2010. APrIGF Roundtable – June 15th, 2010: Session 1 – Welcome Remarks and Introduction – Real Time Transcript. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://2010.rigf.asia/aprigf-roundtable-june-15th-2010-session-1/&#34;&gt;http://2010.rigf.asia/aprigf-roundtable-june-15th-2010-session-1/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Bloggers 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Bloggers Collective Group. 2006. Bloggers Against Censorship. Last updated on April 30, 2009‎. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://censorship.wikia.com/wiki/Bloggers_Against_Censorship&#34;&gt;http://censorship.wikia.com/wiki/Bloggers_Against_Censorship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Civil 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus. 2006. Internet Governance Caucus Charter. October 14. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC-charter_final-061014.html&#34;&gt;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC-charter_final-061014.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Civil 2008]&lt;/code&gt; Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus. 2008. Inputs for the Open IGF Consultation, Geneva, 26th February, 2008 – Statement II: Main Session Themes for IGF, Hyderabad. February 26. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC%20-%20Main%20themes%20for%20IGF%20Hyd.pdf&#34;&gt;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC%20-%20Main%20themes%20for%20IGF%20Hyd.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Civil 2008b]&lt;/code&gt; Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus. 2008. Inputs for the Open IGF Consultation, Geneva, 26th February, 2008 – Statement III: Renewal / Restructuring of Multi-stakeholder Advisory Group. February 26. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC%20-%20MAG%20Rotation.pdf&#34;&gt;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC%20-%20MAG%20Rotation.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Desai 2005]&lt;/code&gt; Desai, Nitin, et al. 2005. Report of the Working Group on Internet Governance. United June. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wgig.org/docs/WGIGREPORT.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.wgig.org/docs/WGIGREPORT.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Economic 2007]&lt;/code&gt; The Economic Times. 2007. Orkut&amp;rsquo;s Tell-All Pact with Cops. May 01. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2007-05-01/news/28459689_1_orkut-ip-addresses-google-spokesperson&#34;&gt;http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2007-05-01/news/28459689_1_orkut-ip-addresses-google-spokesperson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Garden 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Garden Networks for Freedom of Information. 2004. Breaking through the “Golden Shield.” Open Society Institute. November 01. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.opensocietyfoundations.org/sites/default/files/china-internet-censorship-20041101.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.opensocietyfoundations.org/sites/default/files/china-internet-censorship-20041101.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[George 2002]&lt;/code&gt; George, Susanna. 2002. Women and New Information and Communications Technologies: The Promise of Empowerment. Presented at The World Summit on the Information Society: An Asian Response Meeting, November 22-24. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsisasia.org/materials/susanna.doc/&#34;&gt;http://www.wsisasia.org/materials/susanna.doc/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2005]&lt;/code&gt; Gurumurthy, Anita, &amp;amp; Parminder Jeet Singh. 2005. WSIS PrepCom 2: A South Asian Perspective. Association for Progressive Communications. April 01. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apc.org/en/news/hr/world/wsis-prepcom-2-south-asian-perspective&#34;&gt;https://www.apc.org/en/news/hr/world/wsis-prepcom-2-south-asian-perspective&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum (IGF). 2006. Athens 2006 – List of Participants. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intgovforum.org/PLP.html&#34;&gt;http://www.intgovforum.org/PLP.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2008]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum (IGF). 2008. Arrangements for Internet Governance, Global and National/Regional. IGF Hyderabad, India. December 5. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20130621205004/http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/hyderabad_prog/AfIGGN.html&#34;&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20130621205004/http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/hyderabad_prog/AfIGGN.html&lt;/a&gt; [Original URL: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/hyderabad_prog/AfIGGN.html&#34;&gt;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/hyderabad_prog/AfIGGN.html&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum (IGF). 2009. Taking Stock and Looking Forward – On the Desirability of the Continuation of the Forum, Part II. IGF Sharm El Sheikh, Egypt. November 18. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/2009/sharm_el_Sheikh/Transcripts/Sharm%20El%20Sheikh%2018%20November%202009%20Stock%20Taking%20II.txt&#34;&gt;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/2009/sharm_el_Sheikh/Transcripts/Sharm%20El%20Sheikh%2018%20November%202009%20Stock%20Taking%20II.txt&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2010]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum (IGF). 2010. Taking Stock of Internet Governance and the Way Forward. IGF Vilnius, Lithuania. September 17. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://igf.wgig.org/cms/component/content/article/102-transcripts2010/687-taking-stock&#34;&gt;http://igf.wgig.org/cms/component/content/article/102-transcripts2010/687-taking-stock&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[International 2004]&lt;/code&gt; International Campaign for Tibet. 2004. Chinese Authorities Institute Internet ID Card System in Tibet for Online Surveillance. April 30. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.savetibet.org/chinese-authorities-institute-internet-id-card-system-in-tibet-for-online-surveillance/&#34;&gt;http://www.savetibet.org/chinese-authorities-institute-internet-id-card-system-in-tibet-for-online-surveillance/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003]&lt;/code&gt; International Telecommunication Union (ITU). 2003. PrepCom-2 / 17-28 February 2003 – Final List of Participants. February 28. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/participation/prepcom2/prepcom2-cl.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/participation/prepcom2/prepcom2-cl.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003b]&lt;/code&gt; International Telecommunication Union (ITU). 2003. Geneva Phase of the WSIS: List of Participants. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/summit_participants.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/summit_participants.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Jain 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Jain, Rekha. 2006. Participation of Developing Countries in the World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) Process: India Case Study. Association for Progressive Communications. March. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://rights.apc.org/documents/wsis_india.pdf&#34;&gt;http://rights.apc.org/documents/wsis_india.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Reporters 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Reporters without Borders. 2006. List of the 13 Internet Enemies. Last updated on August 28, 2007. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.rsf.org/list-of-the-13-internet-enemies-07-11-2006,19603&#34;&gt;http://en.rsf.org/list-of-the-13-internet-enemies-07-11-2006,19603&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Reporters 2012]&lt;/code&gt; Reporters without Borders. 2012. Internet Enemies Report 2012. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.rsf.org/IMG/pdf/rapport-internet2012_ang.pdf&#34;&gt;http://en.rsf.org/IMG/pdf/rapport-internet2012_ang.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Souter 2007]&lt;/code&gt; Souter, David. 2007. WSIS and Civil Society. In: Whose Summit? Whose Information Society? Developing Countries and Civil Society at the World Summit on the Information Society. With additional research by Abiodun Jagun. Association for Progressive Communications. Pp. 72-89. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://rights.apc.org/documents/whose_summit_EN.pdf&#34;&gt;http://rights.apc.org/documents/whose_summit_EN.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Thai 2012]&lt;/code&gt; Thai Netizen Network et al. 2012. Southeast Asian Civil Society Groups Highlight Increasing Rights Violations Online, Call for Improvements to Internet Governance Processes in the Region. Statement of Civil Society Delegates from Southeast Asia to 2012 Asia-Pacific Regional Internet Governance Forum (APrIGF). July 31. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;https://freedomhouse.org/sites/default/files/AprIGF-Joint%20Statement-FINAL.pdf&#34;&gt;https://freedomhouse.org/sites/default/files/AprIGF-Joint%20Statement-FINAL.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Thien 2011]&lt;/code&gt; Thien, Vee Vian. 2011. The Struggle for Digital Freedom of Speech: The Malaysian Sociopolitical Blogosphere’s Experience. In: Ronald Deibert et al. (eds.) Access Contested. OpenNet Initiative. Pp. 43-63. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://access.opennet.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/accesscontested-chapter-03.pdf&#34;&gt;http://access.opennet.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/accesscontested-chapter-03.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Tibet 2015]&lt;/code&gt; Tibet Action Institute. 2015. Tibet: Frontline of the New Cyberwar. YouTube. January 27. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yE3AQqbGVkk&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yE3AQqbGVkk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[UNSAJ 2003]&lt;/code&gt; UNSAJ et al. 2003. Civil Society Observations and Response to the Tokyo Declaration. Asia-Pacific Regional Conference on the World Summit on the Information Society. January 15. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsisasia.org/wsis-tokyo/tokyo-statement.html&#34;&gt;http://www.wsisasia.org/wsis-tokyo/tokyo-statement.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Wang 2007]&lt;/code&gt; Wang, Stephanie. 2007. Internet Filtering in Asia in 2006-2007. OpenNet Initiative. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://opennet.net/studies/asia2007&#34;&gt;https://opennet.net/studies/asia2007&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2002]&lt;/code&gt; The World Summit on the Information Society: An Asian Response. 2002. Final Document. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsisasia.org/materials/finalversion.doc&#34;&gt;http://www.wsisasia.org/materials/finalversion.doc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Civil Society Subcommittee on Content and Themes. 2003. “Seven Musts”: Priority Principles Proposed by Civil Society. February 25. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.movimientos.org/es/foro_comunicacion/show_text.php3%3Fkey%3D1484&#34;&gt;http://www.movimientos.org/es/foro_comunicacion/show_text.php3%3Fkey%3D1484&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003b]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Civil Society Subcommittee on Content and Themes. 2003. Final Report on Prepcom-2 Activities of the Civil Society on Content and Themes. March 27. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/pcip/misc/cs_sct.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/pcip/misc/cs_sct.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003c]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Civil Society Plenary. 2003. “Shaping Information Societies for Human Needs” – Civil Society Declaration to the World Summit on the Information Society. December 8. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/civil-society-declaration.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/civil-society-declaration.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003d]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Executive Secretariat. 2003. Report of the Asia-Pacific Regional Conference for WSIS (Tokyo, 13-15 January 2003). WSIS. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/dms_pub/itu-s/md/03/wsispc2/doc/S03-WSISPC2-DOC-0006!!PDF-E.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/dms_pub/itu-s/md/03/wsispc2/doc/S03-WSISPC2-DOC-0006!!PDF-E.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2005]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus. 2005. Initial Reactions to the WGIG Report. Contribution from GLOCOM on behalf of the WSIS Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus. July 19. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from www.itu.int/wsis/%20docs2/pc3/contributions/co23.doc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2005b]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Civil Society Plenary. 2005. “Much more could have been achieved” – Civil Society Statement on the World Summit on the Information Society. December 18. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/contributions/co13.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/contributions/co13.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Yusuf 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Yusuf, Huma. 2009. Old and New Media: Converging during the Pakistan Emergency (March 2007 - February 2008). MIT Centre for Civic Media. January 12. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://civic.mit.edu/blog/humayusuf/old-and-new-media-converging-during-the-pakistan-emergency-march-2007-february-2008&#34;&gt;https://civic.mit.edu/blog/humayusuf/old-and-new-media-converging-during-the-pakistan-emergency-march-2007-february-2008&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Civil Society Organisations and Internet Governance in India, 2000-2010</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/civil-society-organisations-and-internet-governance-in-india-2000-2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/civil-society-organisations-and-internet-governance-in-india-2000-2010/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;this-is-a-book-section-written-for-the-asia-internet-history-third-decade-2001-2010-volume-edited-by-prof-kilnam-chon-the-book-was-published-both-in-print-and-as-an-online-open-access-version-in-december-2015-read-the-book-online-here-https-sites-google-com-site-internethistoryasia-book3-https-sites-google-com-site-internethistoryasia-book3:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;This is a book section written for the &lt;em&gt;Asia Internet History - Third Decade (2001~2010)&lt;/em&gt; volume edited by Prof. Kilnam Chon. The book was published, both in print and as an online open access version, in December 2015. Read the book online here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/internethistoryasia/book3&#34;&gt;https://sites.google.com/site/internethistoryasia/book3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#early-days:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Early Days&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#key-organizations:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Key Organizations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#global-and-national-events:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Global and National Events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#internet-policies-and-censorship:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Internet Policies and Censorship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#acknowledgment:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#reference:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Reference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;early-days:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Early Days&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overarching context of development interventions and rights-based approaches has shaped the space of civil society organizations working on the topics of information and communication technologies (ICTs) and Internet governance in India. Early members of this space came from diverse backgrounds. Satish Babu was working with the South Indian Federation of Fishermen Societies (SIFFS) in the mid-1990s, when he set up a public mailing list called &amp;lsquo;FishNet,&amp;rsquo; connected to the Internet via the IndiaLink email network, (then) run by India Social Institute to inter-connect development practitioners in India. He went on to become the President of Computer Society of India during 2012-2013; he also co-founded the Society for Promotion of Alternative Computing and Employment (SPACE) in 2003, where he served as the Executive Secretary during 2003-2010 &lt;code&gt;[Wikipedia 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. Anita Gurumurthy, Executive Director of IT for Change and one of the key actors from Indian civil society organizations that took part in the World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) process, had previously worked extensively on topics related to public health and women&amp;rsquo;s rights &lt;code&gt;[ITfC 2015b]&lt;/code&gt;, which deeply shaped the perspectives she and IT for Change have brought into the Internet governance sphere, globally as well as nationally &lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2001]&lt;/code&gt;. Arun Mehta initiated a mailing list titled &amp;lsquo;India-GII&amp;rsquo; in 2002 to discuss &amp;lsquo;India&amp;rsquo;s bumpy progress on the global infohighway&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[India-GII 2005]&lt;/code&gt;. This list played a critical role in curating an early community of non-governmental actors interested in the topics of telecommunication policy, spectrum licensing, Internet governance, and consumer and communication rights. As Frederick Noronha documented, the mailing list culture grew slowly in India during the late 1990s and early 2000s. However, they had a great impact on organizing early online communities, sometimes grouped around a topical focus, sometimes functioning as a bridge among family members living abroad, and sometimes curating place-specific groups &lt;code&gt;[Noronha 2002]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inaugural conference of the Free Software Foundation of India (FSFI) in Thiruvananthapuram, on 20 July 2001, galvanized the Free/Libre and Open Source Software (FLOSS) community in India. The conference was titled &amp;lsquo;Freedom First,&amp;rsquo; and Richard Stallman was invited as the chief guest. It was a vital gathering of actors from civil society organizations, software businesses, academia, and media, as well as the Secretary of the Department of Information Technology, Government of Kerala (the state where the conference was held). The conference laid the basis for sustained collaborations between the free software community, civil society organizations, emerging software firms in the state, and the Government of Kerala for the years to come. Two early initiatives that brought together free software developers and state government agencies were the Kerala Transportation Project and the IT@School project, which not only were awarded to firms promoting use of FLOSS in electronic governance projects, but also facilitated a wider public dialogue regarding the need to think critically about the making of an information society in India &lt;code&gt;[Kumar 2007]&lt;/code&gt;. The inter-connected communities and overlapping practices of the FLOSS groups, civil society organizations involved in ICT for Development initiatives, telecommunication policy analysts and advocates, and legal-administrative concerns regarding life in the information society – from digital security and privacy, to freedom of online expressions, to transparency in electronic governance infrastructures – have, hence, continued to shape the sub-spherer of civil society organizations in India that are discussing, responding to, and contributing to policies and practices around the Internet governance in India and elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-organizations:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Key Organizations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IT for Change was established in 2000, in Bengaluru, as a non-governmental organization that &amp;lsquo;works for the innovative and effective use of information and communication technologies (ICTs) to promote socio-economic change in the global south, from an equity, social justice and gender equality point of view&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[ITfC 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. It has since made important contributions in the field of ICTs for Development, especially in integrating earlier communication rights practices organized around old media forms with newer possibilities of production and distribution of electronic content using digital media and the Internet &lt;code&gt;[ITfC 2015e]&lt;/code&gt;, and in the field of the Internet governance, especially through their participation in the WSIS and Internet Governance Forum (IGF) processes and by co-shaping the Internet governance discourse in and from the global south &lt;code&gt;[ITfC 2015d]&lt;/code&gt;. It has also done significant works in the area of women&amp;rsquo;s rights in the information society, and has been a core partner in a multi-country feminist action research project on using digital media to enhance the citizenship rights and experiences of marginalized women in India, Brazil, and South Africa &lt;code&gt;[ITfC 2015c]&lt;/code&gt;. IT for Change co-led the formation of Just Net Coalition in February 2014 &lt;code&gt;[JNC 2015]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF) was founded by Osama Manzar in New Delhi in 2002, with a &amp;lsquo;deep understanding that marginalized communities living in socio-economic backwardness and information poverty can be empowered to improve their lives almost on their own, simply by providing them access to information and knowledge using digital tools&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[DEF 2015c]&lt;/code&gt;. DEF has contributed to setting up Community Information Resource Centres from 19 states and 53 districts in India, with computers, printers, scanners, and Internet connectivity &lt;code&gt;[DEF 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. DEF organizes one of the biggest competitions in Asia to identify, foreground and honor significant contributions in the area of ICT for Development &lt;code&gt;[DEF 2015d]&lt;/code&gt;. This annual competition series, titled the &amp;lsquo;Manthan Award&amp;rsquo; (&amp;lsquo;manthan&amp;rsquo; means &amp;lsquo;churning&amp;rsquo; in Sanskrit), started in 2004. It has allowed DEF to create a detailed database of ICT for Development activities and actors in the South Asia and Asia Pacific region. Since 2011, DEF has been working with Association for Progressive Communications on a project titled &amp;lsquo;Internet Rights&amp;rsquo; to move forward the agenda of &amp;lsquo;Internet access for all&amp;rsquo; in India &lt;code&gt;[DEF 2015b]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Society for Knowledge Commons was formed in New Delhi 2007 by &amp;lsquo;scientists, technologists, researchers, and activists to leverage the tremendous potential of the “collaborative innovation” model for knowledge generation that has lead to the growth of the Free and Open Source Software community (FOSS) around the world&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[SKC 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. It has championed integration of FOSS into public sector operations in India – from electronic governance systems to the use of software in educational institutes – and has continuously intervened in Internet governance issues from the perspective of the critical importance of shared knowledge properties and practices for a more democratic information society. It is a part of the Free Software Movement of India &lt;code&gt;[FSMI 2015]&lt;/code&gt;, an alliance of Indian organizations involved in advocating awareness and usage of FOSS, as well as a founding member of the Just Net Coalition &lt;code&gt;[JNC 2015]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre for Internet and Society (CIS) was established in Bengaluru in 2008 with a research and advocacy focus on topics of accessibility of digital content for differently-abled persons, FOSS and policies on intellectual property rights, open knowledge and Indic language Wikipedia projects, digital security and privacy, freedom of expression and Internet governance, and socio-cultural and historical studies of Internet in India &lt;code&gt;[CIS 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. In one of the key early projects, CIS contributed to the creation of web accessibility policy for government websites in India, which was being drafted by the Department of Information Technology, Government of India &lt;code&gt;[CIS 2008]&lt;/code&gt;. In the following years it took part in Internet Governance Forum summits; submitted responses and suggestions to various policies being introduced by the government, especially the Information Technology (Amendment) Act, 2008, National Identification Authority of India (NIA) Bill, 2010, and the Approach Paper for Legislation on Privacy, 2010; produced a report on the state of open government data in India &lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2011b]&lt;/code&gt;; and undertook an extensive study on the experiences of young people in Asia with Internet, digital media, and social change &lt;code&gt;[Shah 2011]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Software Freedom Law Centre has undertaken research and advocacy interventions, since 2011, on the topics of digital privacy, software patents, and cyber-surveillance &lt;code&gt;[SFLC 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. The Internet Democracy Project, an initiative of Point of View, has organized online and offline discussions, participated in global summits, and produced reports on the topics of freedom of expression, cyber security and human rights, and global Internet governance architecture since 2012 &lt;code&gt;[IDP 2015]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Internet Society chapter to be established in India was in Delhi. The chapter began in 2002 but went through a period of no activity before being revived in 2008 &lt;code&gt;[Delhi 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. The Chennai chapter started in 2007 &lt;code&gt;[Chennai 2015]&lt;/code&gt;, the Kolkata one in 2009 &lt;code&gt;[Kolkata 2015]&lt;/code&gt;, and the Bengaluru chapter came into existence in 2010 &lt;code&gt;[Bangalore 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. Asia Internet Symposium have been organized in India twice: 1) the Kolkata one, held on on 1 December 2014, focused on &amp;lsquo;Internet and Human Rights: Empowering the Users,&amp;rsquo; and 2) the Chennai symposium, held on 2 December 2014, discussed &amp;lsquo;India in the Open and Global Internet.&amp;rsquo; The newest Internet Society chapter in India is in the process of formation in Trivandrum &lt;code&gt;[Trivandrum 2015]&lt;/code&gt;, led by the efforts of Satish Babu (mentioned above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;global-and-national-events:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Global and National Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) conference held on 10-12 December 2003 in Geneva, was not attended by many civil society organizations from India. Several Indian participants in the conference were part of a team of representatives from different global civil society organizations, including Digital Partners, Development Alternatives with Women for a New Era (DAWN), and International Centre for New Media &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003]&lt;/code&gt;. Between the first and the second conference, engagement with the WSIS process increased among Indian civil society organizations, and was especially led by IT for Change. In early 2005, before the second Preparatory Committee meeting for the Tunis conference, IT for Change organized a discussion event titled &amp;lsquo;Gender Perspectives on the Information Society: South Asia Pre-WSIS Seminar&amp;rsquo; in partnership with DAWN and the Indian Institute of Management, Bangalore, which was supported by UNIFEM and the UNDP Asia-Pacific Development Information Programme &lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. In a separate note, Anita Gurumurthy and Parminder Jeet Singh of IT for Change noted their experience as a South Asian civil society organization engaging with the WSIS process &lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2005]&lt;/code&gt;. The second WSIS conference in Tunis, held on 16-18 November 2005, however, did not see significant participation from Indian civil society organizations, except for Ambedkar Centre for Justice and Peace, Childline India Foundation / Child Helpline International, and IT for Change &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2005]&lt;/code&gt;. This contrasted sharply with the over 60 delegates from various Indian government agencies that took part in the conference &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2005]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two important events took place in India in early 2005 that substantially contributed to the civil society discourses in India around information technology and its socio-legal implications and possibilities. The firt was a conference titled &amp;lsquo;Contested Commons, Trespassing Publics&amp;rsquo; organized by the Sarai Programme at the Centre for the Study of Developing Societies, Alternative Law Forum, and Public Service Broadcasting Trust, in Delhi on 6-8 January 2005. This conference attempted to look into the terms of intellectual property rights (IPR) debates from the perspectives of experiences in countries in Asia, Latin America, and Africa. It was based on research carried out by the Sarai Programme and Alternative Law Forum on contemporary realities of media production and distribution, and the ways in which law and legal instruments enter into the most intimate spheres of social and cultural life to operationalize IPRs. The conference combined academic discussions with parallel demonstrations by media practitioners, and knowledge sharing by FLOSS communities &lt;code&gt;[Sarai 2005]&lt;/code&gt;. The second event was the first Asia Source workshop, which took place in Bengaluru during 28 January - 4 February 2005. It brought together more than 100 representatives from South and South-East Asian civil society organizations and technology practitioners working with them, along with several leading practitioners from Africa, Europe, North America, and Latin America, to promote adoption and usage of FLOSS across the developmental sector in the region. The workshop was organized by Mahiti (Bengaluru) and Tactical Technology Collective (Amsterdam), with intellectual and practical support from an advisory group of representatives from FLOSS communities and civil society organizations, and financial support from Hivos, the Open Society Institute, and International Open Source Network &lt;code&gt;[Asia 2015]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the participation of representatives from Indian civil society organizations at the IGFs in Athens (2006) and Rio de Janeiro (2007) was minimal, the IGF Hyderabad, held on 3-6 December 2008, provided a great opportunity for Indian civil society actors to participate in and familiarize themselves with the global Internet governance process. Apart from various professionals, especially lawyers, who attended the Hyderabad conference as individuals, the leading civil society organizations participating in the event included: Ambedkar Center for Justice and Peace, Centre for Internet and Society, Centre for Science, Development and Media Studies, Digital Empowerment Foundation, Internet Society Chennai chapter, IT for Change, and Mahiti. The non-governmental participants from India at the event, however, were predominantly from private companies and academic institutes &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2008]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IT for Change made a critical intervention into the discourse of global Internet governance during the Hyderabad conference by bringing back the term &amp;lsquo;enhanced cooperation&amp;rsquo;, as mentioned in the Tunis Agenda for the Information Society &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2005b]&lt;/code&gt;. At IGF Sharm El Sheikh, held during 15-18 November 2009, Parminder Jeet Singh of IT for Change explained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[E]nhanced cooperation consists of two parts. One part is dedicated to creating globally applicable policy principles, and there is an injunction to the relevant organizations to create the conditions for doing that. And I have a feeling that the two parts of that process have been conflated into one. And getting reports from the relevant organizations is going on, but we are not able to go forward to create a process which addresses the primary purpose of enhanced cooperation, which was to create globally applicable public policy principles and the proof of that is that I don&amp;rsquo;t see any development of globally applicable public policy principles, which remains a very important need &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2009]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This foregrounding of the principle of &amp;lsquo;enhanced cooperation&amp;rsquo; has since substantially contributed to rethinking of not only the global Internet governance mechanisms and its reconfigurations, but also the Indian government&amp;rsquo;s perspectives towards the same. It eventually led to the proposal made by a representative of Government of India at the UN General Assembly session on 26 October 2011 regarding the establishment of a UN Committee for Internet-Related Policies &lt;code&gt;[Singh 2011]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;internet-policies-and-censorship:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Internet Policies and Censorship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the earliest instances of censorship of online content in India was the blocking of several websites offering Voice over IP (VoIP) software, which can be downloaded to make low-cost international calls, during the late 1990s. The India-GII mailing list initiated by Arun Mehta, as mentioned above, started largely as a response to this blocking move by Videsh Sanchar Nigam Limited (VSNL), the government-owned Internet Service Provider (ISP). Additionally, Mehta filed a case against VSNL for blocking these e-commerce websites, which might be identified as the first case of legal activism for Internet-related rights in India &lt;code&gt;[India-GII 2001]&lt;/code&gt;. During the war between India and Pakistan in 1999, the Indian government instructed VSNL to block various Pakistani media websites, including that of Dawn. As in the case of websites offering VoIP services, this blocking did not involve direct intervention with the websites concerned but only the ability of Indian users to access them &lt;code&gt;[Tanna 2004]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first well-known case of the Government of India blocking digital content for political reasons occurred in 2003 when a mailing list titled &amp;lsquo;Kynhun&amp;rsquo; was banned. The Department of Telecommunications instructed all the ISPs to stop Indian users from accessing the list, hosted don Yahoo! Group, but the previously deployed URL-blocking strategy did not work in this new situation. Blocking the URL of the list did not stop its members from continuing to share emails through it. The Government of India then approached Yahoo! directly to ensure that the mailing list was taken down, which Yahoo! declined to implement. This resulted in the imposition of a blanket block on all Yahoo! Groups pages across ISPs in India in September 2003. By November, Yahoo! decided to close down the mailing list, and the blanket block was repealed &lt;code&gt;[Tanna 2004]&lt;/code&gt;. Further blocking of several blogs and websites continued through 2006 and 2007, where the government decided to work in collaboration with various platforms offering hosted blog and personal web page services to remove access to specific sub-domains. In resistance to this series of blocking orders by the government, there emerged an important civil society campaign titled &amp;lsquo;Bloggers Against Censorship&amp;rsquo; led by the Bloggers Collective Group, a distributed network of bloggers from all across India &lt;code&gt;[Bloggers 2006]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks after the IGF Hyderabad, the Government of India passed the Information Technology (Amendment) Act 2008 on 22 December 2008 &lt;code&gt;[MoLaJ 2009]&lt;/code&gt;, although it was notified and enforced much later on 27 October 2009 &lt;code&gt;[MoCaIT 2009]&lt;/code&gt;. This amendment attempted to clarify various topics left under-defined in the Information Technology Act of 2000. However, as Pranesh Prakash of the Centre for Internet and Society noted, the casual usage of the term &amp;lsquo;offensive content&amp;rsquo; in the amendment opened up serious threats of broad curbing of freedom of online expression under the justification that it caused &amp;lsquo;annoyance&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;inconvenience&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2009]&lt;/code&gt;. Sections 66 and 67 of the amended Information Technology Act, which respectively address limits to online freedom of expression and legally acceptable monitoring of digital communication by government agencies, have since been the objects of strong protests by civil society organizations across India for enabling broad-brushed censorship and surveillance of the Internet in India. Section 66A has, in particular, allowed the government to make a series of arrests of Internet users for posting and sharing &amp;lsquo;offensive content&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[Pahwa 2015]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, the Government of India introduced another critical piece of policy instrument for controlling online expressions – the Information Technology (Intermediary Guidelines) Rules, 2011 &lt;code&gt;[MoCaIT 2011]&lt;/code&gt; – targeted at defining the functions of the intermediaries associated with Internet-related services and communication, and how they are to respond to the government&amp;rsquo;s directives towards taking down and temporarily blocking digital content. The draft rules were published in early 2011 and comments were invited from the general public. One of the responses, submitted by Privacy India and the Centre for Internet and Society, explicitly highlighted the draconian implications of the (then) proposed rules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This rule requires an intermediary to take immediately steps to remove access to information merely upon receiving a written request from “any authority mandated under the law”. Thus, for example, any authority can easily immunize itself from criticism on the internet by simply sending a written notice to the intermediary concerned. This is directly contrary to, and completely subverts the legislative intent expressed in Section 69B which lays down an elaborate procedure to be followed before any information can be lawfully blocked &lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2011]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy apparatus of controlling online expression in India took full form by the beginning of the decade under study here. The &amp;lsquo;chilling effect&amp;rsquo; of this apparatus was made insightfully evident by a study conducted by Rishabh Dara at the Centre for Internet and Society, where fake takedown notices (regarding existing digital content) were sent to seven important Internet intermediaries operating in India, and their responses were studied. The results of this experiment demonstrated that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[T]he Rules create uncertainty in the criteria and procedure for administering the takedown, thereby inducing the intermediaries to err on the side of caution and over-comply with takedown notices in order to limit their liability, and as a result suppress legitimate expressions. Additionally, the Rules do not establish sufficient safeguards to prevent misuse and abuse of the takedown process to suppress legitimate expressions &lt;code&gt;[Dara 2012]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgment:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to Anita Gurumurthy and Parminder Jeet Singh for their generous sharing of information and insights. Raman Jit Singh Cheema, Pranesh Prakash, and Sunil Abraham have also provided crucial suggestions. Extensive background research by P.P. Sneha has significantly enriched my efforts. The Wayback Machine of the Internet Archive deserves a very special thanks. Last but not the least, I am thankful to Kilnam Chon for this wonderful opportunity and his patient support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reference:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Bloggers 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Bloggers Collective Group, Bloggers Against Censorship. Last updated on April 30, 2009‎. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://censorship.wikia.com/wiki/Bloggers_Against_Censorship&#34;&gt;http://censorship.wikia.com/wiki/Bloggers_Against_Censorship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Dara 2012]&lt;/code&gt; Dara, Rishabh, Intermediary Liability in India: Chilling Effects on Free Expression on the Internet. The Centre for Internet and Society. April 27. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/chilling-effects-on-free-expression-on-internet&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/chilling-effects-on-free-expression-on-internet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[DEF]&lt;/code&gt; Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF). Community Information Resource Centre. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://defindia.org/circ-2/&#34;&gt;http://defindia.org/circ-2/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[DEF b]&lt;/code&gt; Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF). Internet Rights. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://internetrights.in/&#34;&gt;http://internetrights.in/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[DEF c]&lt;/code&gt; Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF). Our Story. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://defindia.org/about-def/&#34;&gt;http://defindia.org/about-def/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[DEF d]&lt;/code&gt; Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF). Manthan Awards. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://defindia.org/manthan-award-south-asia-masa/&#34;&gt;http://defindia.org/manthan-award-south-asia-masa/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[FSFI]&lt;/code&gt; Free Software Foundation of India. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://fsf.org.in/&#34;&gt;http://fsf.org.in/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[FSMI]&lt;/code&gt; Free Software Movement of India. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fsmi.in/node&#34;&gt;http://www.fsmi.in/node&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2001]&lt;/code&gt; Gurumurthy, Anita, A Gender Perspective to ICTs and Development: Reflections towards Tunis. January 15. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldsummit2003.de/en/web/701.htm&#34;&gt;http://www.worldsummit2003.de/en/web/701.htm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2005]&lt;/code&gt; Gurumurthy, Anita, and Parminder Jeet Singh, WSIS PrepCom 2: A South Asian Perspective. Association for Progressive Communications. April 01. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apc.org/en/news/hr/world/wsis-prepcom-2-south-asian-perspective&#34;&gt;https://www.apc.org/en/news/hr/world/wsis-prepcom-2-south-asian-perspective&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Gurumuthy, Anita et al (eds.), Gender in the Information Society: Emerging Issues. UNDP Asia-Pacific Development Information Programme. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genderit.org/sites/default/upload/GenderIS.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.genderit.org/sites/default/upload/GenderIS.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[India-GII 2001]&lt;/code&gt; India-GII, Status of VSNL Censorship of IP-Telephony Sites. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://members.tripod.com/~india_gii/statusof.htm&#34;&gt;http://members.tripod.com/~india_gii/statusof.htm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[India-GII 2005]&lt;/code&gt; India-GII. 2005. Last modified on May 24. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://india-gii.org/&#34;&gt;http://india-gii.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IDP]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Democracy Project. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://internetdemocracy.in/&#34;&gt;http://internetdemocracy.in/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003]&lt;/code&gt; International Telecommunication Union (ITU), Geneva Phase of the WSIS: List of Participants. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/summit_participants.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/summit_participants.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITU 2005]&lt;/code&gt; International Telecommunication Union (ITU), List of Participants (WSIS) – Update 5 Dec 2005. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/final-list-participants.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/final-list-participants.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITU 2005 b]&lt;/code&gt; International Telecommunication Union (ITU), Tunis Agenda for the Information Society. November 18. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/off/6rev1.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/off/6rev1.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2008]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum, Hyderabad Provisional List of Participants. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/index.php/component/content/article/385-hyderabad-provisional-list-of-participants&#34;&gt;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/index.php/component/content/article/385-hyderabad-provisional-list-of-participants&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum, Managing Critical Resources. IGF Sharm El Sheikh, Egypt . November 16. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/2009/sharm_el_Sheikh/Transcripts/Sharm%20El%20Sheikh%2016%20November%202009%20Managing%20Critical%20Internet%20Resources.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/2009/sharm_el_Sheikh/Transcripts/Sharm%20El%20Sheikh%2016%20November%202009%20Managing%20Critical%20Internet%20Resources.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Bangalore]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Society Bangalore Chapter. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocbangalore.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocbangalore.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Delhi]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Society Delhi Chapter. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocbangalore.org&#34;&gt;http://www.isocbangalore.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Chennai]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Society Chennai Chapter. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocbangalore.org&#34;&gt;http://www.isocbangalore.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Kolkata]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Society Kolkata Chapter. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://isockolkata.in/&#34;&gt;http://isockolkata.in/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Trivandrum]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Society Trivandrum Chapter. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.internetsociety.org/what-we-do/where-we-work/chapters/india-trivandrum-chapter&#34;&gt;http://www.internetsociety.org/what-we-do/where-we-work/chapters/india-trivandrum-chapter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITfC]&lt;/code&gt; IT for Change, About IT for Change. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itforchange.net/aboutus&#34;&gt;http://www.itforchange.net/aboutus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITfC b]&lt;/code&gt; IT for Change, Anita Gurumurthy. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itforchange.net/Anita&#34;&gt;http://www.itforchange.net/Anita&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITfC c]&lt;/code&gt; IT for Change, Gender and Citizenship in the Information Society: Southern Feminist Dialogues in Practice and Theory. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gender-is-citizenship.net/&#34;&gt;http://www.gender-is-citizenship.net/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITfC d]&lt;/code&gt; IT for Change, Internet Governance. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itforchange.net/Techgovernance&#34;&gt;http://www.itforchange.net/Techgovernance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITfC e]&lt;/code&gt; IT for Change, Our Field Centre. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itforchange.net/field_centre&#34;&gt;http://www.itforchange.net/field_centre&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[JNC]&lt;/code&gt; Just Net Coalition (JNC). Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://justnetcoalition.org/&#34;&gt;http://justnetcoalition.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Kumar 2007]&lt;/code&gt; Kumar, Sasi V. 2007. The Story of Free Software in Kerala, India. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://swatantryam.blogspot.in/2007/08/story-of-free-software-in-kerala-india.html&#34;&gt;http://swatantryam.blogspot.in/2007/08/story-of-free-software-in-kerala-india.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[MoLaJ 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Ministry of Law and Justice (MoLaJ), The Information Technology (Amendment) Act, 2008. The Gazette of India. February 05. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/downloads/itact2000/it_amendment_act2008.pdf&#34;&gt;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/downloads/itact2000/it_amendment_act2008.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[MoCaIT 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Ministry of Communications and Information Technology (MoCaIT), Notification. The Gazette of India. October 27. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/downloads/itact2000/act301009.pdf&#34;&gt;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/downloads/itact2000/act301009.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[MoCaIT 2011]&lt;/code&gt; Ministry of Communications and Information Technology (MoCaIT), Information Technology (Intermediaries Guidelines) Rules, 2011. The Gazette of India. April 11. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/GSR314E_10511%281%29.pdf&#34;&gt;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/GSR314E_10511%281%29.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Noronha 2002]&lt;/code&gt; Noronha, Frederick, Linking a Diverse Country: Mailing Lists in India. The Digital Development Network. May 22. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.comminit.com/ict-4-development/content/linking-diverse-country-mailing-lists-india&#34;&gt;http://www.comminit.com/ict-4-development/content/linking-diverse-country-mailing-lists-india&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Pahwa 2015]&lt;/code&gt; Pahwa, Nikhil, A List of Section 66A Arrests in India through the Years. Medianama. March 24. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medianama.com/2015/03/223-section-66a-arrests-in-india/&#34;&gt;http://www.medianama.com/2015/03/223-section-66a-arrests-in-india/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Prakash, Pranesh, Short Note on IT Amendment Act, 2008 . The Centre for Internet and Society. February. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/publications/it-act/short-note-on-amendment-act-2008/&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/publications/it-act/short-note-on-amendment-act-2008/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2011]&lt;/code&gt; Prakash, Pranesh, CIS Para-wise Comments on Intermediary Due Diligence Rules, 2011. The Centre for Internet and Society. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/blog/intermediary-due-diligence&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/blog/intermediary-due-diligence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2011 b]&lt;/code&gt; Prakash, Pranesh, et al, Open Government Data Study. The Centre for Internet and Society. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/openness/blog/open-government-data-study&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/openness/blog/open-government-data-study&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[SFLC]&lt;/code&gt; Software Freedom Law Centre (SFLC). Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://sflc.in/&#34;&gt;http://sflc.in/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Shah 2011]&lt;/code&gt; Shah, Nishant. 2011. Digital AlterNatives with a Cause? The Centre for Internet and Society. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/digital-natives/blog/dnbook&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/digital-natives/blog/dnbook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Singh 2011]&lt;/code&gt; Singh, Dushyant, India&amp;rsquo;s Proposal for a United Nations Committee for Internet-Related Policies. Sixty Sixth Session of the UN General Assembly, New York. October 26. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itforchange.net/sites/default/files/ItfC/india_un_cirp_proposal_20111026.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itforchange.net/sites/default/files/ItfC/india_un_cirp_proposal_20111026.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[SKC]&lt;/code&gt; Society for Knowledge Commons. About Us. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.knowledgecommons.in/about-us/&#34;&gt;http://www.knowledgecommons.in/about-us/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Asia Source]&lt;/code&gt; Tactical Technology Collective, Asia Source. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://tacticaltech.org/asiasource&#34;&gt;https://tacticaltech.org/asiasource&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Tanna 2004]&lt;/code&gt; Tanna, Ketan, Internet Censorship in India: Is It Necessary and Does It Work?. Sarai-CSDS Independent Fellowship. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ketan.net/INTERNET_CENSORSHIP_IN_INDIA.html&#34;&gt;http://www.ketan.net/INTERNET_CENSORSHIP_IN_INDIA.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[CIS]&lt;/code&gt; The Centre for Internet and Society. About Us. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/about/&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/about/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[CIS 2008]&lt;/code&gt; The Centre for Internet and Society. 2008. Annual Report. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/accessibility/annual-report-2008.pdf&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/accessibility/annual-report-2008.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Sarai 2005]&lt;/code&gt; The Sarai Programme, Contested Commons, Trespassing Publics. January 12. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://sarai.net/contested-commons-trespassing-publics/&#34;&gt;http://sarai.net/contested-commons-trespassing-publics/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Wikipedia 2015]&lt;/code&gt; Satish Babu. Wikipedia. Last modified on June 25. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satish_Babu&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satish_Babu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Aakash Tablet and Technological Imaginaries of Mass Education in Contemporary India</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/aakash-tablet-and-technological-imaginaries-of-mass-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2016 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/aakash-tablet-and-technological-imaginaries-of-mass-education/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;co-authored-with-dr-jahnavi-phalkey-http-www-kcl-ac-uk-sspp-sga-kii-people-jahnaviphalkey-index-aspx:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;Co-authored with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kcl.ac.uk/sspp/sga/kii/people/jahnaviphalkey/index.aspx&#34;&gt;Dr. Jahnavi Phalkey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper, co-authored by Dr. Jahnavi Phalkey, King&amp;rsquo;s College London, and I, was published in &lt;em&gt;History and Technology&lt;/em&gt;, on 5 February, 2016. It can be accessed from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/07341512.2015.1136142&#34;&gt;journal website&lt;/a&gt; (behind pay wall), and the pre-publication version is available from &lt;a href=&#34;http://ssrn.com/abstract=2761716&#34;&gt;SSRN&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We explore here public and private initiatives in technological solutions for educating the poor and the disadvantaged in India since the second half of the twentieth century. Specifically, we document Ministry of Human Resource Development’s project to develop an affordable tablet computer, named ‘Aakash,’ as a personal access device for digital courses and online learning materials. We approach this case study in relation to several educational technologies that preceded it, and with a wider interest in mapping a contemporary transition from satellite-based mass education to Internet-based mass education. We argue that this process cannot be easily seen as a transition from unilateral broadcasting to more democratic multi-casting model of communication and learning. Specifically, we study the manufacturing process of Aakash and the public debates around it, to comment on the nature of state power in India, as revealed in its attempts to imagine and develop a digital personal device to deliver mass education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blog-post:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;Blog Post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;this-blog-post-containing-excerpts-from-the-paper-was-published-by-the-south-asia-lse-blog-http-blogs-lse-ac-uk-southasia-2016-02-12-the-aakash-tablet-and-technological-imaginaries-of-mass-education-in-contemporary-india-on-february-12-2016:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;This blog post containing excerpts from the paper was published by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.lse.ac.uk/southasia/2016/02/12/the-aakash-tablet-and-technological-imaginaries-of-mass-education-in-contemporary-india/&#34;&gt;South Asia @ LSE Blog&lt;/a&gt;, on February 12, 2016.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/SC_Aakash_Resized.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;code&#34; title=&#34;Students at Pardada Pardadi Education Society in Anupshahr, Uttar Pradesh, use the Aakash tablet in class as part of a pilot project. Photograph by Sonali Campion.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;students-at-pardada-pardadi-education-society-in-anupshahr-uttar-pradesh-use-the-aakash-tablet-in-class-as-part-of-a-pilot-project-introducing-the-low-cost-computer-into-rural-schools-photograph-by-sonali-campion-https-www-flickr-com-photos-sonalicampion-9449250639-april-09-2013:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;Students at Pardada Pardadi Education Society in Anupshahr, Uttar Pradesh, use the Aakash tablet in class as part of a pilot project introducing the low-cost computer into rural schools. Photograph by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sonalicampion/9449250639/&#34;&gt;Sonali Campion&lt;/a&gt;, April 09, 2013.&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2010, the Ministry of Human Resource Development (MHRD) of the Government of India launched a set of prototype devices of an affordable tablet computer, the development and production of which were to be supported by the Ministry as part of its larger ICTs for education project. This device later came to be known as the “Aakash” tablet, and the project went through several iterations, between 2010 and 2014, of not only technological re-designs, but also institutional arrangements to design, develop, manufacture, test, and procure the devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;technological-solutions-for-mass-education:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;Technological Solutions for Mass Education&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our exploration of technological solutions for mass education in India has taken us through a not-so-linear history of projects that have informed the imagination and making of the Aakash project. This include the Satellite Instructional Television Experiment, or SITE (1975); University Grants Commission-led Countrywide Classroom project (1984 -); the Simputer, the first hand-held device developed in India (1998); the Hole in the Wall project developed and led by Sugata Mitra (1999); the Government of India-led EDUSAT (2004); National Programme on Technology Enhanced Learning (2003); and finally, a national online education portal named Sakshat (2006). The Satellite Instructional Television Experiment itself terminated rather quickly, but it led to several versions of television based instruction programmes, most notably aimed at higher secondary and university students. Instruction in the broadcast-format continues to date, even after the arrival of the internet and the fact it has become the preferred medium for the Indian state. The television has not been replaced, but certainly shadowed by a variety of internet access and computing devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;aakash-a-low-cost-access-cum-computing-device:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;Aakash, a “Low Cost Access-Cum-Computing Device”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An early official description of the then-nameless tablet as a “low cost access-cum-computing device” is noteworthy &lt;code&gt;[1]&lt;/code&gt;. It is difficult to imagine a contemporary computing device that does not also function as an access device (say, to the internet). Where does the need for calling it an “access-cum-computing” device come from? It comes, perhaps, from the hierarchy of priority – the device is primarily an access device, and secondarily can perform the function of a general-purpose computer. An archaeological reading of the assumptions of learning processes embodied in this device reveals an earlier layer of thinking – that of broadcasting educational programmes to television sets via satellite connection. Labelling it as “access-cum-computing” frames the object as being shaped by the residue of the Indian state’s education technological experiences of the past, including that of the SITE initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-aakash-tablet-was-my-dream-but-it-was-not-fulfilled:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;“[The] Aakash tablet was my dream but it was not fulfilled”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the short history of the Aakash device, the verdict of “failed innovation” figures prominently – from the early failure of “Sakshat” &lt;code&gt;[2]&lt;/code&gt;, to allegations of the Chinese origin of the Aakash device &lt;code&gt;[3]&lt;/code&gt;, to manufacturing troubles and under-production of the device &lt;code&gt;[4]&lt;/code&gt;, to criticisms of the tablet’s built quality and computing capacity &lt;code&gt;[5]&lt;/code&gt;, to mistrust and failed collaborations between parties involved in its production &lt;code&gt;[6]&lt;/code&gt;, and intra-governmental criticisms of the implementation process &lt;code&gt;[7]&lt;/code&gt;. Moreover, there remained a continuous tension within the government itself regarding the necessity of the project, especially fuelled by (and fuelling) the image of the project as being driven by the dreams of a specific minister &lt;code&gt;[8]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To simply describe the Aakash project’s failure as one due to the unbearable heaviness of functions ranging from the technical to the symbolic and political is to fall short of a full explanation. Alongside that narrative of failure, it is critical to foreground the quiet success of the project in establishing the tablet computer as a near-essential and familiarised everyday object for access to educational material. There is an alarming accuracy in the MHRD claim that the Aakash project established a sub $100 tablet market in India – it did, even if it was not for the device they wanted to promote &lt;code&gt;[9]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-device-is-the-desire:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;The Device is the Desire&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We observe that the Aakash project, as well as the ones preceding it, have been driven primarily by a desire to scale up the provision of education. The initiatives towards building delivery infrastructures for such mass-scale provision of education has almost always been accompanied by a larger desire for developing capabilities in space exploration, communication, and computing – the key technologies of twentieth century geopolitics. Our study of the manufacturing of the Aakash tablet, and its surrounding discourses, foreground the technological imagination of the state after liberalisation in India (1991), and its unique arrangements and efforts to create domestic capability of technological innovation in a context of globalised production and communication networks. We see our role as one of recovering the work of technology in the history of education as understood through the interactions between the state, academia, and industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;archival-research-in-increasingly-digital-india:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;Archival Research in (Increasingly) Digital India&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Documenting the project has been an interesting historical exercise. We have been attentive to documents disappearing from their online locations. One remarkable possibility for archival research opened up by the internet is the (limited, and often uncertain) ability to access materials that are not presently available on a website, but were part of it in the past. This possibility allowed us to access a few crucial government documents that are not directly available on the official websites any more. We have also been attentive to the reiterations and revisions that do not merely overtake or shadow earlier documents. They sometimes erase earlier documents altogether as digital revisions. We do not have access to personal correspondence or internal institutional correspondence relating to the project. We are, however, skeptical of that happening as no protocols for the archiving of digital correspondence is yet in place with the Government of India. Doing recent history of India is becoming an ever more difficult exercise that historians must urgently attend to, if we are to make the present ready to have its own past in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[1]&lt;/code&gt; Ministry of Human Resource Development, Government of India. “The History of Aakash Low Cost Access cum Computing Device.” Sakshat. October 05, 2011. &lt;a href=&#34;http://archive.sakshat.ac.in/pdf/Final_Note_Aakash.pdf&#34;&gt;http://archive.sakshat.ac.in/pdf/Final_Note_Aakash.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[2]&lt;/code&gt; Mukherjee, Arindam. “Bonsai Netbooks.” Outlook. February 16, 2009. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.outlookindia.com/article/Bonsai-Netbooks/239719&#34;&gt;http://www.outlookindia.com/article/Bonsai-Netbooks/239719&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[3]&lt;/code&gt; Raina, Pamposh, and Mia Li. “India’s ‘Aakash,’ Now Made in China.” The New York Times. November 26, 2012. &lt;a href=&#34;http://india.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/11/26/india%E2%80%99s-super-cheap-tablet-now-made-in-china/&#34;&gt;http://india.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/11/26/india%E2%80%99s-super-cheap-tablet-now-made-in-china/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[4]&lt;/code&gt; Nanda, Prashant K., and Surabhi Agarwal. “Government Close to Giving Up on Aakash Project.” Mint. March 22, 2013. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.livemint.com/Politics/fmEi8gsOSFgOzSTFfLsw6J/Govt-almost-gives-up-on-Aakash-says-no-point-in-hardware-ob.html&#34;&gt;http://www.livemint.com/Politics/fmEi8gsOSFgOzSTFfLsw6J/Govt-almost-gives-up-on-Aakash-says-no-point-in-hardware-ob.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[5]&lt;/code&gt; Chopra, Ritika. “Kapil Sibal&amp;rsquo;s Cheap Aakash Proves to be a Dud.” Mail Today. January 08, 2012. &lt;a href=&#34;http://indiatoday.intoday.in/story/kapil-sibal-cheapest-tablet-of-world-aakash-failure/1/167730.html&#34;&gt;http://indiatoday.intoday.in/story/kapil-sibal-cheapest-tablet-of-world-aakash-failure/1/167730.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[6]&lt;/code&gt; Julka, Harsimran. “14 Lakh Aakash Tablets Booked in 14 Days.” The Economic Times. January 03, 2012. &lt;a href=&#34;http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/tech/hardware/14-lakh-aakash-tablets-booked-in-14-days/articleshow/11345695.cms&#34;&gt;http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/tech/hardware/14-lakh-aakash-tablets-booked-in-14-days/articleshow/11345695.cms&lt;/a&gt;. Parthasarathi, Ashok. “Cloudy Outlook for Aakash.” The Hindu. May 21, 2012 (Updated: May 22, 2012). &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thehindu.com/opinion/op-ed/article3439629.ece&#34;&gt;http://www.thehindu.com/opinion/op-ed/article3439629.ece&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[7]&lt;/code&gt; Comptroller and Auditor General of India, Government of India. Report No. 19 of 2013 - Union Government (Civil) - Report of the Comptroller and Auditor General of India on Compliance Audit Observations. Government of India. 2013. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cag.gov.in/content/report-no-19-2013-compliance-audit-observations-union-governmentcivil&#34;&gt;http://www.cag.gov.in/content/report-no-19-2013-compliance-audit-observations-union-governmentcivil&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[8]&lt;/code&gt; At an event in late 2013, Kapil Sibal admitted, “[the] Aakash tablet was my dream but it was not fulfilled, I tried hard…” Quoted in Press Trust of India. “Kapil Sibal: Aakash Tablet is My Unfulfilled Dream.” Financial Express. December 24, 2013. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.financialexpress.com/news/kapil-sibal-aakash-tablet-is-my-unfulfilled-dream/1211284/0&#34;&gt;http://www.financialexpress.com/news/kapil-sibal-aakash-tablet-is-my-unfulfilled-dream/1211284/0&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[9]&lt;/code&gt; See [1].&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Studying the Emerging Database State in India: Notes for Critical Data Studies - Accepted Abstract</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/studying-the-emerging-database-state-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2015 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/studying-the-emerging-database-state-in-india/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A paper abstract of mine has been provisionally accepted for publication in the upcoming special issue of &lt;a href=&#34;http://bds.sagepub.com/&#34;&gt;Big Data &amp;amp; Society&lt;/a&gt; journal on &amp;lsquo;Critical Data Studies.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://bigdatasoc.blogspot.co.uk/2015/06/call-for-proposals-special-theme-on.html&#34;&gt;call for papers&lt;/a&gt; of the issue notes that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critical Data Studies (CDS) is a growing field of research that focuses on the unique theoretical, ethical, and epistemological challenges posed by “Big Data.” Rather than treat Big Data as a scientifically empirical, and therefore largely neutral phenomena, CDS advocates the view that data should be seen as always-already constituted within wider data assemblages&amp;hellip; CDS questions the many assumptions about data that permeate contemporary literature on information and society by locating instances where data may be naively taken to denote objective and transparent informational entities. CDS may be viewed as an emerging field connected to Information Ethics, Software Studies, and Critical Information Studies in that it seeks to question the ethical import of information and Big Data for society&amp;hellip; We seek essays for this special volume that broaden these latest commitments in CDS to include new empirical research projects on information and communication technologies (ICTs) that fall under the umbrella of Big Data, while also seeking to question their attendant epistemological shifts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the last decade, the Government of India has given shape to an digital identification infrastructure, developed and operated by the Unique Identification Authority of India (UIDAI). The infrastructure combines the task of assigning unique identification numbers, called Aadhaar numbers, to individuals submitting their biometric and demographic details, and the task of authenticating their identity when provided with an Aadhaar number and associated data (biometric data, One Time Pin sent to the pre-declared mobile number, etc.). The aim of UIDAI is to provide universal authentication-as-a-service for all residents of India who approach any public or private agencies for any kind of service or transaction. Simultaneously, the Aadhaar numbers will function as unique identifiers for joining up databases of different government agencies, and hence allow the Indian government to undertake big data analytics at a governmental scale, and not only at a departmental one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, I am primarily motivated by the challenge of finding points and objects to enter into a critical study of such an in-progress data infrastructure. As I proceed with an understanding that data is produced within its specific social and material context, the question then is to read through the data to reflect on its possible social and material context. This is complicated when approaching a big data infrastructure that is meant to produce data for explicitly intra-governmental consumption and circulation. The problem then is not one of reading through available big data, but one of reading through the assemblage and imaginaries of big data to reflect on the kind of data it will give rise to, and thus on the politics of the data assemblage and the database state it enables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;logic-of-the-database-state:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Logic of the Database State&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Application of data to inform governmental acts have taken place at least since government has been understood as responsible for the welfare of the population and the territory. The measurement of the population and the territory – the number of people, their demographic features, amounts and locations of natural resources, and so on – have always been integral to the functioning of the modern nation-state. Database state is used in this paper to identify a particular mode of mobilisation of data within governmental acts, which is fundamentally shaped by the possibilities of big data extraction, appropriation, and analytics pioneered by a range of companies since late 1990s. The reason for not using big data state but database dtate is that big data refers to a body of technologies emerging in response to a set of data management and analysis challenges situated in a certain moment of development of information technologies, whereas database refers to a symbolic form (Manovich 1999): a form in which not only the population is made visible to the government (as a collection of visual, textual, numeric, and other forms of records), but also how the acts of government are made visible to the population (as a collection of performance indicators, budget allocation and utilisation tables, and other data visualised through dashboards, analog and digital).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data production and management logic of this database state is specifically inspired by the notion of platform introduced by the so-called Web 2.0 companies: providing a common service layer upon which various other applications may also run, but under specific arrangements (including distribution of generated user data) with the original common layer provider. Data assemblages of the database state are expected to enable the government to function as a platform, as an intensely data-driven layer that widely gathers data about population individuals and feeds it back selectively to various providers of public and private services. This transforms the data assemblage from one vertical of governmental activities to a horizontal critical infrastructure for modularisation of governmental activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;studying-the-emerging-database-state-in-india:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Studying the Emerging Database State in India&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government of India is presently debating the legal and technical validity of the digital identity infrastructure programme in the Supreme Court, while simultaneously carrying out the enrolment drive for the same, linking up assignment of unique identity numbers with a national drive for population registration, and rolling out citizen-facing services and applications that implement the Aadhaar number as a necessary key to access them. With the enrollment process going on and the integration with various governmental processes (termed seeding by Aadhaar policy literature) just beginning, I enter this study through two key sets of objects reflecting the imaginaries and the technical specifications of the emerging database state in India. The first entry point is through the various official documents of vision, intentions, plans, and reconsiderations, and the second entry point is through the Application Programming Interface (API) documentations published by UIDAI to specify how its identity authentication platform will collaborate with various public and private services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first section of the paper provides a brief survey of pre-UIDAI attempts by the Government of India to deploy unique identification numbers and Smart Cards for specific population groups, so as to understand the initial conceptualisation of this data assemblage of a digital identification platform. The second section foregrounds how this platform undertakes a transformation of the components and relations of the pre-existing data assemblage of the Government of India, as articulated in various official documents of promised utility and proposed collaborations. The third section studies the API documentations to track how such imaginaries are materially interpreted and operationalised through the design of protocols of data interactions with various public and private agencies offering services utilising the identity authentication platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;notes-for-critical-data-studies:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Notes for Critical Data Studies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expanding the early agenda note on Critical Data Studies by Craig Dalton and Jim Thatcher (2014), Rob Kitchin and Tracey P. Lauriault have taken steps towards emphasising the responsibility of this nebulous research strategy to chart and unpack the data assemblages (2014). This is exactly what I propose to do in this paper. While Kitchin and Lauriault provide a detailed list of the components of the apparatus of a data assemblage (2014: 7), I find the concepts of infrastructural components and infrastructural relations very useful in thinking through the emerging infrastructure of authentication. Thus, my approach to these tasks of charting and unpacking is focused on the infrastructural relations that the digital identity infrastructure re-configures, instead of the infrastructural components it mobilises (Bowker et al 2010). This tactical choice of focusing on the infrastructural relations is also necessitated by the practical difficulty in having comprehensive access to the individual components of the data assemblage concerned. Addressing questions of causality and quality becomes difficult when studying the assemblage sans the produced data, and rigorously analysing concerns of security and uncertainty pre-requires an actually existing data assemblage, with a public interface to investigating its leakages, breakages, and internal functioning. In the absence of such points of entry into the data assemblage, which I fear may not be an exceptional case, I attempt an inverted reading. Turning the data infrastructure inside out, in this paper I describe how the digital identity platform is critically reshaping the basis of governmental acts in India, through a specific model of production, extraction and application of big data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bibliography:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bowker, Geoffrey C., Karen Baker, Florence Millerand, &amp;amp; David Ribes. 2010. Toward Information Infrastructure Studies: Ways of Knowing in a Networked Environment. Jeremy Hunsinger, Lisbeth Klastrup, &amp;amp; Matthew Allen (Eds.) International Handbook of Internet Research. Springer Dordrecht Heidelberg London New York. Pp. 97-117.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dalton, Craig, &amp;amp; Jim Thatcher. 2014. What does a Critical Data Studies Look Like, and Why do We Care? Seven Points for a Critical Approach to ‘Big Data.’ Society and Space. May 19. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://societyandspace.com/material/commentaries/craig-dalton-and-jim-thatcher-what-does-a-critical-data-studies-look-like-and-why-do-we-care-seven-points-for-a-critical-approach-to-big-data/&#34;&gt;http://societyandspace.com/material/commentaries/craig-dalton-and-jim-thatcher-what-does-a-critical-data-studies-look-like-and-why-do-we-care-seven-points-for-a-critical-approach-to-big-data/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kitchin, Rob, &amp;amp; Tracey P. Lauriault. 2014. Towards Critical Data Studies: Charting and Unpacking Data Assemblages and their Work. The Programmable City Working Paper 2. July 29. National University of Ireland Maynooth, Ireland. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2474112&#34;&gt;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2474112&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manovich, Lev. 1999. Database as Symbolic Form. Convergence. Volume 5, Number 2. Pp. 80-99.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital Activism in Asia Reader</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/digital-activism-in-asia-reader/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2015 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/digital-activism-in-asia-reader/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;co-edited-with-prof-nishant-shah-http-cdc-leuphana-com-people-nishant-shah-and-puthiya-purayil-sneha-http-cis-india-org-about-people-our-team-sneha:8d1467b8da1a03f3ba8d40454c48961f&#34;&gt;Co-edited with &lt;a href=&#34;http://cdc.leuphana.com/people/#nishant-shah&#34;&gt;Prof. Nishant Shah&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/about/people/our-team#sneha&#34;&gt;Puthiya Purayil Sneha&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/daar_cover.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;code&#34; title=&#34;Digital Activism in Asia Reader - Cover&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Digital Activism in Asia Reader took shape over two workshops with a diverse range of participants, including activists, change-makers, and scholars, organised by the Researchers at Work (RAW) programme in June 2014 and March 2015. During the first workshop, the participants identified the authors, topics, and writings that should be included/featured in the reader, based upon their relevance in the grounded practices of the participants, who came from various Asian countries. The second workshop involved open discussions regarding how the selected readings should be annotated, from key further questions to strategies of introducing them, followed by development of the annotations by the participants of the workshop. The full list of contributors, annotators, and editors is mentioned at the end of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Reader is edited by Nishant Shah, Puthiya Purayil Sneha, and I, with support from Anirudh Sridhar, Denisse Albornoz, and Verena Getahun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are grateful to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://meson.press/about/&#34;&gt;Meson Press&lt;/a&gt; for its generous and patience support throughout the development process of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please download, read, and share this open-access book from the Meson Press website: &lt;a href=&#34;http://meson.press/books/digital-activism-in-asia-reader/&#34;&gt;http://meson.press/books/digital-activism-in-asia-reader/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;excerpt-from-the-foreword:8d1467b8da1a03f3ba8d40454c48961f&#34;&gt;Excerpt from the Foreword&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compiling this Reader on Digital Activism in Asia is fraught with compelling challenges, because each of the key terms in the formulation of the title is sub-ject to multiple interpretations and fierce contestations. The construction of ‘Asia’ as a region, has its historical roots in processes of colonial technologies of cartography and navigation. Asia was both, a measured entity, mapped for resources to be exploited, and also a measure of the world, promising anorientation to the Western World’s own turbulent encounters. As Chen Kuan-Hsing points out in his definitive history of the region, Asia gets re-imagined as­ a­ ‘method’ in cold-war conflicts, becoming the territory to be assimilated through exports of different ideologies and cultural purports. Asia does not have its own sense of being­ a­region. The transactions, interactions, flows and exchanges between different countries and regions in Asia have been so entirely mediated by powers of colonisation that the region remains divided and reticent in its imagination of itself. However, by the turn of the 21st century, Asia has seen­ a­ new awakening. It finds­ a­ regional identity, which, surprisingly did not emerge from its consolidating presence in global economics or in globalised structures of trade and commerce. Instead, it finds­ a­ presence, for itself, through a series of crises of governance, of social order, of political rights, and of cultural productions, that binds it together in unprecedented ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The digital turn might as well be marked as an Asian turn, because with the new networks of connectivity, with Asian countries marking themselves as informatics hubs, working through a circulated logic of migrant labour and dis-tributed resources, there came a sense of immediacy, proximity, and urgencythat continues to shape the Asian imagination in a new way. In the last decade or so, the rapid changes that have emerged, creating multiple registers of modernity, identity, and community in different parts of Asia, accelerated by a­ seamless exchange of ideas, commodities, cultures, and people have created a new sense of the region as emerging through co-presence rather than competition and conflict. Simultaneously, the emergence of global capitals of information, labour and cultural export, have created new reference points by which the region creates its identities and networks that are no longer subject to the tyranny of Western hegemony&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the digital remains crucial to this shaping of contemporary Asia, both in sustaining the developmental agenda that most of the countries espouse, and in opening up an inward looking gaze of statecraft and social organisation, the digital itself remains an ineffable concept. Largely because the digital is like­ a­ blackbox that conflates multiple registers of meaning and layers of life, it becomes important to unengineer it and see what it enables and hides. The economic presence of the digital is perhaps the most visible in telling the story of Asia in the now. Beginning with the dramatic development of Singapore as the centre of informatics governance and the emergence of a range of cities from Shanghai to Manilla and Bangalore to Tehran, there has been an accelerated narrative of economic growth and accumulation of capital that is often the global face of the Asian turn. However, this economic reordering is not a practice in isolation. It brings with it, a range of social stirrings that seek to overthrow traditional structures of oppression, corruption, control, and injustice that have often remained hidden in the closed borders of Asian countries. However, the digital marks a particular shift where these questions are no longer being excavated by the ICT4D logic, of the West’s attempts to save Asia from itself. These are questions that emerge from the ground, as more people interact with progressive and liberal politics and aspire not only for higher purchase powers but a better quality of rights. The digital turn has opened up a range of social and political rights based discourses, practices, and movements, where populations are holding their governments and countries responsible, accountable, and culpable in the face of personal and collective loss and injustice&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of this multiplicity of digital sites and usages that are reconfiguring Asia, it is obvious then, that the very nature of what constitutes activism is changing as well. Organised civil society presence in Asia has often had a strong role in shaping modern nation states, but more often than not these processes were defined in the same vocabulary as that of the powers that they were fighting against.­ Marked by­ a­ strong sense of developmentalism and often working in complement to the state rather than keeping a check on the state’s activities, traditional activism in Asia has often suffered from the incapacity to scale and the inability to find alternatives to the state-defined scripts of development, growth and progress. In countries where literacy rates have been low, these movements also suffer from being conceived in philosophical and linguistic sophistry that escapes the common citizen and remains the playground of the few who have privileges afforded to them by class and region. Digital Activism, however, seems to have broken this language barrier, both internally and externally, allowing for new visualities enabled by ubiquitous computing to bring various stakeholders into the fray… At the same time, the digital itself has introduced new problems and concerns that are often glossed over, in the enthralling tale of progress. Concerns around digital divide, invasive practices of personal data gathering, the nexus of markets and governments that install the citizen/consumer in precarious conditions, and the re-emergence of organised conservative politics are also a part of the digital turn. Activism has had to focus not only on digital as a tool, but digital also as a site of protest and resistance&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Reader does not offer an index of the momentous emergence with the growth of the digital or a chronological account of how digital activism in Asia has grown and shaped the region. Instead, the Reader attempts a crowd-sourced compilation that presents critical tools, organisations, theoretical concepts, political analyses, illustrative case-studies and annotations, that an emerging network of changemakers in Asia have identified as important in their own practices within their own contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opening Government Data through Mediation</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/opening-government-data-through-mediation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2015 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/opening-government-data-through-mediation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;report-produced-as-part-of-the-exploring-the-emerging-impacts-of-open-data-in-developing-countries-http-opendataresearch-org-emergingimpacts-project-of-the-open-data-research-network-http-opendataresearch-org-managed-by-the-world-wide-web-foundation-and-supported-by-the-international-development-research-centre-canada:d228ae7112f637e5efb26e3cab82dc7b&#34;&gt;Report produced as part of the &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://opendataresearch.org/emergingimpacts&#34;&gt;Exploring the Emerging Impacts of Open Data in Developing Countries&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; project of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://opendataresearch.org/&#34;&gt;Open Data Research Network&lt;/a&gt;, managed by the World Wide Web Foundation and supported by the International Development Research Centre, Canada.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://data.gov.in/sites/default/files/NDSAP.pdf&#34;&gt;National Data Sharing and Accessibility Policy (NDSAP)&lt;/a&gt; was approved by the Government of India in early 2012 to encourage and govern publication of government created and owned datasets, from various agencies of the central government of India, in open digital formats and through a single national data portal. The Policy extended the mandate of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rti.gov.in/rti-act.pdf&#34;&gt;Right to Information Act of 2005&lt;/a&gt; by establishing the principles and procedures of proactive disclosure of government data in India. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://data.gov.in/&#34;&gt;Open Government Data Platform of India&lt;/a&gt; was launched later in 2012 to collect and publish open government data. This study explores the existing practices of accessing and using government data in India to understand what challenges this Policy and its implementation measures must overcome to actualise the open data agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study surveys selected non­governmental and non­commercial data intermediary organisations, across sectors, that enable other organisations to better work with (access, use, and share) government and non­government data. Interviewing representatives of these organisations and understanding their actual data practices, the study attempts to respond to three key objectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;to undertake a provisional mapping of government data related activities across different sectors to understand the nature of the “open data community” in India,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;to enrich government data/information policy discussion in India by gathering evidence and experience of (non-governmental) data intermediaries regarding their actual practices of accessing and sharing government data, and their utilisation of the provisions of NDSAP and RTI act, and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;to critically reflect on the nature of open data practices in India.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;project-report:d228ae7112f637e5efb26e3cab82dc7b&#34;&gt;Project Report&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project website can be accessed here: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/&#34;&gt;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project Report - Executive Summary: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/report/sumandro_oddc_executive_summary.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/report/report_summary.html&#34;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project Report - Complete: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/report/sumandro_oddc_project_report.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/report/report_01_introduction.html&#34;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-materials:d228ae7112f637e5efb26e3cab82dc7b&#34;&gt;Other Materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timeline of open government data in India: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/resources/timeline.html&#34;&gt;URL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mapping data practices of (potential) data intermediary organisations in India: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/resources/mapping_data_practices.html&#34;&gt;URL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey questionnaire document: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/resources/sumandro_oddc_questionnaire_final.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Open Data Agenda for Post-2015 Sustainable Development Goals</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/an-open-data-agenda-for-post-2015-sustainable-development-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2014 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/an-open-data-agenda-for-post-2015-sustainable-development-goals/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;this-is-the-text-of-a-submission-note-prepared-by-me-in-response-to-the-call-from-the-independent-expert-advisory-group-on-data-revolution-and-sustainable-development-of-united-nations-it-includes-contributions-from-tim-davies-zacharia-chiliswa-and-gisele-s-craveiro:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;This is the text of a submission note prepared by me in response to the call from the Independent Expert Advisory Group on ‘data revolution and sustainable development’ of United Nations. It includes contributions from Tim Davies, Zacharia Chiliswa, and Gisele S. Craveiro.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The submitted document can be accessed here: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ajantriks/docs/blob/master/sumandro_ieag_datarevolution_submission_2014.10.15.pdf?raw=true&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1-an-open-data-agenda-for-post-2015-sustainable-development-goals:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;1. An Open Data Agenda for Post-2015 Sustainable Development Goals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;2-embracing-open-data-in-data-revolution-for-sustainable-development:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2. Embracing Open Data in ‘Data Revolution for Sustainable Development’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;2-1-openness-in-data-production:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2.1. Openness in Data Production&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;2-2-openness-in-data-publication:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2.2. Openness in Data Publication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;2-3-openness-in-data-usage:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2.3. Openness in Data Usage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;3-references:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;3. References&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;4-profiles:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;4. Profiles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-an-open-data-agenda-for-post-2015-sustainable-development-goals:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;1. An Open Data Agenda for Post-2015 Sustainable Development Goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data revolution’ has been one of the most remarkable categories of imagination and exploration to emerge from the report of the United Nation’s High Level Panel on the Post-2015 Development Agenda &lt;code&gt;[1]&lt;/code&gt;. The identification of availability of data on the global status of human development as a key problem area is not surprising given the experiences of measuring, monitoring and implement the Millennium Development Goals. Nonetheless, the recommendation by the High Level Panel for massive restructuring of infrastructures for generating global, reliable, comparable, and timely data is significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A brief note prepared by the High Level Panel explains that the ‘data revolution’ has two key objectives: ‘1) the integration of statistics into public and private sector decision making; and 2) building trust between society and state through transparency and accountability’ &lt;code&gt;[2]&lt;/code&gt;. The note also lists nine strategic interventions required to achieve these objectives. Only one of which, however, addresses the second main objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This submission suggests that an accountable and transparent revolution of global collection and utilisation of data for sustainable development must embrace openness as a fundamental pre-condition of the data concerned. In other words, a data revolution for sustainable development must be based upon global collection, usage, and publication of open data (relevant for purposes of sustainable development).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Independent Expert Advisory Group on ‘data revolution for sustainable development’ (henceforth, IEAG) has already addressed the question of open data through defining one of its consultation areas around the concept of ‘Accessible Data,’ which comprises of topics related to open data, accountability, and data literacy. This submission, however, proposes that open data must be considered as a cross-cutting principle and instrument of ensuring transparency, trust and security spanning all the constituent areas of the ‘data revolution’ — measuring of sustainable development goals, innovation through big data and new technologies, and addressing system challenges throughout the data landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reiterate, this submission finds the decision of the IEAG to dedicate an entire consultation area to ‘Accessible Data’ most encouraging and praiseworthy. However, it is necessary to simultaneously ensure that the concern for and transformative potential of open data is not contained within one consultation area within, but is discussed and deployed across the various aspects of the ‘data revolution.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-embracing-open-data-in-data-revolution-for-sustainable-development:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2. Embracing Open Data in ‘Data Revolution for Sustainable Development’&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discourse of ‘open data’ have emerged primarily from a ‘developed world’ context, and this has informed the efforts to define the term in terms of legal and technological considerations. The ‘8 Principles of Open Government Data’ prepared by Tim O’Reilly, Carl Malamud and others mention qualities regarding the nature of the published data (‘complete’ and ‘primary’), how it is published (‘timely,’ ‘accessible,’ and ‘machine- processable’), and the legal status of the published data (‘non-discriminatory’, ‘non- proprietary,’ and ‘license-free’) &lt;code&gt;[3]&lt;/code&gt;. The ‘Open Definition,’ largely accepted as a necessary and sufficient definition of ‘open data,’ also approaches ‘open data’ as data without any legal and technological constraints upon how it can be accessed, used, modified, and shared (for any purpose) &lt;code&gt;[4]&lt;/code&gt;. While such emphasis upon legal and technological concerns in defining ‘open data’ is necessary, operationalisation of ‘open data’ in the global development context requires consideration of other principles that may ensure the accountability of the the data production and publication processes, and the effective and transparent usage of the published data. Some of such principles have already emerged in mainstream (‘developed world’) discussion of open data. Such as the ‘7 additional principles’ listed by Tim O’Reilly, Carl Malamud and others that include critical issues like ‘open by default,’ ‘documentation,’ and incorporation of ‘public inputs’ &lt;code&gt;[5]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section highlights several other principles the importance of which have emerged from my own survey of research and advocacy organisations in India and their practices of accessing, using and sharing (open) government data &lt;code&gt;[6]&lt;/code&gt; and various studies undertaken as part of the ‘Exploring the Emerging Impacts of Open Data in Developing Countries’ project of the Open Data Research Network managed by World Wide Web Foundation and supported by International Development Research Centre &lt;code&gt;[7]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-1-openness-in-data-production:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2.1. Openness in Data Production&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.1.1. Open Procedures of Data Collection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– The principle of openness must be implemented from the very beginning of the data lifecycle – from the collection (or production) of data for purposes of sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Open production of data for sustainable development involves implementation of open documentation of data collection methods, prioritisation of free and open source softwares, hardwares and data formats for data collection, as well as ensuring sufficiently detailed description of the categories and assumptions employed in the data collection process. Unless these conditions are satisfied, it will not be possible to subject the collected data to public scrutiny and will undermine accountability of the collected data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.1.2. Openness Regarding Potential Uses of Collected Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Openness in collection of data must also be implemented in terms of explicitly communicating the reason for collection and potential usages of collected data to the individual or collective sources of data (from whom the data is collected). Though not commonly included in understanding of open data, this is an absolutely critical condition in the context of interventions towards global sustainable development. The individual and collective sources of data (to be used for purposes of sustainable development) must be effectively informed of the potential usages of the collected data, as absence of this can fundamentally damage the social trust between citizens and governmental agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.1.3. Openness for Big Data from Social Networks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– The above points are especially crucial when considering web-based social networks as sources of collection of data to be used for informing and measuring actions towards global sustainable development. Openness in the methods, assumptions, software and hardware employed in collection of data, and prior knowledge of the those who created/shared the data regarding its potential usages, must be strictly implemented when collecting data from such networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-2-openness-in-data-publication:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2.2. Openness in Data Publication&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.2.1. Open Data as an Universal Principle for Data Revolution, or ‘Open by Default’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– All data collected and utilised (by public, private, academic, or civic organisations) for purposes of interventions towards global sustainable development must be published as open data. This principle should cover data used both at the international level and also at the national level for such purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– ‘Open by default’ is a necessary (but not sufficient) condition for building trust through ensuring accountability and transparency in the strategies and techniques of ‘data revolution for sustainable development.’ ‘Open by default’ in this context emphasises treatment of the above as universal and ‘normal’ guiding principle for all data relevant to the processes of ensuring global sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Implementing ‘open by default’ for all data collected and utilised for the purpose of informing and/or measuring sustainable development actions will require an expanded understanding of ‘open data,’ possibly augmenting the dominant understanding formulated by Open Definition &lt;code&gt;[8]&lt;/code&gt;. The legal and technological understanding of ‘open data’ needs to be expanded by (1) an understanding of the entire lifecycle of the data concerned, as mentioned above, (2) carefully assessed inclusion of existing practices of accessing, using and re-sharing government data and information that are available publicly or in semi-public networks, (3) responsiveness to different modes of consuming, analysing and acting upon (disaggregated and aggregated) data across regions, sectors, disciplines, etc., and (4) an acknowledgement that ‘openness’ of data is not simply defined by conditions under which it is published, but ‘openness’ must also apply to its various moments of usage and interpretation. Of course, this is not an exhaustive list of concerns but an indicative one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Further, it is crucial to consider globally produced data for the purpose of informing and measuring sustainable development as common resources and not as an asset. This principle highlights the need for making such data available as open data, but also to restrict (and/or regulate) the commercial usage of that data in cases where commercial use may negatively impact one or more sustainable development goals and/or basic human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.2.2. Proactive and Reactive Disclosure of Data and Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Proactive and reactive disclosure of data and information must be treated as essential complements. While, proactive disclosure of data and information is generally categorised as ‘open data’ and reactive disclosure of the same is called ‘right to information’ or ‘freedom of intervention,’ there is a threat in treating either policies of proactive or reactive disclosure as a substitute of the other. Proactive disclosure reduces public efforts in requesting for and gathering data and information on one hand, and reduces administrative efforts in re-sharing to already disclosed data and information on the other. Reactive disclosure ensures publication of such data and information that are most valuable in the context of public interests (including those concerning accountability and transparency of governance). Both the types of policies must be enforced nationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Data and information sharing by government agencies are often governed by a complex and specific (to the national system) sets of policies, acts, rules, and other directives. Policies for proactive and reactive disclosure of data and information, and governance guidelines for national portals to host the disclosed data, should effectively cross-reference all such relevant documents. This is critical for avoiding intra-governmental conflicts in publishing open government data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.2.3. Anonymity as a Strict Condition of Openness of Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Personally identifiable information in an open data set, that is information that can lead to a person (or a family) being identified from a dataset, or easily de-anonymisable open data set has the potential to cause irreversible damage to human security and well-being. Data to be used for the purpose of informing and/or measuring global sustainable development interventions, under no circumstances, should be collected, stored, analysed and shared in a form that either contains personally identifiable information or that allows easy de-anonymisation of the identities of the individuals and families mentioned in the data. It is absolutely critical that this is treated as a fundamental principle of any data under the purview of ‘data revolution for sustainable development.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Further, joining up of various data sets referring to the same population of individuals or families may potentially reveal the real identity(ies) of one or more members of the population. This also poses similar threat as above. To ensure that such triangulation of real identities is not possible by combining multiple data sets, all data sets used within the purview of ‘data revolution for sustainable development’ must necessarily contain only internally-consistent unique identifiers of each individuals or families (to whom the data refer to). In other words, unique identifiers used to represent a particular individual or family in a specific data set, under no circumstances, may refer to the same individual or family in another data set. This principle can be only relaxed in cases where data is collected about the same individual or family at different points of time, and hence consistent unique identifier is needed to generate a temporal analysis of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.2.4. National Open Data Portals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Neither are national open data portals substitutes for open data policies. While introducing an open data portal before a fully-formed (national) open data policy can have its benefits (such as accelerating the publication and usage of open government data), national open data portal cannot be sustained effectively in medium- and long-run without an open data policy to operationalise the portal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– This is of course not to take away focus from the critical need to build public data infrastructures, not only to host open data shared by various government agencies, but also providing common archival support to host open data shared by private, academic and civic organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– For successful implementation of national open data portals it is crucial to understand the deep backend of such a data portal that rests across multiple government agencies and sometime conflicting claims (within government) regarding ownership and control priviledges regarding data. Establishment of a national open data portal, hence, must not be seen as building an additional public-facing (and government-facing) component of government, but as an opportunity to re-configure very processes of management of data across agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– A government-wide incorporation of the notion and practice of open data is needed to ensure success of the national data portals. This requires re-designing the processes of data production and circulation within the government, including re-creating incentive structures towards publication of open, reliable and timely data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– It is fundamental that introduction of open data practices within government is not appropriated as a mechanism of greater surveillance and control of activities of lower levels of bureaucracy by higher levels of bureaucracy. Adoption of open government data means opening up data produced at all levels of government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– A commonly provided reason (by government agencies) for non-publication of government data is either bad quality or bad format of the data. Restructuring of government data practices towards making it more open must emphasise upon publication of all data that is identified as ‘bad quality’ or ‘badly formatted’ by the government agencies. Opening up of such data and establishment of feedback mechanisms are the most effective method to improve their quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Further, for citizens and development professionals to effectively participate in global sustainable development discussions, decision-making, and actions, it is critical that they have access to open government data at the national level, and comparable open data sets at the global level. Also, they must, as required, be provided technological support to publicly host and share (local, regional or other) primary data collected by them to inform the global discussions and actions. Both these tasks can be ably performed by a network of national and international (perhaps sectoral) data portals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.2.5. Creating Spaces for Open Data Intermediaries&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Government-run data portals are not sufficient to reach out to all the potential users of data in the world, nor should they aspire to do so. Open data intermediary organisations – that is organisations that specialise in mediating access, use and re-sharing of open data by other organisations – must be provided space in the national and international strategies of data revolution to augment and amplify the supply of national and international open data, as well as its availability across various media forms – digital and analog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– There is a rich range of organisations across the world that perform this role of mediating access, use, and re-sharing of government data by other organisations. While all such organisations may play productive roles in supporting other organisations and individual to work with open data, it is crucial to ensure that these intermediary organisations does not stop the flow (that is, re-sharing) of open data in the process of offering value-added services around open data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– In creating institutional support and partnerships between government and open data intermediary organisations, special support and capacity building processes must be employed to ensure that organisations that have been working with government data for long are able to preserve and build on their expertise as data-driven policy discussions and decision-making shift from paper-based to web-based media .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-3-openness-in-data-usage:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2.3. Openness in Data Usage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.3.1. Openness in Usage of Data for Global Sustainable Development&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Creating global trust through accountability and transparency of data-driven processes of measuring development indicators, and of designing and monitoring development interventions require open documentation of these processes and availability of open data that are used to drive them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Any data used for taking local, regional, national, and global development decisions must be open data, that is it must be available for public scrutiny. This is a necessary principle for ensuring accountability of ‘data revolution.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Following the examples of data bank maintained by United Nations, World Bank, and other international agencies, the Sustainable Development Goal monitoring agency should create an online data archive to host disaggregated (as opposed to ‘country-level averages’) data utilised in the processes of measuring Sustainable Development Goals indicators, and informing and monitoring relevant development interventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.3.2. Opening up Public Participation in Data Discussions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– To ensure a truly broad-based revolution in the use of data for understanding and acting upon development needs, it is necessary to reach out to various communities working with data and information in the contexts of public accountability, sustainable development, human and community rights, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– While the ‘data revolution’ and also the ‘open data’ agenda focus on an imaginary of data as digital, numerical and disaggregated, it is crucial to keep in mind the multiplicity of forms in which data is accessed, used, shared and acted upon by individual citizens and various collectives. The data revolution will be truly successful if it empowers and mobilises all such circulations and usages of data, towards achieving global sustainable development. Openness of data is crucial step in enabling that, but is must be supported through public consultation processes of various kinds — from requesting inputs for technical design (of semantic standards, technical standards, data portal architectures, etc.) decisions, to educating individuals and various groups in effectively accessing, using and re-sharing data and information to ensure public accountability and informed development interventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Further and in reference to earlier discussion of ‘open procedures of data collection’ (#2.1.1.), to ensure effective use of open data by various individuals and collectives, it is critical to involve them from the very beginning of the data lifecycle, that is from its collection. Various forms of analysis and uses of the data require it to be available not only in specific forms (say, CSV or XML) but also the data structure to have specific qualities (say, inclusion of geo-referencing of each unit source of data). Such usage requirements are best resolved by involving actors at an early stage of conceptualising the structure of data to be collected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Effective usage of open data for purposes of development not only requires ‘data literacy’ but also enabling institutional contexts and civic skills and capacities to take advantage of such institutional contexts. The success of the ‘data revolution for sustainable development,’ hence, depends not only on systematic production of global, reliable and timely data on topics of sustainable development, and open publication of such data to enable public, private, academic and civic agencies to participate in the global development discussion, but also on the commitment of the governments to engage in and respond to data-driven discussion and decision-making processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.3.3. Opening Up Political Representation and Claim-Making through Use of Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– The previous point envisages the ‘data revolution for sustainable development’ promoting data-driven discussions and decision-making regarding global interventions towards sustainable development. This is of course not to suggest that all global sustainable development related discussions and decisions should solely be taken on the basis of available data. What is measured and what is not measured is a political decision to begin with, and often not all members of the population have equal abilities or priviledges to be included or represented within the collected data. One of the key barriers faced by disadvantaged groups globally while accessing welfare services is the need to belong to a government and/or official data set that determines one’s status as a beneficiary or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Thus, it is crucial for a successful ‘data revolution’ to faciliatate empowerment of individuals and communities to use not only existing open data, but also to use (locally and globally accepted) methods and techniques of creating open data to enter processes of claim making and of accessing welfare services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– To reiterate, it is absolutely crucial that lack of ability, capacity, resources, or priviledges to represent oneself in data terms, or in terms acceptable to the data-driven mechanisms of global sustainable development interventions, does not prevent any individual or collective from accessing the benefits of global sustainable development or from bettering one’s human wellbeing. In other words, while the ‘data revolution’ initiates struggles to bring down ‘data divides’ &lt;code&gt;[9]&lt;/code&gt; and the various other ‘divides’ that it is determined by (and determine back), in the meantime it must not allow individual and collective to be denied of development interventions and welfare services for their lack of capability to use and belong to datasets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.3.4. Essential Question – Who is Empowered by Using (Opened Up) Data?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– An essential governing question while taking decisions regarding conceptualisation and operationalisation of the ‘data revolution for sustainable development’ is who is empowered by collection and opening up of the specific data concerned? The ‘data revolution for sustainable development’ framework may mandate collection, archival, usage, and open sharing of only such data about human, infrastructural and ecological conditions that when used will lead to empowerment of people towards greater and sustainable wellbeing. This is a fundamental principle for two reasons – (1) falling costs of collection and archival of data at a global scale creates a strong attraction towards gathering of as much data as possible without specific objectives for their collection, and (2) availability of open data regarding human wellbeing conditions at a global scale has massive commercial value, unlocking of which may not necessarily lead to positive impacts in terms of global sustainable development goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Strict adherence to the notion of ‘open data’ as data that can be accessed, used, modified, and shared for any purpose need to be re-considered especially in the context of global sustainable development. The emphasis on any purpose specifically ensures the legal possibility of commercial use of the data concerned. While any re-consideration of the any purpose principle must allow for commercial activities such development experts undertaking analysis of published data (that is, commercial creation of data derivatives), but usage of such data for commercial decision making purposes (such as, differential rates for agricultural loans using environmental data) can be regulated. One possible legal instrument for ensuring open data use in public interest is the requirement that open data collected and published for the purpose of sustainable development can only be combined with data itself published as open data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-references:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;3. References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[1]&lt;/code&gt; High Level Panel – The Post 2015 Development Agenda. 2013. Retrieved October 14, 2014, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post2015hlp.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.post2015hlp.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[2]&lt;/code&gt; High Level Panel on the Post-2015 Development Agenda. 2013. What is Data Revolution? Retrieved October 14, 2014, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post2015hlp.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/What-is-the-Data-Revolution.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.post2015hlp.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/What-is-the-Data-Revolution.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[3]&lt;/code&gt; The Annotated 8 Principles of Open Government Data. 2013. Retrieved on October 14, 2014, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://opengovdata.org/&#34;&gt;http://opengovdata.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[4]&lt;/code&gt; Open Definition. Retrieved on October 14, 2014, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://opendefinition.org/&#34;&gt;http://opendefinition.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[5]&lt;/code&gt; See &lt;code&gt;[3]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[6]&lt;/code&gt; Chattapadhyay, Sumandro. 2014. Opening Government Data through Mediation: Exploring Roles, Practices and Strategies of (Potential) Data Intermediary Organisations in India. Retrieved on October 14, 2014, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/&#34;&gt;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[7]&lt;/code&gt; Open Data Research Network. Retrieved on October 14, 2014, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://opendataresearch.org/&#34;&gt;http://opendataresearch.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[8]&lt;/code&gt; See &lt;code&gt;[4]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[9]&lt;/code&gt; Gurstein, Michael. 2011. A Data Divide? Data “Haves” and “Have Nots” and Open (Government) Data. July 11. Retrieved on October 15, 2014, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://gurstein.wordpress.com/2011/07/11/a-data-divide-data-%E2%80%9Chaves%E2%80%9D-and-%E2%80%9Chave-nots%E2%80%9D-and-open-government-data/&#34;&gt;http://gurstein.wordpress.com/2011/07/11/a-data-divide-data-%E2%80%9Chaves%E2%80%9D-and-%E2%80%9Chave-nots%E2%80%9D-and-open-government-data/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-profiles:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;4. Profiles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sumandro Chattapadhyay&lt;/strong&gt; is a Research Associate with The Sarai Programme at the Centre for the Study of Developing Societies, New Delhi, India. His academic interests include history and politics of informatics in post-independence India, science and technology studies, and political economy. He is associated with DataMeet, an organisation of open data and data science enthusiasts from India, and Open Data Research Network, a community of researchers from ‘developing countries’ working on themes related to open data. He also frequently works with the Centre for Internet and Society, Bangalore, India. Website: &lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.net/&#34;&gt;ajantriks.net&lt;/a&gt;. E-mail: mail[at]ajantriks[dot]net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tim Davies&lt;/strong&gt; is coordinator of the Open Data Research Network for the World Wide Web Foundation, and is a PhD Candidate the University of Southampton focussing on the democratic dimensions of open data policy. Websites: &lt;a href=&#34;http://webfoundation.org/&#34;&gt;http://webfoundation.org/&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.opendataresearch.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.opendataresearch.org/&lt;/a&gt;. E-mail: timdavies[at]webfoundation[dot]org.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zacharia Chiliswa&lt;/strong&gt; is the programmes Manager at Jesuit Hakimani Centre responsible for coordinating and supporting implementation of JHC programmes and projects. His areas of interest are communication for development, open governance and public policy. Website: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jesuithakimani.net/&#34;&gt;http://www.jesuithakimani.net/&lt;/a&gt;. E-mail: zchiliswa[at]yahoo[dot]com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gisele da Silva Craveiro&lt;/strong&gt; is a Computer Science Bachelor, has Master degree in Computer Science and PhD in Computer Systems. Since 2005 is University of São Paulo assistant professor. Coordinates the research group Colaboratory of Development and Participation (Colab-USP). She is also in the Open Government Partnership Latin American Civil Society advisor committee. She is Open Knowledge Brazil board chairwoman. Her national and international projects and publications are focused in open budget, ranging from government transparency portals analysis, data extraction, standardization of budgetary data disclosure on the web, civic application development and open data initiatives impact research. E-mail: giselesc[at]usp[dot]br.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The note is authored by Sumandro Chattapadhyay and is shared under Creative Commons &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20150401221441/http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&#34;&gt;Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International&lt;/a&gt; license. In this note, the author does not claim to represent any of the organisations and networks he is associated with. The articulated agenda is his own, and it includes ideas shared by the three contributors — Tim Davies, Zacharia Chiliswa, and Giselse Craveiro. The author takes full responsibility for reworking and rephrasing the ideas of the contributors into the note.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Revolution for Sustainable Development - Readings</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/data-revolution-for-sustainable-development-readings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2014 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/data-revolution-for-sustainable-development-readings/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;With the policy period of the Millennium Development Goals (MDGs) coming to an end in 2015, United Nations instituted a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post2015hlp.org/&#34;&gt;High Level Panel&lt;/a&gt; to advise on the framing of the discussion on post-2015 global development framework and the design of the Sustainable Development Goals. The Panel submitted its &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post2015hlp.org/the-report/&#34;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; in May 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report highlights &lt;a href=&#34;http://report.post2015hlp.org/five-transformative-shifts.html&#34;&gt;five transformative shifts&lt;/a&gt; as core foci of the post-2015 development agenda, and identifies &amp;lsquo;data revolution&amp;rsquo; as a necessary and fundamental component of operationalising such an agenda. This identification is directly compelled by the experiences of measuring, monitoring and implement the MDGs. To quote from a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post2015hlp.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/What-is-the-Data-Revolution.pdf%22&#34;&gt;brief note on &amp;lsquo;data revolution&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt; published by the Panel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, the availability quality and accessibility of the data we have today just aren’t good enough. Too often, development efforts are hampered by a lack of the most basic data about the social and economic circumstances in which people live. This requires a commitment to changing the way we collect and share data, both from the bottom up and the top down&amp;hellip; The availability of information has improved during the implementation of the MDGs, but much better data are necessary. We have yet to establish an accurate picture of how many people are living in extreme poverty today; without that, it is very hard to work out the best ways to move that number to zero by 2030.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the challenge of absent and unreliable of global development data is a very critical one, the question here is if &amp;lsquo;data revolution&amp;rsquo; is being conceptualised robustly enough to address it. The same note explains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its heart, the data revolution comprises two main objectives: 1) the integration of statistics into public and private sector decision making; 2) building trust between society and state through transparency and accountability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The note lists nine strategic interventions required to achieve these objectives. Only one of which, however, addresses the second &lt;em&gt;main&lt;/em&gt; objective of building trust through transparency and accountability. Five interventions focus on resource moblisation, infrastructural development, and capacity building to upgrade national statistical systems, so as to generate reliable and timely data at national scale, as well as to extract data through new technological apparatuses such as social media networks, and national identity card systems. Two strategies highlight the need to engage public and private sector leaders to implement cross-sector transparency initiatives and sharing of open data and information. One strategy calls for a fresh round of collection of baseline data on development (by 2016) to inform the monitoring of post-2015 development goals. And only a single strategy focuses on the need to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create space for civil society to ensure these promises are fulfilled, and especially that we ‘Leave No One Behind’ and that the rights of marginalized groups are ensured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prepare recommendations for strategies towards a &amp;lsquo;data revolution in sustainable development,&amp;rsquo; UN has established an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.undatarevolution.org/&#34;&gt;Independent Expert Advisory Group&lt;/a&gt;. The Group formed on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.undatarevolution.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/PR-Announcement_Secretary-Generals-Independent-Expert-Advisory-Group-on-Data-Revolution.pdf&#34;&gt;August 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and is currently seeking submissions from the public, and is expected to present its final report by the end of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is set of background readings to inform engagements with the idea of &amp;lsquo;data revolution&amp;rsquo; and what can be its location within the post-2015 development agenda. Comments and suggestions of absent essential readings are very much welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-revolution-introduction:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Data Revolution - Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High Level Panel on the Post-2015 Development Agenda , UN - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post2015hlp.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/What-is-the-Data-Revolution.pdf&#34;&gt;What is the Data Revolution?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Johannes Jütting, Manager, PARIS21 Secretariat - &lt;a href=&#34;http://post2015.org/2014/08/14/data-revolution-in-development-countries-come-first/&#34;&gt;Data Revolution in Development: Countries Come First!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Claire Melamed - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/global-development/poverty-matters/2014/jan/31/data-development-reliable-figures-numbers&#34;&gt;Development Data: How Accurate are the Figures?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-revolution-national-statistical-systems:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Data Revolution - National Statistical Systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PARIS21 - &lt;a href=&#34;http://paris21.org/NSDS&#34;&gt;National Strategies for the Development of Statistics (NSDS)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;African Union - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.au.int/en/sites/default/files/AFRICAN_CHARTER_ON_STATISTICS.pdf&#34;&gt;African Charter on Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OECD - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oecd.org/dac/POST-2015%20P21.pdf&#34;&gt;Strengthening National Statistical Systems to Monitor Global Goals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-realise-the-data-revolution:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;How to Realise the Data Revolution?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morten Jerven - &lt;a href=&#34;http://post2015.org/2013/11/05/new-blog-series-what-kind-of-data-revolution-do-we-need-for-post-2015/&#34;&gt;What Kind of Data Revolution do We Need?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centre for Global Development and The African Population and Health Research Centre - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cgdev.org/sites/default/files/CGD14-01%20complete%20for%20web%200710.pdf&#34;&gt;Delivering on the Data Revolution in Sub-Saharan Africa: Final Report of the Data for African Development Working Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open Data Institute, Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation, DFID, Development Initiatives, ONE, Paris21, UNDP, USAID and World Bank - &lt;a href=&#34;http://post2015.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/data-revolution-expert-workshop-outcome-document1.pdf&#34;&gt;Towards a Strategy for the Data Revolution: Outcomes from the July 11–12 Experts’ Workshop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-revolution-and-big-data:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Data Revolution and Big Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UN Global Pulse - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unglobalpulse.org/sites/default/files/BigDataforDevelopment-UNGlobalPulseJune2012.pdf&#34;&gt;Big Data for Development: Challenge and Opportunities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emmanuel Letouzé - &lt;a href=&#34;http://post2015.org/2014/04/01/the-big-data-revolution-should-be-about-knowledge-security/&#34;&gt;The Big Data Revolution should be about Knowledge Security&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bellagio Big Data Workshop - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rockefellerfoundation.org/uploads/files/c220f1f3-2e9a-4fc6-be6c-45d42849b897-big-data-and.pdf&#34;&gt;Big Data and Positive Social Change in the Developing World: A White Paper for Practitioners and Researchers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-disclosure-privacy:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Data, Disclosure, Privacy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vijay Pandurangan - &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@vijayp/of-taxis-and-rainbows-f6bc289679a1&#34;&gt;On Taxis and Rainbows: Lessons from NYC’s Improperly Anonymized Taxi Logs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arvind Narayanan and Edward W. Felten - &lt;a href=&#34;http://randomwalker.info/publications/no-silver-bullet-de-identification.pdf&#34;&gt;No Silver Bullet: De-Identification Still doesn&amp;rsquo;t Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Executive Office of the President, Government of USA - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/docs/big_data_privacy_report_5.1.14_final_print.pdf&#34;&gt;Big Data: Seizing Opportunities, Preserving Values&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-information-transparency:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Data, Information, Transparency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aruna Roy and Nikhil Dey, MKSS Rajasthan - &lt;a href=&#34;http://ibsa.cgg.gov.in/Articles/1.pdf&#34;&gt;The Right to Information: Facilitating People’s Participation and State Accountability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publish What You Fund - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.publishwhatyoufund.org/files/2010/05/BP1_Why-Aid-Transparency-Matters_FINAL.pdf&#34;&gt;Why Aid Transparency Matters, and the Global Movement for Aid Transparency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Access Info Europe and Open Knowledge Foundation - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.access-info.org/documents/Access_Docs/Advancing/Beyond_Access_7_January_2011_web.pdf&#34;&gt;Beyond Access: Open Government Data and the Right to (Re)use Public Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-data-introduction:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Data - Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim G. Davies and Zainab Ashraf Bawa - &lt;a href=&#34;http://ci-journal.net/index.php/ciej/article/view/929/955&#34;&gt;The Promises and Perils of Open Government Data (OGD)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harlan Yu and David G. Robinson - &lt;a href=&#34;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2012489&#34;&gt;The New Ambiguity of &amp;lsquo;Open Government&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Gurstein - &lt;a href=&#34;http://gurstein.wordpress.com/2011/07/11/a-data-divide-data-%E2%80%9Chaves%E2%80%9D-and-%E2%80%9Chave-nots%E2%80%9D-and-open-government-data/&#34;&gt;A Data Divide? Data ‘Haves’ and ‘Have Nots’ and Open (Government) Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-data-principles-and-definition:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Data - Principles and Definition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim O&amp;rsquo;Reilly, Carl Malamud and others - &lt;a href=&#34;http://opengovdata.org/&#34;&gt;The Annotated 8 Principles of Open Government Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open Data Handbook - &lt;a href=&#34;http://opendatahandbook.org/en/what-is-open-data/index.html&#34;&gt;What is Open Data?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rufus Pollock - &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.okfn.org/2014/09/30/why-the-open-definition-matters-for-open-data-quality-compatibility-and-simplicity/&#34;&gt;Why the Open Definition Matters for Open Data: Quality, Compatibility and Simplicity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-government-data-declarations-and-policies:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Government Data - Declarations and Policies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Executive Office of the President, Government of USA - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/omb/memoranda/2013/m-13-13.pdf&#34;&gt;Open Data Policy - Managing Information as an Asset&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;European Commission - &lt;a href=&#34;http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=COM:2011:0882:FIN:EN:PDF&#34;&gt;Open Data: An Engine for Innovation, Growth and Transparent Governance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministry of Science and Technology, Government of India - &lt;a href=&#34;http://data.gov.in/sites/default/files/NDSAP.pdf&#34;&gt;National Data Sharing and Accessibility Policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-government-data-implementation-guidelines:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Government Data - Implementation Guidelines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centre for Technology in Government, University of Albany - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ctg.albany.edu/publications/reports/opendata&#34;&gt;The Dynamics of Opening Government Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UNESCO - &lt;a href=&#34;http://fas.org/sgp/library/unesco_govinfo.pdf&#34;&gt;Policy Guidelines for the Development and Promotion of Governmental Public Sector Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephan Shakespeare and others - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/198752/13-744-shakespeare-review-of-public-sector-information.pdf&#34;&gt;Shakespeare Review - An Independent Review of Public Sector Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-government-data-global-surveys:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Government Data - Global Surveys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open Knowledge Foundation - &lt;a href=&#34;http://global.census.okfn.org/&#34;&gt;Global Open Data Index&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;World Wide Web Foundation - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.opendataresearch.org/project/2013/odb&#34;&gt;Open Data Barometer 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southern Voice and others - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post2015datatest.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/Post2015-Data-Test-Methodology-Guide.pdf&#34;&gt;The Post-2015 Data Test: Country Level Experiences - Methodology and Implementation Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-government-data-regional-surveys:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Government Data - Regional Surveys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Becky Hogge, Transparency and Accountability Initiative - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.transparency-initiative.org/reports/open-data-study-new-technologies&#34;&gt;Open Data Study – New Technologies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara Ubaldi, OECD - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oecd-ilibrary.org/governance/open-government-data_5k46bj4f03s7-en&#34;&gt;Open Government Data: Towards Empirical Analysis of Open Government Data Initiatives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waltraut Ritter, Knowledge Dialogues - &lt;a href=&#34;http://knowledgedialogues.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/open-data-asia-09-2014.pdf&#34;&gt;Open Data in Asia: An Overview of Open Data Policies and Practices in 13 Countries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-data-selected-sectoral-portals:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Data - Selected Sectoral Portals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://opencorporates.com/&#34;&gt;Open Corporates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://aiddata.org/&#34;&gt;AidData - Open Data for International Development&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://landmatrix.org/en/&#34;&gt;Land Matrix - The Online Public Database on Land Deals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-data-supply-and-implementation:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Data - Supply and Implementation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UN Public Administration Programme - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unpan.org/DPADM/EGovernment/OpenGovernmentDataandServices/tabid/1536/language/en-US/Default.aspx&#34;&gt;Guidelines on Open Government Data for Citizen Engagement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Robinson, Harlan Yu,William P. Zeller and Edward W.Felten - &lt;a href=&#34;http://yjolt.org/sites/default/files/robinson-11-YJOLT-.pdf&#34;&gt;Government Data and the Invisible Hand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marijn Janssen, Yannis Charalabidis &amp;amp; Anneke Zuiderwijk - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.academia.edu/2852526/Benefits_Adoption_Barriers_and_Myths_of_Open_Data_and_Open_Government&#34;&gt;Benefits, Adoption Barriers and Myths of Open Data and Open Government&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-data-political-economy:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Data - Political Economy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Manyika and others, McKinsey Global Institute - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mckinsey.com/insights/business_technology/open_data_unlocking_innovation_and_performance_with_liquid_information&#34;&gt;Open Data: Unlocking Innovation and Performance with Liquid Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jo Bates - &lt;a href=&#34;http://ci-journal.net/index.php/ciej/article/view/845/916&#34;&gt;‘This is what modern deregulation looks like’: Co-optation and Contestation in the Shaping of the UK&amp;rsquo;s Open Government Data Initiative&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Governance Lab, New York University - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.opendata500.com/&#34;&gt;The Open Data 500&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-data-technological-concerns:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Data - Technological Concerns&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim Berners-Lee - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/LinkedData.html&#34;&gt;Linked Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timothy G. Davies and Mark Frank - &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.soton.ac.uk/352115/&#34;&gt;There’s no such thing as raw data:’ Exploring the Socio-Technical Life of a Government Dataset&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Civicus - &lt;a href=&#34;http://civicus.org/thedatashift/background/&#34;&gt;The Big Development DataShift&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-data-critiques:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Data - Critiques&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Gurstein - &lt;a href=&#34;http://firstmonday.org/article/view/3316/2764&#34;&gt;Open Data: Empowering the Empowered or Effective Data Use for Everyone?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tom Slee - &lt;a href=&#34;http://crookedtimber.org/2012/06/25/seeing-like-a-geek/&#34;&gt;Seeing Like a Geek&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rob Kitchin - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.maynoothuniversity.ie/progcity/2013/11/four-critiques-of-open-data-initiatives/&#34;&gt;Four Critiques of Open Data Initiatives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-algorithm-governance:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Data, Algorithm, Governance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evgeny Morozov - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/technology/2014/jul/20/rise-of-data-death-of-politics-evgeny-morozov-algorithmic-regulation&#34;&gt;The Rise of Data and the Death of Politics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Eaves - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/future_tense/2012/09/open_data_movement_how_to_keep_information_from_being_politicized_.single.html&#34;&gt;Lies, Damned Lies, and Open Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Alan Johnson - &lt;a href=&#34;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10676-014-9351-8&#34;&gt;From Open Data to Information Justice&lt;/a&gt; [Behind paywall]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>These Cities are Made for Watchin’</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/these-cities-are-made-for-watchin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2014 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/these-cities-are-made-for-watchin/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;published-by-the-pop-up-city-http-popupcity-net-these-cities-are-made-for-watchin:c16d05bacacc488815d5e3e5fdb66283&#34;&gt;Published by &lt;a href=&#34;http://popupcity.net/these-cities-are-made-for-watchin/&#34;&gt;The Pop Up City&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/Watch-Dogs.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Codes&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ubisoft.com/de-DE/game/watch-dogs/&#34;&gt;Watch Dogs&lt;/a&gt;, by Ubisoft, has finally come out. In this game, you play an urban hacker in Chicago, who can hack into the operating system of the city and turn the very built environment into a weapon. We have talked about the game &lt;a href=&#34;http://popupcity.net/data-driven-urban-citizenship/&#34;&gt;earlier&lt;/a&gt; in the context of how data-driven urban infrastructures create new possibilities of looking at the city and acting in it — for governments, citizens and hackers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the advertisement campaign for the game, Devin Graham has directed a short action sequence that brings together parkour running and urban hacking. This amazing clip shows how we inhabit the city both physically and informationally — and can hack it by going beyond the designed circuits of physical movement, and access to information and data-driven control systems. 
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/UIkkiyGKfA0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such concerns about the collapsing of physical and or informational dimensions of the city is not something that begins with the integration of computers into urban infrastructure. One of the greatest explorations of this topic can be found in Gillo Pontecorvo’s ‘&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Battle_of_Algiers&#34;&gt;The Battle of Algiers&lt;/a&gt;.’ The film narrates the incidents of urban guerilla warfare in Algiers during the Algerian War of 1954-62. Throughout the film, the physicality and the knowledge about the urban spaces of Algiers — divided into the ‘modern’ French town and the ‘native’ city of casbah — is the very object and site of struggle for control of the city. Throughout the film, it is crucial for the French police and military to dominate urban mobility by gaining information about identities, intentions and locations of the Algerians. Converesely, the Algerian guerilla hides their existence not only through physical means (dresses and wells) but also through their knowledge of the alleys of casbah. Interestingly, one of the most iconic sequence of the film is of a boy hijacking a microphone system at a city checkpost and using it to announce pro-Algeria messages. 
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/ToFw7zqJ_sc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tom Brewster raises the obvious question of whether increasing integration of software and software-controlled hardware into the body of cities is making it more &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/cities/2014/may/21/smart-cities-future-stupid-hack-terrorism-watchdogs&#34;&gt;vulnerable&lt;/a&gt; to cyber-attacks. Last year, Kashmir Hill, senior online editor at Forbes, demonstrated how common security-lapses can allow strangers to gain &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.forbes.com/sites/kashmirhill/2013/07/26/smart-homes-hack/#6013508f46a5&#34;&gt;control over ‘smart home’ devices&lt;/a&gt; via internet. Brewster further shows how these vulenerabilities of smart systems may not only come from mistakes while deploying or configuring them, but can simply be caused by &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/message/everything-is-broken-81e5f33a24e1#.ixgu30qhv&#34;&gt;sloppy code&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To prove the point, a researcher from security consultancy IOActive recently showed that vulnerabilities in road sensors relaying information to traffic lights could be exploited to turn them from red to green, or keep them on a certain colour. The potential impact is all too obvious: traffic carnage and deadly accidents… Many of the weaknesses are basic, [Cesar Cerrudo] says: devices often don’t do adequate validation of the data being sent to them, failing to check whether malicious streams of information are being sent rather than legitimate bits and bytes determining their functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a pattern here: Watch Dogs imagines a smart city that is under control of ‘corrupt officials’ and ‘elite hackers;’ Hill talks about errors commited by uses that expose smart devices; and Brewster reveals how internal shortcomings of smart systems may lead to real-world disasters. In all these narratives, something needs to go wrong — either the people running the smart city, the people deploying the smart systems, or the software running the smart systems — for the smart city to hit a 404 page (or worse). 
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/1hpU_Neg1KA&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an imagination of the ‘threat’ of smart cities completely ignores the physical and informational surveillance that will be undertaken as &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;/em&gt; everyday life in a smart city. Data coming out of such surveillance devices will of course be consumed and acted upon by machines and humans alike — as Edward Snowden’s revealations have shown. Further, this entire surveillance will often take place without the residents noticing or giving attention to. Neither the governments nor the corporates, the key controllers of such smart city utilities, have much reputation when it comes to respecting electronic privacy of people, or sensitising the users to seriously consider terms of data usage before using a product/service. The big threat of smart cities does not come from malfunctioning or abuse of those systems, but from their normal usages. These are cities made for watching, and they don’t necessarily come with in-built mechanisms for citizens to watch the watchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Courtesy: Thank to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ehooge/status/469511898334261249&#34;&gt;Emile Hooge&lt;/a&gt; for the Watch Dogs parkour video link.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Of Identity, Platform, and &#39;New&#39; Information Infrastructure of Governance: Situating the Aadhaar Project within the History of Electronic Governance in India</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/situating-the-aadhaar-project-within-the-history-of-electronic-governance-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2013 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/situating-the-aadhaar-project-within-the-history-of-electronic-governance-in-india/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I presented this paper at &lt;a href=&#34;http://sarai.net/social-and-cultural-life-of-information/&#34;&gt;The Social and Cultural Life of Information workshop&lt;/a&gt; organised by the Sarai Programme, CSDS, on November 14-16, 2013. “It brought together a select group of media scholars, historians, anthropologists and geographers for an intensive two day workshop, and aimed at bringing together research on colonial and postcolonial information infrastructures, with a strong South Asian component.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;excerpt:4b3345dd999e8171226a4ff304e711cf&#34;&gt;Excerpt&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper is about a &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; technology of addressing the population, the Aadhaar project, that is under construction in India. Like all (self-declared) &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; technologies, it involves a continued engagement and negotiations with of older technological infrastructures and practices. In this paper, I critically examine the claim of newness by the Aadhaar project, and argue that this newness is to be found in the information infrastructure of governance that the Aadhaar project envisions and promotes, as opposed to the demographic and biometric data it gathers. Brian Larkin brings forward another crucial aspect of the techniques and technologies of addressing. He reminds us that addressing may not necessarily involve a pre-existing object, or an object existing independent of the act of addressing at all. Addressing can be employed to create a semblance of systemic integrity, by referring &amp;ldquo;to the material qualities of the signifier itself rather than to its referential meaning&amp;rdquo; &lt;code&gt;(Larkin 2013: 334)&lt;/code&gt;. It is the army of ghost beneficiaries of welfare-services populating the existing databases of ‘target populations&amp;rsquo; across government departments that the Aadhaar project aims to exorcise in its attempt to re-address the nation, by making them addressable through unique identification numbers with verifiable authenticity (one-to-one correspondence between a number and the resident it refers to)&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explaining the narrower idea of &amp;ldquo;information infrastructure,&amp;rdquo; Geoffrey Bowker et al employ a stricter concept of ‘infrastructure&amp;rsquo; – defined as &amp;ldquo;pervasive enabling resources in network form&amp;rdquo; &lt;code&gt;(Bowker et al 2010: 98)&lt;/code&gt;. The twin emphasis on the network form and its pervasiveness foreground the question of scale threshold of infrastructure. In a crucial intervention, Bowker et al argue for moving the understanding of infrastructure away from something that is in the background, transparent, already-existing and hence can only be studied by its inversion, or in the moment of its breakdown. They approach infrastructure as &amp;ldquo;a fundamentally relational concept,&amp;rdquo; that is in terms of its relationships with other artifacts and processes, specific substantial qualities and spatio-temporal structures of such relationships, relative visibilities of the infrastructure vis-a-vis the other artifacts, and especially the scale and depth of socio-political and organisational interaction, resistance, debate and reconfiguration it generates &lt;code&gt;(Ibid. 99)&lt;/code&gt;. Further, Bowker et al re-introduce the term ‘infrastructural inversion&amp;rsquo; and define it as &amp;ldquo;shifting the emphasis from changes in infrastructural components to changes in infrastructural relations.&amp;rdquo; In his earlier work, Bowker describes the idea of &amp;ldquo;infrastructural inversion&amp;rdquo; as a strategy for foregrounding how technological intervention is not merely about application of scientific or technological reason but substantially involves a strategy of organisation, of assemblage, that is &amp;ldquo;applied simultaneously to the social and natural worlds so as to make them converge&amp;rdquo; &lt;code&gt;(Bowker 1994: 104)&lt;/code&gt;. In this paper, I find his later formulation of the concept through ‘infrastructural components&amp;rsquo; and ‘infrastructural relations&amp;rsquo; – almost as an analogy to the ‘means of production&amp;rsquo; and ‘relations of production&amp;rsquo; – most useful. In this paper I employ the same strategy to read the infrastructural propositions of the Aadhaar project,  and to focus not on the content of the generated unique identity number or the biopolitical economy of their production, but on the relational implications of the project for the national information infrastructure of electronic governance&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taha Mehmood begins an extensive survey of the ‘contested history of National Identity Card in India&amp;rsquo; with the Kargil War of 1999 and the subsequent report of the Kargil Review Committee &lt;code&gt;(Mehmood 2008)&lt;/code&gt;. The executive summary of the report was presented to the members of the Upper House of Parliament on February 25, 2000, and was published later after selective deletion of information (in the interest of national security). Among other recommendations about military, intelligence and general administration in border areas, the report suggested that &amp;ldquo;steps should be taken to issue ID Cards to border villagers in certain vulnerable areas on a priority basis,  pending its extension to other or all parts of the State [of Jammu and Kashmir]&amp;rdquo; &lt;code&gt;(National Security Council Secretariat 1999: 263)&lt;/code&gt;. While, committees and reports that immediately followed this report did not highlight the need for a National Identity Card, the same demand came back in the aftermath of the attack on the Indian Parliament on December 13, 2001. The spatial short circuiting caused by the site of ‘intrusion&amp;rsquo; shifting rapidly from the frontier territory of mountain peaks of Kashmir to the symbolic heart of the nation in New Delhi, perhaps shaped the public acceptance of border securitisation technologies, like unique identity cards embedded with biometric details, as applicable to the entire span of the country. The demand for such a card was eventually shaped into a national project titled Multi-Purpose National Identity Card (MNIC), later categorised as one of the Central Mission Mode Projects of the National E-Governance Plan &lt;code&gt;(Mehmood 2008, DeitY 2011)&lt;/code&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phrase &amp;ldquo;unique identification,&amp;rdquo; however, did not originate with the post-Kargil war security analysis and recommendations. It possibly first appeared in the Long Term National IT Policy report of the National Task Force on Information Technology and Software Development &lt;code&gt;(NTFoITaSD 1999)&lt;/code&gt;, published in April 1999, barely a few months before the war. The report recommended that &amp;ldquo;[i]n the long run citizens must have unique identification Cards – the Citizen ID&amp;hellip; A smart card citizen ID with multi-functions [should] also be launched. The private sector will be actively associated by ensuring a business angle in the project* &lt;code&gt;(Ibid. #70)&lt;/code&gt;. Both these terms &amp;ldquo;unique identification&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;citizen ID&amp;rdquo; are also used by Nandan Nilekani when within a month of the declaration by the Empowered Group of Ministers regarding the making of the UIDAI, he wrote on how a &amp;ldquo;single citizen ID&amp;rdquo; can get rid of the phantoms that haunt the welfare delivery systems in India &lt;code&gt;(Nilekani 2008)&lt;/code&gt;. In the same article, Nilekani provided an early road map of the approach of the Aadhaar project. He referred to Arvind Virmani&amp;rsquo;s efforts to initiate implementation of MASCs and critiqued the (then) ongoing folly of identifying the &amp;ldquo;issuing [of] smart cards as the main challenge of implementing such a system,&amp;rdquo; whereas &amp;ldquo;[i]t is in making the back-end infrastructure secure and scalable, providing a single record keeper for the whole country and integrating the agents who issue these numbers that it gets tough&amp;rdquo; (Ibid.). This position of Nilekani has defined the problem statement of the Aadhaar project since. The philosophical and practical problem that the Aadhaar project tries to solve is that of representing a person using a number, where the one-to-one correspondence between the person and the number can be repeatedly verified. Unlike the problem statement, the solution, however, is not inspiring. While the Aadhaar number itself is an arbitrarily assigned or random number, that is it does not have any causal relation to the information shared by the person (or the Aadhaar number holder) during the act of enrollment, once mapped to a person or to the set of (demographic and bodily/biometric) information shared by the person, the relationship between this otherwise-arbitrary number and the person it signifies (in the Aadhaar database) can only be ‘authenticated&amp;rsquo; if the person is able to produce the same piece (or combination of pieces) of bodily/biometric information provided at the beginning. This creates a bizarre burden upon the person concerned to maintain a certain (selective) bodily integrity, to sustain the authenticity of the relationship with an arbitrary number&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CIDR rests at the centre of the information infrastructure imagined and under deployment by the Aadhaar project &lt;code&gt;(UIDAI 2010a: 10-13)&lt;/code&gt;. On one hand, it is the centralised (not in a physical sense but in an architectural sense) repository of all the assigned Aadhaar numbers along with the corresponding demographic (name, date of birth, sex, family details, and residential address), biometric (photograph of face, and scans of both iris and all fingers), and additional information (e-mail address, mobile number, bank account number to be linked with the Aadhaar number, etc.) collected during the &amp;ldquo;enrollment&amp;rdquo; process; and against which database the de-duplication exercise takes place when a new bundle of demographic and biographic data enter the Aadhaar system for assignment of an Aadhaar number. On the other, it receives the electronically shared information by the Aadhaar number holder for ‘authentication&amp;rsquo; of the one-to-one correspondence between the number and its holder, and sends the verification result as a Yes/No message &lt;code&gt;(Ibid., UIDAI 2010b)&lt;/code&gt;. Now this is all that the Aadhaar project, in its maturity, is expected to perform – authentication of the relationship between a random number pre-assigned to a person and a person who claims that a particular number has been assigned to him/her. While, the description may seem anti-climactic, it performs a fundamental and critical infrastructural operation for linking the distributed agency-specific databases operated by government bodies of all scale and size, inherited from the past decades of information systems for electronic governance. CIDR, hence, is not simply a database of identities, it is a database of identifiers. Its logic of operation draws more from a technological culture of database management, as evident from its embracing of technical terms such as &amp;ldquo;unique identification number&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;de-duplication&amp;rdquo; for abstract conceptualisation of intimately political processes of formation of social identities and collectivities, than from the logic of a governmental panopticon or a totalising information repository, as evident from its attempts to minimise the personal information collected during the &amp;ldquo;enrollment&amp;rdquo; process and to  avoid political messiness by specifically not collecting information regarding &amp;ldquo;race, religion, caste, tribe, ethnicity, language, income or health&amp;rdquo; &lt;code&gt;(Ibid.)&lt;/code&gt;. It is not aimed at undertaking financial surveillance across all public and private transactions taking place in the county, but at enabling the same&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual realisation of the Aadhaar project as a ‘platform&amp;rsquo; to be leveraged by all the government agencies remains open to chances, to be determined by political negotiations, civil society activisms, intra-governmental administrative reforms politics and so on. This paper, however, is not about the chances of the Aadhaar project being implemented, the eventual forms of its implementation, and political economic struggles created in its wake. It is about tracing and locating its vision of rethinking information infrastructure of governance in India. Hence, in this paper, I mark a historic period in the transformations of the information infrastructure of governance in India, where there is great resistance and confusion regarding the very act and the multi-dimensional implications, especially for the national administrative structure, of the specter of a &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; national information infrastructure of governance. The key, as I argue in this paper, for confronting the changes in the national information architecture, including its possibilities of breakdown, spillage, splintering, and totalising biopolitical gaze, that this spectral Aadhaar project proposes and deploys, is not to be found in the infrastructural components that it mobilises (e.g., biometric scanners, the Aadhaar number, CIDR) but in the infrastructural relations that it necessitates (e.g., incorporation of the Aadhaar number-based authentication process into welfare delivery activities of various government agencies, and the technical requirements for their internal information architecture reform)&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references:4b3345dd999e8171226a4ff304e711cf&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(Bowker 1994)&lt;/code&gt; Bowker, Geoffrey C. 1994. &lt;em&gt;Science on the Run: Information Management and Industrial Geophysics at Schlumberger, 1920–1940&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(Bowker et al 2010)&lt;/code&gt; Bowker, Geoffrey C., Karen Baker, Florence Millerand &amp;amp; David Ribes. 2010. Toward Information Infrastructure Studies: Ways of Knowing in a Networked Environment. In Jeremy Hunsinger et al (eds.), &lt;em&gt;International Handbook of Internet Research&lt;/em&gt;. Springer Science+Business Media B.V. Pp. 97-117.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(DeitY 2011)&lt;/code&gt; Department of Electronics and Information Technology (DeitY), Ministry of Communications and Information Technology, Government of India. 2010. &lt;em&gt;Meeting of the National e-Governance Advisory Group: Background Papers&lt;/em&gt;. November 12. New Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(Larkin 2013)&lt;/code&gt; Larkin, Brian. 2013. The Politics and Poetics of Infrastructure. &lt;em&gt;Annual Review of Anthropology&lt;/em&gt;. Volume 42. Pp. 327–343.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(Mehmood 2008)&lt;/code&gt;Mehmood, Taha. 2008. Notes from a Contested History of National Identity Card in India: 1999-2007. South Asia Citizens Web. December 09. Accessed on November 09, 2013 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sacw.net/article391.html&#34;&gt;http://www.sacw.net/article391.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(National Security Council Secretariat 1999)&lt;/code&gt; National Security Council Secretariat, Government of India. 2000. &lt;em&gt;From Surprise to Reckoning: The Kargil Review Committee Report&lt;/em&gt;. New Delhi: Sage Publications India Pvt. Ltd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(NTFoITaSD 1999)&lt;/code&gt; National Task Force on Information Technology and Software Development (NTFoITaSD), Office of the Prime Minister, Government of India. 2008. &lt;em&gt;IT Action Plan Part III: Long Term National IT Policy&lt;/em&gt;. Accessed on November 09, 2013 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://it-taskforce.nic.in/actplan3/&#34;&gt;http://it-taskforce.nic.in/actplan3/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(Nilekani 2008)&lt;/code&gt; Nilekani, Nandan. 2008. From Bangalore One to Country One. Outlook. December 01. Accessed on November 09, 2013 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?239112&#34;&gt;http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?239112&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(UIDAI 2010a)&lt;/code&gt; Unique Identification Authority of India (UIDAI), Planning Commission, Government of India. 2010a. &lt;em&gt;Strategy Overview: Creating a Unique Identity Number for Every Resident in India&lt;/em&gt;. April. New Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(UIDAI 2010b)&lt;/code&gt; Unique Identification Authority of India (UIDAI), Planning Commission, Government of India. 2010b. &lt;em&gt;Aadhaar Automated Biometric Identification Subsystem Interface&lt;/em&gt;. June. New Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Indic Wikipedia Visualisation Project #2: Visualising Page Views and Project Pages</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/indic-wikipedia-visualisation-project-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2013 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/indic-wikipedia-visualisation-project-2/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;co-authored-with-sajjad-anwar-http-geohacker-in-published-by-the-centre-for-internet-and-society-http-cis-india-org-openness-blog-old-indic-wikipedia-visualisation-project-visualising-page-views-and-project-pages:e0fe0008838454773365ee5a4e37cd7f&#34;&gt;Co-authored with &lt;a href=&#34;http://geohacker.in/&#34;&gt;Sajjad Anwar&lt;/a&gt;. Published by &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/openness/blog-old/indic-wikipedia-visualisation-project-visualising-page-views-and-project-pages&#34;&gt;the Centre for Internet and Society&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://geohacker.in/&#34;&gt;Sajjad Anwar&lt;/a&gt; and I undertook a series of visualisations of readership and editing data of the Indic Wikipedia projects in early 2013. The work was supported by &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/&#34;&gt;the Centre for Internet and Society&lt;/a&gt;, and the data was provided by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wikimedia.org/&#34;&gt;Wikimedia Foundation&lt;/a&gt;. This post looks at the basic parameters associated with the Indic Wikipedia projects, and shares visualisations divided in three focus areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction:e0fe0008838454773365ee5a4e37cd7f&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the basic parameters that &lt;a href=&#34;../indic-wikipedia-visualisation-project-1/&#34;&gt;we discussed last month&lt;/a&gt;, we received the Page Views data only from January 2008 onwards. The project-specific pages allow the user to see all the different variables related to a Indic language Wikipedia project in one page, thus giving a general overview of the activities in that project and their inter-relationships. Instead of comparing multiple projectsn, as in the calendar charts and motion chart discussed in the last post, the project-specific pages focus on understanding one Wikipedia project in detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;page-views:e0fe0008838454773365ee5a4e37cd7f&#34;&gt;Page Views&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data came in a structure that is useful for human-readability of the data but not so much for visualisation. The first column contained the date value (01/01/2008, 01/02/2008, and so on), followed by a column for each Indic Wikipedia project (Assamese, Bhojpuri, and so on) and one for the total Page Views across projects for the month concerned. The original data file can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/geohacker/indicwiki/blob/master/data/page_views.csv&#34;&gt;accessed here&lt;/a&gt;. We re-formatted this data to the following column structure: the first column gives the date value, the second column gives the language of the Wikipedia project, and the third column gives the Page Views value. Further, the Page Views file contained data for 2013 that are not available for any other variables (like Total Articles, Total Editors etc.). So we decided to remove the 2013 values from the Page Views file for easier comparison with other variables. The data file that we finally used for the visualisation can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/geohacker/indicwiki/blob/master/data/page_views_2.csv&#34;&gt;accessed here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;calendar-heatmap-chart:e0fe0008838454773365ee5a4e37cd7f&#34;&gt;Calendar (Heatmap) Chart&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first chart that we created was the calendar (heatmap) chart discussed in detail in the &lt;a href=&#34;../indic-wikipedia-visualisation-project-1/&#34;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;. For the Page View variable we only had data form 2008. We plotted it as calendar-like heatmap to allow quick cross-project comparisons of trends in readership. The chart can be &lt;a href=&#34;http://geohacker.github.io/indicwiki/page-views&#34;&gt;accessed here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/indic-wikipedia-page-views-per-month.png&#34; alt=&#34;code&#34; title=&#34;Indic Wikipedia Visualisation Project - Page Views per Month&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;source-http-geohacker-in-indicwiki-page-views:e0fe0008838454773365ee5a4e37cd7f&#34;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://geohacker.in/indicwiki/page-views&#34;&gt;http://geohacker.in/indicwiki/page-views&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;project-pages:e0fe0008838454773365ee5a4e37cd7f&#34;&gt;Project Pages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, we have been visualising the data from an overall perspective, constantly asking the question: “How does project A compare to project B?”. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://geohacker.github.io/indicwiki/projects&#34;&gt;Project pages&lt;/a&gt; shed light from a different angle: “How did project A get to this point?”. Each of the projects are visualised in isolation around the basic parameters to understand how they have changed/evolved over the years. We wanted to keep this as simple as possible and decided to use straight forward line charts. This also ensures that the patterns are clearly evident. On the right corner of the navigation bar is the project selector. You can search or pick a project and the page will load the charts specific to that project. Each project has a different page, this makes it easier for you to share the project that you are interested in. The chart employs filtering and dynamic scales. Dynamic scales are important because not all the projects have the same rate of growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/indic-wikipedia-project-pages.png&#34; alt=&#34;code&#34; title=&#34;Indic Wikipedia Visualisation Project - Project Pages&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;source-http-geohacker-in-indicwiki-projects:e0fe0008838454773365ee5a4e37cd7f&#34;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://geohacker.in/indicwiki/projects&#34;&gt;http://geohacker.in/indicwiki/projects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;readership-dashboard:e0fe0008838454773365ee5a4e37cd7f&#34;&gt;Readership Dashboard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were not satisfied with creating only the calendar heatmap chart for Page Views. Being a very important variable for anybody trying to understand activities on Indic Wikipedia projects, we wanted to create a more detailed visualisation for the variable. While the project-specific pages do allow for comparing Page Views for a certain Indic Wikipedia with its other variables (such as Total Articles), we wanted to make that comparison even easier. Hence we decided to make a chart combining a line graph showing the movement of Page View for a project across the years and bar graphs showing a separate variable for the same project. Thus we created the &lt;a href=&#34;http://geohacker.github.io/indicwiki/readers&#34;&gt;Readership Dashboard&lt;/a&gt;. The dashboard has two controls: project selector and the parameter selector buttons. Selecting a project from the dropdown will update the line chart showing the movement of page views. Hover over the line graph points to see the date of observation and the corresponding value. The bars behind the line represent the selected parameters. Click on the parameter buttons to load different parameters as the background bar graph. Hover over the bars to see the date and the value. The bar graph is carefully aligned to the line chart such that the visualisation reflects the relation in movement of both. However, please note that the vertical scale of the line graph and the bar graphs are not the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/indic-wikipedia-readership.png&#34; alt=&#34;code&#34; title=&#34;Indic Wikipedia Visualisation Project - Readership Dashboard&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;source-http-geohacker-in-indicwiki-readership:e0fe0008838454773365ee5a4e37cd7f&#34;&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://geohacker.in/indicwiki/readership&#34;&gt;http://geohacker.in/indicwiki/readership&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h6&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>