<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Government And Computing In India on Sumandro</title>
    <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/categories/government-and-computing-in-india/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Government And Computing In India on Sumandro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 20:09:56 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/categories/government-and-computing-in-india/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Protecting the Territory, Killing the Map</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/protecting-the-territory-killing-the-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/protecting-the-territory-killing-the-map/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;co-authored-with-adya-garg-published-by-the-wire-http-thewire-in-2016-05-16-before-geospatial-bill-a-long-history-of-killing-the-map-in-order-to-protect-the-territory-36453:26906d7510c4a6c3ffdbbbee2ba326c2&#34;&gt;Co-authored with Adya Garg. Published by &lt;a href=&#34;http://thewire.in/2016/05/16/before-geospatial-bill-a-long-history-of-killing-the-map-in-order-to-protect-the-territory-36453/&#34;&gt;The Wire&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The global history of cartography is intimately linked with political needs and economic interests, from the public depiction of sovereign territories to navigating treacherous seas to (wrongly) ‘discover’ the land of spices. In India, the politics of making and using maps has taken a sudden and complex turn with the publication of the draft Geospatial Information Regulation Bill, 2016. Contrary to the expectations arising out of several government schemes that are promoting the development of the new digital economy in India – from start-ups to the ongoing expansion of connectivity network – the bill seems to be undoing various economic and humanitarian efforts, and other opportunities involving maps, by imposing strict guidelines and harsh penalties on the use of maps by private actors, commercial or otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://mha.nic.in/sites/upload_files/mha/files/GeospatialBill_05052016_eve.pdf&#34;&gt;introductory note to the bill&lt;/a&gt; clearly states its primary objective is to ensure the protection of ‘security, sovereignty and integrity of India.’ The concern around ‘security’ is not new when it comes to regulating cartographic activities. It is prominently addressed across the current set of policies and guidelines that govern mapping in India: 1) the National Map Policy, 2005 (“NMP”) and associated guidelines issued by the Survey of India, 2) the Remote Sensing Data Policy, 2011 that regulates satellite-based mapping, and 3) the Civil Aviation Requirement, 2012, which regulates mapping and photography using flights and drones. Protection of ‘sovereignty and integrity,’ however, does not find a mention in any of these map-related policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have of course been several incidents where the government has taken steps (including the temporary blocking of service) against companies that have represented Indian national boundaries that are not in accordance with official maps. Such companies include &lt;em&gt;Google&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The Economist&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Al Jazeera&lt;/em&gt;. Two companies that have gotten away with no consequences after publicly showing maps of India without certain border regions, interestingly, are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scoopwhoop.com/news/kashmir-missing-from-india-map/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Facebook&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://thewire.in/2015/05/14/chinese-state-owned-television-shows-india-map-sans-jammu-kashmir-arunachal-1698/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;CCTV&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the absence of such provisions in the existing map-related policies, thus far, the government has pursued legal action against such ‘anti-national’ depiction of  Indian territory under  Section 69A of the IT Act, 2000, the Official Secrets Act, 1923 (restricting the collection and sharing of information about ‘prohibited places’), the Customs Act, 1962 (prohibiting the export and import of certain maps), and the Criminal Law (Amendment) Act,1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though this present bill has come into public attention rather suddenly, the Indian State has been planning for a comprehensive legal framework for both enabling and restricting mapping, since the coming of the NMP itself. The first avatar of this effort was the Indian Survey Act that was heard about in 2007, but  was never made public. More recently, the first report towards the National Geospatial Information Policy (now called the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dst.gov.in/sites/default/files/Draft-NGP-Ver%201%20ammended_05May2016.pdf&#34;&gt;National Geospatial Policy&lt;/a&gt;) came out in 2012. Instead of waiting for this comprehensive policy to be discussed and notified, the bill seems to have come in a hurry to propose a narrowly designed legal instrument. As is often the problem with such precise devices that also want to be exhaustive, the bill promises much more collateral damage than actual solutions – it ends up killing the map in the name of protecting the territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick look at case law on map-related disputes informs us about the motivations of the state in enacting this bill. A major controversy around ‘sovereignty’ in the field of mapping has been about the depiction of international boundaries of India by Google. After several incidents of conflicts between Google’s map makers and the Indian State regarding the depiction of India’s national boundary, the Survey of India filed a police complaint in 2014. As a result, Google presently shows different map tiles to users from India (according to the boundary specified by the Indian State) and different tiles to users from elsewhere. This geo-targeted solution to the depiction of international borders under dispute has been practiced by Google in the case of other countries too, most notably for &lt;a href=&#34;http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/02/28/the-first-google-maps-war/&#34;&gt;Nicaragua, Costa Rica&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://jtl.columbia.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/4/2016/03/Merel_54-CJTL-425.pdf&#34;&gt;Ukraine and (independent) Crimea&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internal security concerns have also fuelled conflicts with mapping companies. In 2013, the ‘mapathon’ organised by Google faced a lawsuit for not asking for prior permission from the Survey of India for this exercise in user-contributed mapping. This was preceded by a petition filed by J. Mohanraj in the Madras High Court seeking a complete ban on the Google Earth and Bhuvan (run by ISRO) map applications on the ground that they were both  providing information that could be used for planning acts of terror. The petitioner’s argument referred to the provisions of the NMP, and also alleged that such mapping practices violated the individual rights of a person under Article 21 of the Constitution. The court, however, held (2008) that the petitioner was unable to produce any specific “Guidelines/Rules/Law laid down by the Central/State Governments, prohibiting the private organisations or any other individuals to Interactive Mapping Program, covering vast majority of the Planet”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trouble with Google re-opened earlier this year as the Pathankot air base was attacked. Incidentally, Vishal Saini, the winner of the 2013 mapathon by Google, contributed to mapping the features of the very same city. Promptly after the attack in January, Lokesh Kumar Sharma filed a case in the Delhi High Court alleging that the availability of sensitive information (from an internal security point-of-view) on Google Maps created security vulnerabilities. In a rather curious manner, the court disposed of the case on February 24, claiming that it has learned from the Additional Solicitor General that ‘steps are in progress to regulate the publication of aerial/satellite geospatial data.’ In hindsight, we see that this was in reference to the draft bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bill, evidently, is a product of the Indian State’s inefficient attempts at regulating the making and circulation of maps and geospatial data in digital times. The bill ends up disregarding the actual features of digital geospatial data and how it forms a fundamental basis (and asset) for today’s digital economy, and, instead, decides to settle for a form of regulation that is much better suited (if at all) to a pre-digital and pre-liberalisation condition. The regulatory measures proposed by the bill do not only cause worry but also bewilderment. Take for example Section 3 that states that ‘no person shall acquire geospatial imagery or data including value addition of any part of India’ without being expressly given permission for the same or being vetted by the nodal agency set up by the Bill. If implemented strictly, this may mean that you will have to ask for permission and/or security vetting before dropping a pin on the map and sharing your coordinates with your friend or a taxi service. Both involve creating/acquiring geospatial information, and potentially adding value to the map/taxi service as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take an even more bizarre hypothetical situation – the Security Vetting Agency being asked to go through the entire geospatial data chest of Google everyday (or as soon as it is updated) and it taking up to ‘ three months from the date of receipt’ of the data to complete this checking so that Google Maps can tell you how crowded a particular street was three months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, a key term that the bill does not talk about is ‘big data.’ The static or much-slowly-changing geospatial data such as national boundaries and which-military-institute-is-located-where are really the tiny minority of the global geospatial information. The much larger and crucial part is of course the fast-moving big geospatial data – from geo-referenced tweets, to GPS systems of cars, to mobile phones moving through the cities and regions. Addressing such networked data systems, where all data can quite easily be born-georeferenced, and the security and privacy concerns that are engendered by them, should be the ultimate purpose of, and challenge for, a future-looking Geospatial Information Regulation Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The present bill imposes an undesirable bureaucratic structure of licenses and permits upon the GIS industry in the country in particular, and on all sections of the economy using networked devices in general. This will only end up restricting the size of the GIS industry to a few dominant players. For all creators and users of maps for non-commercial, developmental, and humanitarian interests, this bill appears to be an imminent threat, even if it is never actually applied.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Buying into the Aakash Dream: A Tablet’s Tale of Mass Education</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/buying-into-the-aakash-dream/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2016 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/buying-into-the-aakash-dream/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;co-authored-with-jahnavi-phalkey-http-www-kcl-ac-uk-sspp-sga-kii-people-jahnaviphalkey-index-aspx-published-by-economic-and-political-weekly-http-www-epw-in-journal-2016-17-web-exclusives-buying-aakash-dream-html:dcf794d4d237a70396527a795b3ef51c&#34;&gt;Co-authored with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kcl.ac.uk/sspp/sga/kii/people/jahnaviphalkey/index.aspx&#34;&gt;Jahnavi Phalkey&lt;/a&gt;. Published by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.epw.in/journal/2016/17/web-exclusives/buying-aakash-dream.html&#34;&gt;Economic and Political Weekly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This research note is based on a project conducted as part of the Max Weber Foundation’s Transnational Research Group on &amp;ldquo;Poverty and Education in India,&amp;rdquo; and draws from a &lt;a href=&#34;../aakash-tablet-and-technological-imaginaries-of-mass-education/&#34;&gt;paper recently published&lt;/a&gt; by the authors in &lt;em&gt;History and Technology&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction:dcf794d4d237a70396527a795b3ef51c&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Aakash tablet, hailed as the vanguard of India&amp;rsquo;s “tablet revolution,” was unveiled at the United Nations. It was to showcase India&amp;rsquo;s technological prowess but was quickly lamented as a failed “dream,” and as India&amp;rsquo;s “object lesson” in how not to do technological innovation. The so-called failure of the device became a metonym for the government that backed it, and for the technology establishment of the country. While our longer paper (Phalkey and Sumandro 2016) questions this notion of “failure,” in this article we wish to highlight the role played by the discourse and experiments in technologies of mass education in creating the practical context and the market conditions for low-cost tablets in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 2011 report by the Ministry of Human Resource Development (MHRD) claimed that although the initiation of the Aakash tablet project met with “skepticism and scorn,” over time it not only developed an affordable device aimed at students in India, but has produced an entirely new market niche of sub-US$100 tablets. This ambitious statement appears to be vindicated by a recent report by the International Data Corporation (IDC), an economic intelligence company, on the tablet market in India. The report notes that the market has grown in the previous year at an annual rate of 8.2%. More importantly, the two companies leading in market share are DataWind (20.7%) and Samsung (15.8%). Incidentally, after the first quarter of 2014, Samsung had the largest (22.5%) and DataWind the 4th largest (6.8%) share. What is noteworthy here is not the rise of DataWind as the leading seller of tablets alone, but that it is the MHRD that heralded this creation of a market niche in India for affordable tablets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;from-satellite-to-internet-in-education:dcf794d4d237a70396527a795b3ef51c&#34;&gt;From Satellite to Internet in Education&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 30 May, 1974, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) launched an ATS-6 satellite that formed the central infrastructural component of the Satellite Instructional Television Experiment (SITE), one of the early initiatives to harness communication technology for primary and adult education. The SITE project involved broadcasting educational and informational audiovisual content, produced by the All India Radio (AIR), across 2400 selected villages located in Andhra Pradesh, Bihar, Karnataka, Madhya Pradesh, Odisha (erstwhile Orissa), and Rajasthan. Operating from 1 August 1975 to 31 July 31 1976, the experiment was led by the Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO), and was supported by UNESCO, United Nations Development Programme (UNDP), United Negro College Fund (UNCF), and the International Telecommunication Union (ITU).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective of the SITE project was inspired directly by the importance given to skill-development oriented higher education and adult education in the report of the first Education Commission (1964–1966). However, Asif Siddiqi (2015) notes that the project performed a crucial task of establishing the Indian space research programme through a direct alliance with NASA, which held special geopolitical significance given the Chinese nuclear tests of 1964.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experiment paved the way for the development of the Indian National Satellite System (INSAT,) the first Indian satellite. The entanglement of the Indian space programme with the idea of national-level technological infrastructure for education has continued since. The EDUSAT, launched in 2004, was a collaborative project between ISRO and MHRD to drive satellite-based education across disadvantaged and remote regions of the country. In an audit report in 2013, however, the Department of Space declared that the project has failed, and highlighted three lacks in particular– network connectivity, content generation, and management structure (Union Government 2013).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earliest initiatives in India to put computers in schools, supplementing and supplanting television screens, began in the 1980s. These efforts pre-dated extensive terrestrial communication fibre networks and relied almost completely upon the success of the Indian space programme. The University Grants Commission (UGC) Countrywide Classroom, Computer Literacy and Studies in Schools, and Computer Literacy and Awareness Programme are the key examples from this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revised Programme of Action of the National Policy on Education (1986) reiterated the need for increased attention to upgrading education technology infrastructure, as well as the development of electronic content for the same. This led to the initiation of the ICT@Schools scheme beginning with the 8th Five Year Plan (1993–1998). Even after 20 years of the introduction of computers in schools across India, a 2006 report on education technology by the National Council of Educational Research and Training (NCERT) noted that computer-based teaching and learning in an actual classroom setting remains more of a “spectator sport.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the advent of the internet, the MHRD started experimenting with internet-based delivery of distance education from 2003, beginning with the National Programme on Technology Enhanced Learning (NPTEL). It did so alongside satellite-based distribution of educational content. NPTEL involved five Indian Institutes of Technology (IIT) (Bombay, Delhi, Kanpur, Kharagpur, and Madras) developing openly available course materials for more than 100 undergraduate courses in five engineering subjects, as well as courses in basic science. These course materials were later made part of the online learning portal called “Sakshat,” which eventually became one of the pillars of the National Mission on Education through Information and Communication Technologies (NMEICT), initiated during the 11th Five Year Plan (2007–2012). This portal marked the completion of a conceptual and technological shift from the satellite-based models of delivery of educational content, to an internet-based one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-and-unmaking-of-the-aakash-tablet:dcf794d4d237a70396527a795b3ef51c&#34;&gt;Making and Unmaking of the Aakash Tablet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With NMEICT, large-scale education technology initiatives of the Indian state moved away from the earlier emphasis on primary education and school-oriented computer literacy, to that on higher education and aids for self-learning. The plan for an affordable tablet computer was announced in mid-2010 as part of this mission. This “low-cost access-cum-computing device” was aimed at bypassing the institutional, bureaucratic, and infrastructural barriers to access to quality higher education. Its main audience were students in disadvantaged regions and non-elite institutions, as well as self-learners. The actualisation of the device, however, was continuously delayed and blocked by conflicts between the governmental and non-governmental actors, strong skepticism from the media, and several changes in the state&amp;rsquo;s approach to the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first approach to the project was an international company that approached the MHRD in 2006, with a proposal to sell educational laptops for school students at 100 US$ each. NK Sinha, then mission director of NMEICT, argued against the purchase. The MHRD saw this as an opportunity for developing an indigenous low-cost computer, and initiated a competition among the IITs to come up with a prototype for this device, which was won by the IIT Kanpur team led by Prem Kumar Kalra, then professor and head of the department of Electrical Engineering. The first publicly exhibited (2010) prototype of the device was the one developed in IIT Kanpur, which was priced initially at 35 US$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MHRD, however, soon decided to buy the device from a commercial manufacturer. The responsibility of procurement and testing went to IIT Rajasthan, under the leadership of Kalra who joined the newly established institution as its first director. After the contract with HCL Infosystems was called off in January 2011, DataWind, a Canada and UK based company specialising in internet-access devices, won the new tender to produce the first version of the device. On 5 October 2011, the first version of tablet was launched, priced at Rs 2,500, and co-branded as Aakash and Ubislate—respectively for those bought and redistributed at a subsidised rate by MHRD, and those sold commercially by DataWind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An early controversy about the tablet, apart from its technical capabilities, was around the claim that they were produced and assembled in China. DataWind rejected the allegations and claimed that all the devices were assembled by Quad Electronics in its factory in Secunderabad, Telangana (then Andhra Pradesh). Within a year, however, DataWind got involved in serious conflict with IIT Rajasthan on one hand, and Quad Electronics on the other. The MHRD intervened again to change the approach by bringing in IIT Bombay (March 2012) as the new procuring and testing agency, thus removing IIT Rajasthan from the project. DataWind also found a new partner in VMC Systems, who started assembling the “kits” imported from China in its establishments in Amritsar and Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With M M Pallam Raju becoming the Minister of Human Resource Development in late 2012 by succeeding Kapil Sibal, one might say, the Aakash project gradually moved to what we know as its final form. At first, it was suggested that the state should entirely move out of the business of providing low-cost tablets as there is already a vibrant market. Later on, and with thought leadership from Rajat Moona, director general of the Centre for Development of Advanced Computing (CDAC), and others, it was decided that “Aakash” would become a brand name available for commercial manufacturers of affordable tablets that satisfy a minimum set of technical specifications. The first draft of the specifications list was published in June 2013. The tendering process, however, got delayed, and eventually came to a near-permanent pause with the general elections in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of November 2015, the MHRD has again shown interest in the idea of a state-subsidised tablet computer for education. The tablet was now called Udaan, and aimed at girl students at the higher secondary level, priced at Rs 10,000 (against Rs 2,500 of Aakash), and distributed only to 1,000 students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-device-desire:dcf794d4d237a70396527a795b3ef51c&#34;&gt;Creating Device Desire&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an interview in late 2013, Kapil Sibal (then Union Minister of Communication and Information Technology, former Union Minister of Human Resource Development) shared that “[the] Aakash tablet was [his] dream but it was not fulfilled.” Sibal, undoubtedly the key political driver of the project, in his admission to failure, raises deep concerns about the present state and the future of the technological infrastructure—and the imagination—for mass education in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tracing the transition of these technologies from SITE to Aakash, we continuously find it difficult to delineate the state’s transforming and transformative agenda of mass education from that of building technological capability. At times, though, we wondered if the agenda for mass education did not become one that served the purpose of generating, for lack of a better phrase, a certain familiarity and literacy about personal technological devices among the population. The motivations and goals that informed these mammoth projects become more and more difficult to decipher when we look at the relatively poor attention given to the production of content. Careful monitoring and documentation of how such content is being received and utilised by the actual learners and their educators was not prioritised; and whenever undertaken, such exercises revealed the deep lack of pedagogic concerns at the heart of these education technology programmes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside the overwhelming narrative of failure, however, we cannot ignore the remarkable, but quiet, success of the project in normalising and framing the tablet computer as familiar, and almost essential, object for personal learning and development. Apart from presenting the tablet computer as an everyday media object, almost similar to the way television entered the households, the NMEICT and the Aakash project played a crucial role in normalising the notion of online self-learning, and thus that of the online, in the Indian public imagination. In an insightful comment, Suneet Singh Tuli, the CEO of DataWind, remarked that the Aakash tablet was not an “iPad for the poor,” it was the “the computer and Internet of the masses”—it was not selling a demo version of the real thing, it was shaping the very imagination (Kurup 2011).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stories, together, conspire to make us wonder if all this eventually amounts to create desires for devices; and if the educational and developmental rhetoric helped frame electronic devices as everyday and household objects. The consequences, as we see, cannot exactly be called unintended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references:dcf794d4d237a70396527a795b3ef51c&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All URLs accessed on 21 April 2016.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government of India (2011): “The Newsletter on Higher Education,” Issue 6, Department of Higher Education, &lt;a href=&#34;http://mhrd.gov.in/sites/upload_files/mhrd/files/document-reports/Newsletter-062011.pdf&#34;&gt;http://mhrd.gov.in/sites/upload_files/mhrd/files/document-reports/Newsletter-062011.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kurup, Saira (2011): “&amp;rsquo;We Want to Target the Billion Indians Who are Cut Off&amp;rsquo;,” Times of India, 9 October, &lt;a href=&#34;http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/home/sunday-times/deep-focus/We-want-to-target-the-billion-Indians-who-are-cut-off/articleshow/10284832.cms&#34;&gt;http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/home/sunday-times/deep-focus/We-want-to-target-the-billion-Indians-who-are-cut-off/articleshow/10284832.cms&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phalkey, Jahnavi and Sumandro Chattapadhyay (2016): “The Aakash Tablet and Technological Imaginaries of Mass Education in Contemporary India,” History and Technology, Vol 31, No 4, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/07341512.2015.1136142?journalCode=ghat20&#34;&gt;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/07341512.2015.1136142?journalCode=ghat20&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Siddiqi, Asif (2015): “Making Space for the Nation: Satellite Television, Indian Scientific Elites, and the Cold War,” Comparative Studies of South Asia, Africa and the Middle East, Vol 35, No 1, pp 35–49, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cssaame.dukejournals.org/content/35/1/35.abstract&#34;&gt;http://cssaame.dukejournals.org/content/35/1/35.abstract&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Union Government (2013): “Report of the Comptroller and Auditor General of India for the year ended March 2012,” Scientific and Environmental Ministries/Departments, Report No. 22 of 2013 (Compliance Audit), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cag.gov.in/sites/default/files/audit_report_files/Union_Compliance_Scientific_Department_Audit_22_2013.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.cag.gov.in/sites/default/files/audit_report_files/Union_Compliance_Scientific_Department_Audit_22_2013.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welfare is the Message, Surveillance is the Medium</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/welfare-is-the-message-surveillance-is-the-medium/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2016 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/welfare-is-the-message-surveillance-is-the-medium/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;published-by-the-wire-http-thewire-in-2016-04-19-the-last-chance-for-a-welfare-state-doesnt-rest-in-the-aadhaar-system-30256:fdeadc845334f57050ce5e7050d1e1c7&#34;&gt;Published by &lt;a href=&#34;http://thewire.in/2016/04/19/the-last-chance-for-a-welfare-state-doesnt-rest-in-the-aadhaar-system-30256/&#34;&gt;The Wire&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, a king desired that his parrot should be taught all the ancient knowledge of the kingdom. The priests started feeding the pages of the great books to the parrot with much enthusiasm. One day, the king asked the priests if the parrot’s education has completed. The priests poked the belly of the parrot but it made no sound. Only the rustle of undigested pages inside the belly could be heard. The priests declared that the parrot is indeed a learned one now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fate of the welfare system in our country is quite similar to this parrot from Tagore’s parable. It has been forcefully fed identification cards and other official documents (often four copies of the same) for years, and always with the same justification of making it more effective and fixing the leaks. These identification regimes are in effect killing off the welfare system. And some may say that that has been the actual plan in any case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Aadhaar number has been recently offered as &lt;a href=&#34;http://indianexpress.com/article/opinion/columns/aadhaar-project-uidai-last-chance-for-a-welfare-state/&#34;&gt;the ‘last chance’ for the ailing welfare system&lt;/a&gt; – a last identification regime that it needs to gulp down to survive. This argument wilfully overlooks the acute problems with the Aadhaar project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the ‘last chance’ for a welfare state in India is not provided by implementing a new and improved identification regime (Aadhaar numbers or otherwise), but by enabling citizens to effectively track, monitor, and ensure delivery of welfare, services, and benefits. This ‘opening up’ of the welfare bureaucracy has been most effectively initiated by the Right to Information Act. Instead of a centralised biometrics-linked identity verification platform, which gives the privilege of tracking and monitoring welfare flows only to a few expert groups, an effective welfare state requires the devolution of such privilege and responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should harness the tracking capabilities of electronic financial systems to disclose how money belonging to the Consolidated Fund of India travel around state agencies and departmental levels. Instead, the Aadhaar system effectively stacks up a range of entry barriers to accessing welfare – from malfunctioning biometric scanners, to connectivity problems, to the burden of keeping one’s fingerprint digitally legible under all labouring and algorithmic circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, authentication of welfare recipients by Aadhaar number neither make the welfare delivery process free of techno-bureaucratic hurdles, nor does it exorcise away corruption. Anumeha Yadav has recently documented the emerging &lt;a href=&#34;http://scroll.in/article/805909/in-rajasthan-there-is-unrest-at-the-ration-shop-because-of-error-ridden-aadhaar&#34;&gt;‘unrest at the ration shop’ across Rajasthan&lt;/a&gt;, as authentication processes face technical and connectivity delays, people get ‘locked out’ of public services for not having or having Aadhaar number with incorrect demographic details, and no mechanisms exist to provide rapid and definitive recourse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RTI activists at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.snsindia.org/&#34;&gt;Satark Nagrik Sangathan&lt;/a&gt; have highlighted that the Delhi ration shops, using Aadhaar-based authentication, maintain only two columns of data to describe people who have come to the shop – those who received their ration, and those who did not (without any indication of the reason). This leads to erasure-by-design of evidence of the number of welfare-seekers who are excluded from welfare services when the Aadhaar-based authentication process fails (for valid reasons, or otherwise).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reetika Khera has made it very clear that using Aadhaar Payments Bridge to directly transfer cash to a beneficiary’s account, in the best case scenario, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.epw.in/journal/2013/05/commentary/cost-benefit-analysis-uid.html&#34;&gt;may only take care of one form of corruption&lt;/a&gt;: deception (a different person claiming to be the beneficiary). But it does not address the other two common forms of public corruption: collusion (government officials approving undue benefits and creating false beneficiaries) and extortion (forceful rent seeking after the cash has been transferred to the beneficiary’s account). Evidently, going after only deception does not make much sense in an environment where collusion and extortion are commonplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the ‘relevant privacy question’ for Aadhaar is not limited to how UIDAI protects the data collected by it, but expands to usage of Aadhaar numbers across the public and private sectors. The privacy problem created by the Aadhaar numbers does &lt;em&gt;begin&lt;/em&gt; but surely not &lt;em&gt;end&lt;/em&gt; with internal data management procedures and responsibilities of the UIDAI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one hand, the Aadhaar Bill 2016 has reduced the personal data sharing restrictions of the NIAI Bill 2010, and has &lt;a href=&#34;http://scroll.in/article/806297/no-longer-a-black-box-why-does-the-revised-aadhar-bill-allow-sharing-of-identity-information&#34;&gt;allowed for sharing of all data except core biometrics (fingerprints and iris scan)&lt;/a&gt; with all agencies involved in authentication of a person through her/his Aadhaar number. These agencies have been asked to seek consent from the person who is being authenticated, and to inform her/him of the ways in which the provided data (by the person, and by UIDAI) will be used by the agency. In careful wording, the Bill only asks the agencies to &lt;em&gt;inform&lt;/em&gt; the person about “alternatives to submission of identity information to the requesting entity” (Section 8.3) but not to &lt;em&gt;provide&lt;/em&gt; any such alternatives. This facilitates and legalises a much wider collection of personal demographic data for offering of services by public agencies “or any body corporate or person” (Section 57), which is way beyond the scope of data management practices of UIDAI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the Aadhaar number is being &lt;em&gt;seeded&lt;/em&gt; to all government databases – from lists of HIV patients, of rural citizens being offered 100 days of work, of students getting scholarships meant for specific social groups, of people with a bank account. Now in some sectors, such as banking, inter-agency sharing of data about clients is strictly regulated. But we increasingly have non-financial agencies playing crucial roles in the financial sector – from mobile wallets to peer-to-peer transaction to innovative credit ratings. Seeding of Aadhaar into all government and private databases would allow for easy and direct joining up of these databases by anyone who has access to them, and not at all by security agencies only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it becomes publicly acceptable that &lt;a href=&#34;http://indianexpress.com/article/opinion/columns/aadhaar-project-uidai-last-chance-for-a-welfare-state/&#34;&gt;the &lt;em&gt;money bill route&lt;/em&gt; was a ‘remedial’ instrument&lt;/a&gt; to put the Rajya Sabha ‘back on track’, one cannot not wonder about what was being remedied by avoiding a public debate about the draft bill before it was presented in Lok Sabha. The answer is simple: &lt;em&gt;welfare is the message, surveillance is the medium&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acceptance and adoption of all medium requires a message, a content. The users are interested in the message. The message, however, is not the business. Think of Free Basics. Facebook wants people with none or limited access to internet to enjoy parts of the internet at zero data cost. Facebook does not provide the content that the users consume on such internet. The content is created by the users themselves, and also provided by other companies. Facebook own and control the medium, and makes money out of all content, including interactions, passing through it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UIDAI has set up a biometric data bank and related infrastructure to offer authentication-as-a-service. As the Bill clarifies, almost all agencies (public or private, national or global) can use this service to verify the identity of Indian residents. Unlike Facebook, the content of these services do not flow through the Aadhaar system. Nonetheless, Aadhaar keeps track of all ‘authentication records’, that is records of whose identity was authenticated by whom, when, and where. This database is gold (data) mine for security agencies in India, and elsewhere. Further, as more agencies use authentication based on Aadhaar numbers, it becomes easier for them to combine and compare databases with other agencies doing the same, by linking each line of transaction across databases using Aadhaar numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welfare is the message that the Aadhaar system is riding on. The message is only useful for the medium as far as it ensures that the majority of the user population are subscribing to it. Once the users are enrolled, or on-boarded, the medium enables flow of all kinds of messages, and tracking and monetisation (perhaps not so much in the case of UIDAI) of all those flows. It does not matter if the Aadhaar system is being introduced to remedy the broken parliamentary process, or the broken welfare distribution system. What matters is that the UIDAI is establishing the infrastructure for a universal surveillance system in India, and without a formal acknowledgement and legal framework for the same.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Aakash Tablet and Technological Imaginaries of Mass Education in Contemporary India</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/aakash-tablet-and-technological-imaginaries-of-mass-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Feb 2016 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/aakash-tablet-and-technological-imaginaries-of-mass-education/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;co-authored-with-dr-jahnavi-phalkey-http-www-kcl-ac-uk-sspp-sga-kii-people-jahnaviphalkey-index-aspx:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;Co-authored with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kcl.ac.uk/sspp/sga/kii/people/jahnaviphalkey/index.aspx&#34;&gt;Dr. Jahnavi Phalkey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper, co-authored by Dr. Jahnavi Phalkey, King&amp;rsquo;s College London, and I, was published in &lt;em&gt;History and Technology&lt;/em&gt;, on 5 February, 2016. It can be accessed from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/07341512.2015.1136142&#34;&gt;journal website&lt;/a&gt; (behind pay wall), and the pre-publication version is available from &lt;a href=&#34;http://ssrn.com/abstract=2761716&#34;&gt;SSRN&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We explore here public and private initiatives in technological solutions for educating the poor and the disadvantaged in India since the second half of the twentieth century. Specifically, we document Ministry of Human Resource Development’s project to develop an affordable tablet computer, named ‘Aakash,’ as a personal access device for digital courses and online learning materials. We approach this case study in relation to several educational technologies that preceded it, and with a wider interest in mapping a contemporary transition from satellite-based mass education to Internet-based mass education. We argue that this process cannot be easily seen as a transition from unilateral broadcasting to more democratic multi-casting model of communication and learning. Specifically, we study the manufacturing process of Aakash and the public debates around it, to comment on the nature of state power in India, as revealed in its attempts to imagine and develop a digital personal device to deliver mass education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blog-post:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;Blog Post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;this-blog-post-containing-excerpts-from-the-paper-was-published-by-the-south-asia-lse-blog-http-blogs-lse-ac-uk-southasia-2016-02-12-the-aakash-tablet-and-technological-imaginaries-of-mass-education-in-contemporary-india-on-february-12-2016:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;This blog post containing excerpts from the paper was published by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.lse.ac.uk/southasia/2016/02/12/the-aakash-tablet-and-technological-imaginaries-of-mass-education-in-contemporary-india/&#34;&gt;South Asia @ LSE Blog&lt;/a&gt;, on February 12, 2016.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/SC_Aakash_Resized.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;code&#34; title=&#34;Students at Pardada Pardadi Education Society in Anupshahr, Uttar Pradesh, use the Aakash tablet in class as part of a pilot project. Photograph by Sonali Campion.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;students-at-pardada-pardadi-education-society-in-anupshahr-uttar-pradesh-use-the-aakash-tablet-in-class-as-part-of-a-pilot-project-introducing-the-low-cost-computer-into-rural-schools-photograph-by-sonali-campion-https-www-flickr-com-photos-sonalicampion-9449250639-april-09-2013:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;Students at Pardada Pardadi Education Society in Anupshahr, Uttar Pradesh, use the Aakash tablet in class as part of a pilot project introducing the low-cost computer into rural schools. Photograph by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/sonalicampion/9449250639/&#34;&gt;Sonali Campion&lt;/a&gt;, April 09, 2013.&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2010, the Ministry of Human Resource Development (MHRD) of the Government of India launched a set of prototype devices of an affordable tablet computer, the development and production of which were to be supported by the Ministry as part of its larger ICTs for education project. This device later came to be known as the “Aakash” tablet, and the project went through several iterations, between 2010 and 2014, of not only technological re-designs, but also institutional arrangements to design, develop, manufacture, test, and procure the devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;technological-solutions-for-mass-education:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;Technological Solutions for Mass Education&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our exploration of technological solutions for mass education in India has taken us through a not-so-linear history of projects that have informed the imagination and making of the Aakash project. This include the Satellite Instructional Television Experiment, or SITE (1975); University Grants Commission-led Countrywide Classroom project (1984 -); the Simputer, the first hand-held device developed in India (1998); the Hole in the Wall project developed and led by Sugata Mitra (1999); the Government of India-led EDUSAT (2004); National Programme on Technology Enhanced Learning (2003); and finally, a national online education portal named Sakshat (2006). The Satellite Instructional Television Experiment itself terminated rather quickly, but it led to several versions of television based instruction programmes, most notably aimed at higher secondary and university students. Instruction in the broadcast-format continues to date, even after the arrival of the internet and the fact it has become the preferred medium for the Indian state. The television has not been replaced, but certainly shadowed by a variety of internet access and computing devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;aakash-a-low-cost-access-cum-computing-device:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;Aakash, a “Low Cost Access-Cum-Computing Device”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An early official description of the then-nameless tablet as a “low cost access-cum-computing device” is noteworthy &lt;code&gt;[1]&lt;/code&gt;. It is difficult to imagine a contemporary computing device that does not also function as an access device (say, to the internet). Where does the need for calling it an “access-cum-computing” device come from? It comes, perhaps, from the hierarchy of priority – the device is primarily an access device, and secondarily can perform the function of a general-purpose computer. An archaeological reading of the assumptions of learning processes embodied in this device reveals an earlier layer of thinking – that of broadcasting educational programmes to television sets via satellite connection. Labelling it as “access-cum-computing” frames the object as being shaped by the residue of the Indian state’s education technological experiences of the past, including that of the SITE initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-aakash-tablet-was-my-dream-but-it-was-not-fulfilled:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;“[The] Aakash tablet was my dream but it was not fulfilled”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the short history of the Aakash device, the verdict of “failed innovation” figures prominently – from the early failure of “Sakshat” &lt;code&gt;[2]&lt;/code&gt;, to allegations of the Chinese origin of the Aakash device &lt;code&gt;[3]&lt;/code&gt;, to manufacturing troubles and under-production of the device &lt;code&gt;[4]&lt;/code&gt;, to criticisms of the tablet’s built quality and computing capacity &lt;code&gt;[5]&lt;/code&gt;, to mistrust and failed collaborations between parties involved in its production &lt;code&gt;[6]&lt;/code&gt;, and intra-governmental criticisms of the implementation process &lt;code&gt;[7]&lt;/code&gt;. Moreover, there remained a continuous tension within the government itself regarding the necessity of the project, especially fuelled by (and fuelling) the image of the project as being driven by the dreams of a specific minister &lt;code&gt;[8]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To simply describe the Aakash project’s failure as one due to the unbearable heaviness of functions ranging from the technical to the symbolic and political is to fall short of a full explanation. Alongside that narrative of failure, it is critical to foreground the quiet success of the project in establishing the tablet computer as a near-essential and familiarised everyday object for access to educational material. There is an alarming accuracy in the MHRD claim that the Aakash project established a sub $100 tablet market in India – it did, even if it was not for the device they wanted to promote &lt;code&gt;[9]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-device-is-the-desire:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;The Device is the Desire&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We observe that the Aakash project, as well as the ones preceding it, have been driven primarily by a desire to scale up the provision of education. The initiatives towards building delivery infrastructures for such mass-scale provision of education has almost always been accompanied by a larger desire for developing capabilities in space exploration, communication, and computing – the key technologies of twentieth century geopolitics. Our study of the manufacturing of the Aakash tablet, and its surrounding discourses, foreground the technological imagination of the state after liberalisation in India (1991), and its unique arrangements and efforts to create domestic capability of technological innovation in a context of globalised production and communication networks. We see our role as one of recovering the work of technology in the history of education as understood through the interactions between the state, academia, and industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;archival-research-in-increasingly-digital-india:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;Archival Research in (Increasingly) Digital India&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Documenting the project has been an interesting historical exercise. We have been attentive to documents disappearing from their online locations. One remarkable possibility for archival research opened up by the internet is the (limited, and often uncertain) ability to access materials that are not presently available on a website, but were part of it in the past. This possibility allowed us to access a few crucial government documents that are not directly available on the official websites any more. We have also been attentive to the reiterations and revisions that do not merely overtake or shadow earlier documents. They sometimes erase earlier documents altogether as digital revisions. We do not have access to personal correspondence or internal institutional correspondence relating to the project. We are, however, skeptical of that happening as no protocols for the archiving of digital correspondence is yet in place with the Government of India. Doing recent history of India is becoming an ever more difficult exercise that historians must urgently attend to, if we are to make the present ready to have its own past in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references:fa4f0317257e65139c9248e2974ab462&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[1]&lt;/code&gt; Ministry of Human Resource Development, Government of India. “The History of Aakash Low Cost Access cum Computing Device.” Sakshat. October 05, 2011. &lt;a href=&#34;http://archive.sakshat.ac.in/pdf/Final_Note_Aakash.pdf&#34;&gt;http://archive.sakshat.ac.in/pdf/Final_Note_Aakash.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[2]&lt;/code&gt; Mukherjee, Arindam. “Bonsai Netbooks.” Outlook. February 16, 2009. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.outlookindia.com/article/Bonsai-Netbooks/239719&#34;&gt;http://www.outlookindia.com/article/Bonsai-Netbooks/239719&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[3]&lt;/code&gt; Raina, Pamposh, and Mia Li. “India’s ‘Aakash,’ Now Made in China.” The New York Times. November 26, 2012. &lt;a href=&#34;http://india.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/11/26/india%E2%80%99s-super-cheap-tablet-now-made-in-china/&#34;&gt;http://india.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/11/26/india%E2%80%99s-super-cheap-tablet-now-made-in-china/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[4]&lt;/code&gt; Nanda, Prashant K., and Surabhi Agarwal. “Government Close to Giving Up on Aakash Project.” Mint. March 22, 2013. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.livemint.com/Politics/fmEi8gsOSFgOzSTFfLsw6J/Govt-almost-gives-up-on-Aakash-says-no-point-in-hardware-ob.html&#34;&gt;http://www.livemint.com/Politics/fmEi8gsOSFgOzSTFfLsw6J/Govt-almost-gives-up-on-Aakash-says-no-point-in-hardware-ob.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[5]&lt;/code&gt; Chopra, Ritika. “Kapil Sibal&amp;rsquo;s Cheap Aakash Proves to be a Dud.” Mail Today. January 08, 2012. &lt;a href=&#34;http://indiatoday.intoday.in/story/kapil-sibal-cheapest-tablet-of-world-aakash-failure/1/167730.html&#34;&gt;http://indiatoday.intoday.in/story/kapil-sibal-cheapest-tablet-of-world-aakash-failure/1/167730.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[6]&lt;/code&gt; Julka, Harsimran. “14 Lakh Aakash Tablets Booked in 14 Days.” The Economic Times. January 03, 2012. &lt;a href=&#34;http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/tech/hardware/14-lakh-aakash-tablets-booked-in-14-days/articleshow/11345695.cms&#34;&gt;http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/tech/hardware/14-lakh-aakash-tablets-booked-in-14-days/articleshow/11345695.cms&lt;/a&gt;. Parthasarathi, Ashok. “Cloudy Outlook for Aakash.” The Hindu. May 21, 2012 (Updated: May 22, 2012). &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thehindu.com/opinion/op-ed/article3439629.ece&#34;&gt;http://www.thehindu.com/opinion/op-ed/article3439629.ece&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[7]&lt;/code&gt; Comptroller and Auditor General of India, Government of India. Report No. 19 of 2013 - Union Government (Civil) - Report of the Comptroller and Auditor General of India on Compliance Audit Observations. Government of India. 2013. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cag.gov.in/content/report-no-19-2013-compliance-audit-observations-union-governmentcivil&#34;&gt;http://www.cag.gov.in/content/report-no-19-2013-compliance-audit-observations-union-governmentcivil&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[8]&lt;/code&gt; At an event in late 2013, Kapil Sibal admitted, “[the] Aakash tablet was my dream but it was not fulfilled, I tried hard…” Quoted in Press Trust of India. “Kapil Sibal: Aakash Tablet is My Unfulfilled Dream.” Financial Express. December 24, 2013. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.financialexpress.com/news/kapil-sibal-aakash-tablet-is-my-unfulfilled-dream/1211284/0&#34;&gt;http://www.financialexpress.com/news/kapil-sibal-aakash-tablet-is-my-unfulfilled-dream/1211284/0&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[9]&lt;/code&gt; See [1].&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Studying the Emerging Database State in India: Notes for Critical Data Studies - Accepted Abstract</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/studying-the-emerging-database-state-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2015 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/studying-the-emerging-database-state-in-india/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A paper abstract of mine has been provisionally accepted for publication in the upcoming special issue of &lt;a href=&#34;http://bds.sagepub.com/&#34;&gt;Big Data &amp;amp; Society&lt;/a&gt; journal on &amp;lsquo;Critical Data Studies.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://bigdatasoc.blogspot.co.uk/2015/06/call-for-proposals-special-theme-on.html&#34;&gt;call for papers&lt;/a&gt; of the issue notes that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critical Data Studies (CDS) is a growing field of research that focuses on the unique theoretical, ethical, and epistemological challenges posed by “Big Data.” Rather than treat Big Data as a scientifically empirical, and therefore largely neutral phenomena, CDS advocates the view that data should be seen as always-already constituted within wider data assemblages&amp;hellip; CDS questions the many assumptions about data that permeate contemporary literature on information and society by locating instances where data may be naively taken to denote objective and transparent informational entities. CDS may be viewed as an emerging field connected to Information Ethics, Software Studies, and Critical Information Studies in that it seeks to question the ethical import of information and Big Data for society&amp;hellip; We seek essays for this special volume that broaden these latest commitments in CDS to include new empirical research projects on information and communication technologies (ICTs) that fall under the umbrella of Big Data, while also seeking to question their attendant epistemological shifts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the last decade, the Government of India has given shape to an digital identification infrastructure, developed and operated by the Unique Identification Authority of India (UIDAI). The infrastructure combines the task of assigning unique identification numbers, called Aadhaar numbers, to individuals submitting their biometric and demographic details, and the task of authenticating their identity when provided with an Aadhaar number and associated data (biometric data, One Time Pin sent to the pre-declared mobile number, etc.). The aim of UIDAI is to provide universal authentication-as-a-service for all residents of India who approach any public or private agencies for any kind of service or transaction. Simultaneously, the Aadhaar numbers will function as unique identifiers for joining up databases of different government agencies, and hence allow the Indian government to undertake big data analytics at a governmental scale, and not only at a departmental one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, I am primarily motivated by the challenge of finding points and objects to enter into a critical study of such an in-progress data infrastructure. As I proceed with an understanding that data is produced within its specific social and material context, the question then is to read through the data to reflect on its possible social and material context. This is complicated when approaching a big data infrastructure that is meant to produce data for explicitly intra-governmental consumption and circulation. The problem then is not one of reading through available big data, but one of reading through the assemblage and imaginaries of big data to reflect on the kind of data it will give rise to, and thus on the politics of the data assemblage and the database state it enables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;logic-of-the-database-state:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Logic of the Database State&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Application of data to inform governmental acts have taken place at least since government has been understood as responsible for the welfare of the population and the territory. The measurement of the population and the territory – the number of people, their demographic features, amounts and locations of natural resources, and so on – have always been integral to the functioning of the modern nation-state. Database state is used in this paper to identify a particular mode of mobilisation of data within governmental acts, which is fundamentally shaped by the possibilities of big data extraction, appropriation, and analytics pioneered by a range of companies since late 1990s. The reason for not using big data state but database dtate is that big data refers to a body of technologies emerging in response to a set of data management and analysis challenges situated in a certain moment of development of information technologies, whereas database refers to a symbolic form (Manovich 1999): a form in which not only the population is made visible to the government (as a collection of visual, textual, numeric, and other forms of records), but also how the acts of government are made visible to the population (as a collection of performance indicators, budget allocation and utilisation tables, and other data visualised through dashboards, analog and digital).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data production and management logic of this database state is specifically inspired by the notion of platform introduced by the so-called Web 2.0 companies: providing a common service layer upon which various other applications may also run, but under specific arrangements (including distribution of generated user data) with the original common layer provider. Data assemblages of the database state are expected to enable the government to function as a platform, as an intensely data-driven layer that widely gathers data about population individuals and feeds it back selectively to various providers of public and private services. This transforms the data assemblage from one vertical of governmental activities to a horizontal critical infrastructure for modularisation of governmental activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;studying-the-emerging-database-state-in-india:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Studying the Emerging Database State in India&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government of India is presently debating the legal and technical validity of the digital identity infrastructure programme in the Supreme Court, while simultaneously carrying out the enrolment drive for the same, linking up assignment of unique identity numbers with a national drive for population registration, and rolling out citizen-facing services and applications that implement the Aadhaar number as a necessary key to access them. With the enrollment process going on and the integration with various governmental processes (termed seeding by Aadhaar policy literature) just beginning, I enter this study through two key sets of objects reflecting the imaginaries and the technical specifications of the emerging database state in India. The first entry point is through the various official documents of vision, intentions, plans, and reconsiderations, and the second entry point is through the Application Programming Interface (API) documentations published by UIDAI to specify how its identity authentication platform will collaborate with various public and private services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first section of the paper provides a brief survey of pre-UIDAI attempts by the Government of India to deploy unique identification numbers and Smart Cards for specific population groups, so as to understand the initial conceptualisation of this data assemblage of a digital identification platform. The second section foregrounds how this platform undertakes a transformation of the components and relations of the pre-existing data assemblage of the Government of India, as articulated in various official documents of promised utility and proposed collaborations. The third section studies the API documentations to track how such imaginaries are materially interpreted and operationalised through the design of protocols of data interactions with various public and private agencies offering services utilising the identity authentication platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;notes-for-critical-data-studies:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Notes for Critical Data Studies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expanding the early agenda note on Critical Data Studies by Craig Dalton and Jim Thatcher (2014), Rob Kitchin and Tracey P. Lauriault have taken steps towards emphasising the responsibility of this nebulous research strategy to chart and unpack the data assemblages (2014). This is exactly what I propose to do in this paper. While Kitchin and Lauriault provide a detailed list of the components of the apparatus of a data assemblage (2014: 7), I find the concepts of infrastructural components and infrastructural relations very useful in thinking through the emerging infrastructure of authentication. Thus, my approach to these tasks of charting and unpacking is focused on the infrastructural relations that the digital identity infrastructure re-configures, instead of the infrastructural components it mobilises (Bowker et al 2010). This tactical choice of focusing on the infrastructural relations is also necessitated by the practical difficulty in having comprehensive access to the individual components of the data assemblage concerned. Addressing questions of causality and quality becomes difficult when studying the assemblage sans the produced data, and rigorously analysing concerns of security and uncertainty pre-requires an actually existing data assemblage, with a public interface to investigating its leakages, breakages, and internal functioning. In the absence of such points of entry into the data assemblage, which I fear may not be an exceptional case, I attempt an inverted reading. Turning the data infrastructure inside out, in this paper I describe how the digital identity platform is critically reshaping the basis of governmental acts in India, through a specific model of production, extraction and application of big data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bibliography:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bowker, Geoffrey C., Karen Baker, Florence Millerand, &amp;amp; David Ribes. 2010. Toward Information Infrastructure Studies: Ways of Knowing in a Networked Environment. Jeremy Hunsinger, Lisbeth Klastrup, &amp;amp; Matthew Allen (Eds.) International Handbook of Internet Research. Springer Dordrecht Heidelberg London New York. Pp. 97-117.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dalton, Craig, &amp;amp; Jim Thatcher. 2014. What does a Critical Data Studies Look Like, and Why do We Care? Seven Points for a Critical Approach to ‘Big Data.’ Society and Space. May 19. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://societyandspace.com/material/commentaries/craig-dalton-and-jim-thatcher-what-does-a-critical-data-studies-look-like-and-why-do-we-care-seven-points-for-a-critical-approach-to-big-data/&#34;&gt;http://societyandspace.com/material/commentaries/craig-dalton-and-jim-thatcher-what-does-a-critical-data-studies-look-like-and-why-do-we-care-seven-points-for-a-critical-approach-to-big-data/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kitchin, Rob, &amp;amp; Tracey P. Lauriault. 2014. Towards Critical Data Studies: Charting and Unpacking Data Assemblages and their Work. The Programmable City Working Paper 2. July 29. National University of Ireland Maynooth, Ireland. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2474112&#34;&gt;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2474112&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manovich, Lev. 1999. Database as Symbolic Form. Convergence. Volume 5, Number 2. Pp. 80-99.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Of Identity, Platform, and &#39;New&#39; Information Infrastructure of Governance: Situating the Aadhaar Project within the History of Electronic Governance in India</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/situating-the-aadhaar-project-within-the-history-of-electronic-governance-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2013 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/situating-the-aadhaar-project-within-the-history-of-electronic-governance-in-india/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I presented this paper at &lt;a href=&#34;http://sarai.net/social-and-cultural-life-of-information/&#34;&gt;The Social and Cultural Life of Information workshop&lt;/a&gt; organised by the Sarai Programme, CSDS, on November 14-16, 2013. “It brought together a select group of media scholars, historians, anthropologists and geographers for an intensive two day workshop, and aimed at bringing together research on colonial and postcolonial information infrastructures, with a strong South Asian component.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;excerpt:4b3345dd999e8171226a4ff304e711cf&#34;&gt;Excerpt&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper is about a &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; technology of addressing the population, the Aadhaar project, that is under construction in India. Like all (self-declared) &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; technologies, it involves a continued engagement and negotiations with of older technological infrastructures and practices. In this paper, I critically examine the claim of newness by the Aadhaar project, and argue that this newness is to be found in the information infrastructure of governance that the Aadhaar project envisions and promotes, as opposed to the demographic and biometric data it gathers. Brian Larkin brings forward another crucial aspect of the techniques and technologies of addressing. He reminds us that addressing may not necessarily involve a pre-existing object, or an object existing independent of the act of addressing at all. Addressing can be employed to create a semblance of systemic integrity, by referring &amp;ldquo;to the material qualities of the signifier itself rather than to its referential meaning&amp;rdquo; &lt;code&gt;(Larkin 2013: 334)&lt;/code&gt;. It is the army of ghost beneficiaries of welfare-services populating the existing databases of ‘target populations&amp;rsquo; across government departments that the Aadhaar project aims to exorcise in its attempt to re-address the nation, by making them addressable through unique identification numbers with verifiable authenticity (one-to-one correspondence between a number and the resident it refers to)&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explaining the narrower idea of &amp;ldquo;information infrastructure,&amp;rdquo; Geoffrey Bowker et al employ a stricter concept of ‘infrastructure&amp;rsquo; – defined as &amp;ldquo;pervasive enabling resources in network form&amp;rdquo; &lt;code&gt;(Bowker et al 2010: 98)&lt;/code&gt;. The twin emphasis on the network form and its pervasiveness foreground the question of scale threshold of infrastructure. In a crucial intervention, Bowker et al argue for moving the understanding of infrastructure away from something that is in the background, transparent, already-existing and hence can only be studied by its inversion, or in the moment of its breakdown. They approach infrastructure as &amp;ldquo;a fundamentally relational concept,&amp;rdquo; that is in terms of its relationships with other artifacts and processes, specific substantial qualities and spatio-temporal structures of such relationships, relative visibilities of the infrastructure vis-a-vis the other artifacts, and especially the scale and depth of socio-political and organisational interaction, resistance, debate and reconfiguration it generates &lt;code&gt;(Ibid. 99)&lt;/code&gt;. Further, Bowker et al re-introduce the term ‘infrastructural inversion&amp;rsquo; and define it as &amp;ldquo;shifting the emphasis from changes in infrastructural components to changes in infrastructural relations.&amp;rdquo; In his earlier work, Bowker describes the idea of &amp;ldquo;infrastructural inversion&amp;rdquo; as a strategy for foregrounding how technological intervention is not merely about application of scientific or technological reason but substantially involves a strategy of organisation, of assemblage, that is &amp;ldquo;applied simultaneously to the social and natural worlds so as to make them converge&amp;rdquo; &lt;code&gt;(Bowker 1994: 104)&lt;/code&gt;. In this paper, I find his later formulation of the concept through ‘infrastructural components&amp;rsquo; and ‘infrastructural relations&amp;rsquo; – almost as an analogy to the ‘means of production&amp;rsquo; and ‘relations of production&amp;rsquo; – most useful. In this paper I employ the same strategy to read the infrastructural propositions of the Aadhaar project,  and to focus not on the content of the generated unique identity number or the biopolitical economy of their production, but on the relational implications of the project for the national information infrastructure of electronic governance&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taha Mehmood begins an extensive survey of the ‘contested history of National Identity Card in India&amp;rsquo; with the Kargil War of 1999 and the subsequent report of the Kargil Review Committee &lt;code&gt;(Mehmood 2008)&lt;/code&gt;. The executive summary of the report was presented to the members of the Upper House of Parliament on February 25, 2000, and was published later after selective deletion of information (in the interest of national security). Among other recommendations about military, intelligence and general administration in border areas, the report suggested that &amp;ldquo;steps should be taken to issue ID Cards to border villagers in certain vulnerable areas on a priority basis,  pending its extension to other or all parts of the State [of Jammu and Kashmir]&amp;rdquo; &lt;code&gt;(National Security Council Secretariat 1999: 263)&lt;/code&gt;. While, committees and reports that immediately followed this report did not highlight the need for a National Identity Card, the same demand came back in the aftermath of the attack on the Indian Parliament on December 13, 2001. The spatial short circuiting caused by the site of ‘intrusion&amp;rsquo; shifting rapidly from the frontier territory of mountain peaks of Kashmir to the symbolic heart of the nation in New Delhi, perhaps shaped the public acceptance of border securitisation technologies, like unique identity cards embedded with biometric details, as applicable to the entire span of the country. The demand for such a card was eventually shaped into a national project titled Multi-Purpose National Identity Card (MNIC), later categorised as one of the Central Mission Mode Projects of the National E-Governance Plan &lt;code&gt;(Mehmood 2008, DeitY 2011)&lt;/code&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phrase &amp;ldquo;unique identification,&amp;rdquo; however, did not originate with the post-Kargil war security analysis and recommendations. It possibly first appeared in the Long Term National IT Policy report of the National Task Force on Information Technology and Software Development &lt;code&gt;(NTFoITaSD 1999)&lt;/code&gt;, published in April 1999, barely a few months before the war. The report recommended that &amp;ldquo;[i]n the long run citizens must have unique identification Cards – the Citizen ID&amp;hellip; A smart card citizen ID with multi-functions [should] also be launched. The private sector will be actively associated by ensuring a business angle in the project* &lt;code&gt;(Ibid. #70)&lt;/code&gt;. Both these terms &amp;ldquo;unique identification&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;citizen ID&amp;rdquo; are also used by Nandan Nilekani when within a month of the declaration by the Empowered Group of Ministers regarding the making of the UIDAI, he wrote on how a &amp;ldquo;single citizen ID&amp;rdquo; can get rid of the phantoms that haunt the welfare delivery systems in India &lt;code&gt;(Nilekani 2008)&lt;/code&gt;. In the same article, Nilekani provided an early road map of the approach of the Aadhaar project. He referred to Arvind Virmani&amp;rsquo;s efforts to initiate implementation of MASCs and critiqued the (then) ongoing folly of identifying the &amp;ldquo;issuing [of] smart cards as the main challenge of implementing such a system,&amp;rdquo; whereas &amp;ldquo;[i]t is in making the back-end infrastructure secure and scalable, providing a single record keeper for the whole country and integrating the agents who issue these numbers that it gets tough&amp;rdquo; (Ibid.). This position of Nilekani has defined the problem statement of the Aadhaar project since. The philosophical and practical problem that the Aadhaar project tries to solve is that of representing a person using a number, where the one-to-one correspondence between the person and the number can be repeatedly verified. Unlike the problem statement, the solution, however, is not inspiring. While the Aadhaar number itself is an arbitrarily assigned or random number, that is it does not have any causal relation to the information shared by the person (or the Aadhaar number holder) during the act of enrollment, once mapped to a person or to the set of (demographic and bodily/biometric) information shared by the person, the relationship between this otherwise-arbitrary number and the person it signifies (in the Aadhaar database) can only be ‘authenticated&amp;rsquo; if the person is able to produce the same piece (or combination of pieces) of bodily/biometric information provided at the beginning. This creates a bizarre burden upon the person concerned to maintain a certain (selective) bodily integrity, to sustain the authenticity of the relationship with an arbitrary number&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CIDR rests at the centre of the information infrastructure imagined and under deployment by the Aadhaar project &lt;code&gt;(UIDAI 2010a: 10-13)&lt;/code&gt;. On one hand, it is the centralised (not in a physical sense but in an architectural sense) repository of all the assigned Aadhaar numbers along with the corresponding demographic (name, date of birth, sex, family details, and residential address), biometric (photograph of face, and scans of both iris and all fingers), and additional information (e-mail address, mobile number, bank account number to be linked with the Aadhaar number, etc.) collected during the &amp;ldquo;enrollment&amp;rdquo; process; and against which database the de-duplication exercise takes place when a new bundle of demographic and biographic data enter the Aadhaar system for assignment of an Aadhaar number. On the other, it receives the electronically shared information by the Aadhaar number holder for ‘authentication&amp;rsquo; of the one-to-one correspondence between the number and its holder, and sends the verification result as a Yes/No message &lt;code&gt;(Ibid., UIDAI 2010b)&lt;/code&gt;. Now this is all that the Aadhaar project, in its maturity, is expected to perform – authentication of the relationship between a random number pre-assigned to a person and a person who claims that a particular number has been assigned to him/her. While, the description may seem anti-climactic, it performs a fundamental and critical infrastructural operation for linking the distributed agency-specific databases operated by government bodies of all scale and size, inherited from the past decades of information systems for electronic governance. CIDR, hence, is not simply a database of identities, it is a database of identifiers. Its logic of operation draws more from a technological culture of database management, as evident from its embracing of technical terms such as &amp;ldquo;unique identification number&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;de-duplication&amp;rdquo; for abstract conceptualisation of intimately political processes of formation of social identities and collectivities, than from the logic of a governmental panopticon or a totalising information repository, as evident from its attempts to minimise the personal information collected during the &amp;ldquo;enrollment&amp;rdquo; process and to  avoid political messiness by specifically not collecting information regarding &amp;ldquo;race, religion, caste, tribe, ethnicity, language, income or health&amp;rdquo; &lt;code&gt;(Ibid.)&lt;/code&gt;. It is not aimed at undertaking financial surveillance across all public and private transactions taking place in the county, but at enabling the same&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual realisation of the Aadhaar project as a ‘platform&amp;rsquo; to be leveraged by all the government agencies remains open to chances, to be determined by political negotiations, civil society activisms, intra-governmental administrative reforms politics and so on. This paper, however, is not about the chances of the Aadhaar project being implemented, the eventual forms of its implementation, and political economic struggles created in its wake. It is about tracing and locating its vision of rethinking information infrastructure of governance in India. Hence, in this paper, I mark a historic period in the transformations of the information infrastructure of governance in India, where there is great resistance and confusion regarding the very act and the multi-dimensional implications, especially for the national administrative structure, of the specter of a &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; national information infrastructure of governance. The key, as I argue in this paper, for confronting the changes in the national information architecture, including its possibilities of breakdown, spillage, splintering, and totalising biopolitical gaze, that this spectral Aadhaar project proposes and deploys, is not to be found in the infrastructural components that it mobilises (e.g., biometric scanners, the Aadhaar number, CIDR) but in the infrastructural relations that it necessitates (e.g., incorporation of the Aadhaar number-based authentication process into welfare delivery activities of various government agencies, and the technical requirements for their internal information architecture reform)&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references:4b3345dd999e8171226a4ff304e711cf&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(Bowker 1994)&lt;/code&gt; Bowker, Geoffrey C. 1994. &lt;em&gt;Science on the Run: Information Management and Industrial Geophysics at Schlumberger, 1920–1940&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(Bowker et al 2010)&lt;/code&gt; Bowker, Geoffrey C., Karen Baker, Florence Millerand &amp;amp; David Ribes. 2010. Toward Information Infrastructure Studies: Ways of Knowing in a Networked Environment. In Jeremy Hunsinger et al (eds.), &lt;em&gt;International Handbook of Internet Research&lt;/em&gt;. Springer Science+Business Media B.V. Pp. 97-117.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(DeitY 2011)&lt;/code&gt; Department of Electronics and Information Technology (DeitY), Ministry of Communications and Information Technology, Government of India. 2010. &lt;em&gt;Meeting of the National e-Governance Advisory Group: Background Papers&lt;/em&gt;. November 12. New Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(Larkin 2013)&lt;/code&gt; Larkin, Brian. 2013. The Politics and Poetics of Infrastructure. &lt;em&gt;Annual Review of Anthropology&lt;/em&gt;. Volume 42. Pp. 327–343.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(Mehmood 2008)&lt;/code&gt;Mehmood, Taha. 2008. Notes from a Contested History of National Identity Card in India: 1999-2007. South Asia Citizens Web. December 09. Accessed on November 09, 2013 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sacw.net/article391.html&#34;&gt;http://www.sacw.net/article391.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(National Security Council Secretariat 1999)&lt;/code&gt; National Security Council Secretariat, Government of India. 2000. &lt;em&gt;From Surprise to Reckoning: The Kargil Review Committee Report&lt;/em&gt;. New Delhi: Sage Publications India Pvt. Ltd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(NTFoITaSD 1999)&lt;/code&gt; National Task Force on Information Technology and Software Development (NTFoITaSD), Office of the Prime Minister, Government of India. 2008. &lt;em&gt;IT Action Plan Part III: Long Term National IT Policy&lt;/em&gt;. Accessed on November 09, 2013 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://it-taskforce.nic.in/actplan3/&#34;&gt;http://it-taskforce.nic.in/actplan3/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(Nilekani 2008)&lt;/code&gt; Nilekani, Nandan. 2008. From Bangalore One to Country One. Outlook. December 01. Accessed on November 09, 2013 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?239112&#34;&gt;http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?239112&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(UIDAI 2010a)&lt;/code&gt; Unique Identification Authority of India (UIDAI), Planning Commission, Government of India. 2010a. &lt;em&gt;Strategy Overview: Creating a Unique Identity Number for Every Resident in India&lt;/em&gt;. April. New Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;(UIDAI 2010b)&lt;/code&gt; Unique Identification Authority of India (UIDAI), Planning Commission, Government of India. 2010b. &lt;em&gt;Aadhaar Automated Biometric Identification Subsystem Interface&lt;/em&gt;. June. New Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>