<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>India on Sumandro</title>
    <link>https://ajantriks.net/tags/india/</link>
    <description>Recent content in India on Sumandro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 20:09:56 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ajantriks.net/tags/india/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Civil Society Organisations and Internet Governance in India, 2000-2010</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.net/civil-society-organisations-and-internet-governance-in-india-2000-2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.net/civil-society-organisations-and-internet-governance-in-india-2000-2010/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;this-is-a-book-section-written-for-the-asia-internet-history-third-decade-2001-2010-volume-edited-by-prof-kilnam-chon-the-book-was-published-both-in-print-and-as-an-online-open-access-version-in-december-2015-read-the-book-online-here-https-sites-google-com-site-internethistoryasia-book3-https-sites-google-com-site-internethistoryasia-book3:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;This is a book section written for the &lt;em&gt;Asia Internet History - Third Decade (2001~2010)&lt;/em&gt; volume edited by Prof. Kilnam Chon. The book was published, both in print and as an online open access version, in December 2015. Read the book online here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/internethistoryasia/book3&#34;&gt;https://sites.google.com/site/internethistoryasia/book3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#early-days:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Early Days&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#key-organizations:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Key Organizations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#global-and-national-events:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Global and National Events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#internet-policies-and-censorship:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Internet Policies and Censorship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#acknowledgment:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#reference:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Reference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;early-days:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Early Days&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overarching context of development interventions and rights-based approaches has shaped the space of civil society organizations working on the topics of information and communication technologies (ICTs) and Internet governance in India. Early members of this space came from diverse backgrounds. Satish Babu was working with the South Indian Federation of Fishermen Societies (SIFFS) in the mid-1990s, when he set up a public mailing list called &amp;lsquo;FishNet,&amp;rsquo; connected to the Internet via the IndiaLink email network, (then) run by India Social Institute to inter-connect development practitioners in India. He went on to become the President of Computer Society of India during 2012-2013; he also co-founded the Society for Promotion of Alternative Computing and Employment (SPACE) in 2003, where he served as the Executive Secretary during 2003-2010 &lt;code&gt;[Wikipedia 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. Anita Gurumurthy, Executive Director of IT for Change and one of the key actors from Indian civil society organizations that took part in the World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) process, had previously worked extensively on topics related to public health and women&amp;rsquo;s rights &lt;code&gt;[ITfC 2015b]&lt;/code&gt;, which deeply shaped the perspectives she and IT for Change have brought into the Internet governance sphere, globally as well as nationally &lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2001]&lt;/code&gt;. Arun Mehta initiated a mailing list titled &amp;lsquo;India-GII&amp;rsquo; in 2002 to discuss &amp;lsquo;India&amp;rsquo;s bumpy progress on the global infohighway&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[India-GII 2005]&lt;/code&gt;. This list played a critical role in curating an early community of non-governmental actors interested in the topics of telecommunication policy, spectrum licensing, Internet governance, and consumer and communication rights. As Frederick Noronha documented, the mailing list culture grew slowly in India during the late 1990s and early 2000s. However, they had a great impact on organizing early online communities, sometimes grouped around a topical focus, sometimes functioning as a bridge among family members living abroad, and sometimes curating place-specific groups &lt;code&gt;[Noronha 2002]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inaugural conference of the Free Software Foundation of India (FSFI) in Thiruvananthapuram, on 20 July 2001, galvanized the Free/Libre and Open Source Software (FLOSS) community in India. The conference was titled &amp;lsquo;Freedom First,&amp;rsquo; and Richard Stallman was invited as the chief guest. It was a vital gathering of actors from civil society organizations, software businesses, academia, and media, as well as the Secretary of the Department of Information Technology, Government of Kerala (the state where the conference was held). The conference laid the basis for sustained collaborations between the free software community, civil society organizations, emerging software firms in the state, and the Government of Kerala for the years to come. Two early initiatives that brought together free software developers and state government agencies were the Kerala Transportation Project and the IT@School project, which not only were awarded to firms promoting use of FLOSS in electronic governance projects, but also facilitated a wider public dialogue regarding the need to think critically about the making of an information society in India &lt;code&gt;[Kumar 2007]&lt;/code&gt;. The inter-connected communities and overlapping practices of the FLOSS groups, civil society organizations involved in ICT for Development initiatives, telecommunication policy analysts and advocates, and legal-administrative concerns regarding life in the information society – from digital security and privacy, to freedom of online expressions, to transparency in electronic governance infrastructures – have, hence, continued to shape the sub-spherer of civil society organizations in India that are discussing, responding to, and contributing to policies and practices around the Internet governance in India and elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-organizations:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Key Organizations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IT for Change was established in 2000, in Bengaluru, as a non-governmental organization that &amp;lsquo;works for the innovative and effective use of information and communication technologies (ICTs) to promote socio-economic change in the global south, from an equity, social justice and gender equality point of view&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[ITfC 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. It has since made important contributions in the field of ICTs for Development, especially in integrating earlier communication rights practices organized around old media forms with newer possibilities of production and distribution of electronic content using digital media and the Internet &lt;code&gt;[ITfC 2015e]&lt;/code&gt;, and in the field of the Internet governance, especially through their participation in the WSIS and Internet Governance Forum (IGF) processes and by co-shaping the Internet governance discourse in and from the global south &lt;code&gt;[ITfC 2015d]&lt;/code&gt;. It has also done significant works in the area of women&amp;rsquo;s rights in the information society, and has been a core partner in a multi-country feminist action research project on using digital media to enhance the citizenship rights and experiences of marginalized women in India, Brazil, and South Africa &lt;code&gt;[ITfC 2015c]&lt;/code&gt;. IT for Change co-led the formation of Just Net Coalition in February 2014 &lt;code&gt;[JNC 2015]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF) was founded by Osama Manzar in New Delhi in 2002, with a &amp;lsquo;deep understanding that marginalized communities living in socio-economic backwardness and information poverty can be empowered to improve their lives almost on their own, simply by providing them access to information and knowledge using digital tools&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[DEF 2015c]&lt;/code&gt;. DEF has contributed to setting up Community Information Resource Centres from 19 states and 53 districts in India, with computers, printers, scanners, and Internet connectivity &lt;code&gt;[DEF 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. DEF organizes one of the biggest competitions in Asia to identify, foreground and honor significant contributions in the area of ICT for Development &lt;code&gt;[DEF 2015d]&lt;/code&gt;. This annual competition series, titled the &amp;lsquo;Manthan Award&amp;rsquo; (&amp;lsquo;manthan&amp;rsquo; means &amp;lsquo;churning&amp;rsquo; in Sanskrit), started in 2004. It has allowed DEF to create a detailed database of ICT for Development activities and actors in the South Asia and Asia Pacific region. Since 2011, DEF has been working with Association for Progressive Communications on a project titled &amp;lsquo;Internet Rights&amp;rsquo; to move forward the agenda of &amp;lsquo;Internet access for all&amp;rsquo; in India &lt;code&gt;[DEF 2015b]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Society for Knowledge Commons was formed in New Delhi 2007 by &amp;lsquo;scientists, technologists, researchers, and activists to leverage the tremendous potential of the “collaborative innovation” model for knowledge generation that has lead to the growth of the Free and Open Source Software community (FOSS) around the world&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[SKC 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. It has championed integration of FOSS into public sector operations in India – from electronic governance systems to the use of software in educational institutes – and has continuously intervened in Internet governance issues from the perspective of the critical importance of shared knowledge properties and practices for a more democratic information society. It is a part of the Free Software Movement of India &lt;code&gt;[FSMI 2015]&lt;/code&gt;, an alliance of Indian organizations involved in advocating awareness and usage of FOSS, as well as a founding member of the Just Net Coalition &lt;code&gt;[JNC 2015]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centre for Internet and Society (CIS) was established in Bengaluru in 2008 with a research and advocacy focus on topics of accessibility of digital content for differently-abled persons, FOSS and policies on intellectual property rights, open knowledge and Indic language Wikipedia projects, digital security and privacy, freedom of expression and Internet governance, and socio-cultural and historical studies of Internet in India &lt;code&gt;[CIS 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. In one of the key early projects, CIS contributed to the creation of web accessibility policy for government websites in India, which was being drafted by the Department of Information Technology, Government of India &lt;code&gt;[CIS 2008]&lt;/code&gt;. In the following years it took part in Internet Governance Forum summits; submitted responses and suggestions to various policies being introduced by the government, especially the Information Technology (Amendment) Act, 2008, National Identification Authority of India (NIA) Bill, 2010, and the Approach Paper for Legislation on Privacy, 2010; produced a report on the state of open government data in India &lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2011b]&lt;/code&gt;; and undertook an extensive study on the experiences of young people in Asia with Internet, digital media, and social change &lt;code&gt;[Shah 2011]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Software Freedom Law Centre has undertaken research and advocacy interventions, since 2011, on the topics of digital privacy, software patents, and cyber-surveillance &lt;code&gt;[SFLC 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. The Internet Democracy Project, an initiative of Point of View, has organized online and offline discussions, participated in global summits, and produced reports on the topics of freedom of expression, cyber security and human rights, and global Internet governance architecture since 2012 &lt;code&gt;[IDP 2015]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Internet Society chapter to be established in India was in Delhi. The chapter began in 2002 but went through a period of no activity before being revived in 2008 &lt;code&gt;[Delhi 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. The Chennai chapter started in 2007 &lt;code&gt;[Chennai 2015]&lt;/code&gt;, the Kolkata one in 2009 &lt;code&gt;[Kolkata 2015]&lt;/code&gt;, and the Bengaluru chapter came into existence in 2010 &lt;code&gt;[Bangalore 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. Asia Internet Symposium have been organized in India twice: 1) the Kolkata one, held on on 1 December 2014, focused on &amp;lsquo;Internet and Human Rights: Empowering the Users,&amp;rsquo; and 2) the Chennai symposium, held on 2 December 2014, discussed &amp;lsquo;India in the Open and Global Internet.&amp;rsquo; The newest Internet Society chapter in India is in the process of formation in Trivandrum &lt;code&gt;[Trivandrum 2015]&lt;/code&gt;, led by the efforts of Satish Babu (mentioned above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;global-and-national-events:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Global and National Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) conference held on 10-12 December 2003 in Geneva, was not attended by many civil society organizations from India. Several Indian participants in the conference were part of a team of representatives from different global civil society organizations, including Digital Partners, Development Alternatives with Women for a New Era (DAWN), and International Centre for New Media &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003]&lt;/code&gt;. Between the first and the second conference, engagement with the WSIS process increased among Indian civil society organizations, and was especially led by IT for Change. In early 2005, before the second Preparatory Committee meeting for the Tunis conference, IT for Change organized a discussion event titled &amp;lsquo;Gender Perspectives on the Information Society: South Asia Pre-WSIS Seminar&amp;rsquo; in partnership with DAWN and the Indian Institute of Management, Bangalore, which was supported by UNIFEM and the UNDP Asia-Pacific Development Information Programme &lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. In a separate note, Anita Gurumurthy and Parminder Jeet Singh of IT for Change noted their experience as a South Asian civil society organization engaging with the WSIS process &lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2005]&lt;/code&gt;. The second WSIS conference in Tunis, held on 16-18 November 2005, however, did not see significant participation from Indian civil society organizations, except for Ambedkar Centre for Justice and Peace, Childline India Foundation / Child Helpline International, and IT for Change &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2005]&lt;/code&gt;. This contrasted sharply with the over 60 delegates from various Indian government agencies that took part in the conference &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2005]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two important events took place in India in early 2005 that substantially contributed to the civil society discourses in India around information technology and its socio-legal implications and possibilities. The firt was a conference titled &amp;lsquo;Contested Commons, Trespassing Publics&amp;rsquo; organized by the Sarai Programme at the Centre for the Study of Developing Societies, Alternative Law Forum, and Public Service Broadcasting Trust, in Delhi on 6-8 January 2005. This conference attempted to look into the terms of intellectual property rights (IPR) debates from the perspectives of experiences in countries in Asia, Latin America, and Africa. It was based on research carried out by the Sarai Programme and Alternative Law Forum on contemporary realities of media production and distribution, and the ways in which law and legal instruments enter into the most intimate spheres of social and cultural life to operationalize IPRs. The conference combined academic discussions with parallel demonstrations by media practitioners, and knowledge sharing by FLOSS communities &lt;code&gt;[Sarai 2005]&lt;/code&gt;. The second event was the first Asia Source workshop, which took place in Bengaluru during 28 January - 4 February 2005. It brought together more than 100 representatives from South and South-East Asian civil society organizations and technology practitioners working with them, along with several leading practitioners from Africa, Europe, North America, and Latin America, to promote adoption and usage of FLOSS across the developmental sector in the region. The workshop was organized by Mahiti (Bengaluru) and Tactical Technology Collective (Amsterdam), with intellectual and practical support from an advisory group of representatives from FLOSS communities and civil society organizations, and financial support from Hivos, the Open Society Institute, and International Open Source Network &lt;code&gt;[Asia 2015]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the participation of representatives from Indian civil society organizations at the IGFs in Athens (2006) and Rio de Janeiro (2007) was minimal, the IGF Hyderabad, held on 3-6 December 2008, provided a great opportunity for Indian civil society actors to participate in and familiarize themselves with the global Internet governance process. Apart from various professionals, especially lawyers, who attended the Hyderabad conference as individuals, the leading civil society organizations participating in the event included: Ambedkar Center for Justice and Peace, Centre for Internet and Society, Centre for Science, Development and Media Studies, Digital Empowerment Foundation, Internet Society Chennai chapter, IT for Change, and Mahiti. The non-governmental participants from India at the event, however, were predominantly from private companies and academic institutes &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2008]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IT for Change made a critical intervention into the discourse of global Internet governance during the Hyderabad conference by bringing back the term &amp;lsquo;enhanced cooperation&amp;rsquo;, as mentioned in the Tunis Agenda for the Information Society &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2005b]&lt;/code&gt;. At IGF Sharm El Sheikh, held during 15-18 November 2009, Parminder Jeet Singh of IT for Change explained:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[E]nhanced cooperation consists of two parts. One part is dedicated to creating globally applicable policy principles, and there is an injunction to the relevant organizations to create the conditions for doing that. And I have a feeling that the two parts of that process have been conflated into one. And getting reports from the relevant organizations is going on, but we are not able to go forward to create a process which addresses the primary purpose of enhanced cooperation, which was to create globally applicable public policy principles and the proof of that is that I don&amp;rsquo;t see any development of globally applicable public policy principles, which remains a very important need &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2009]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This foregrounding of the principle of &amp;lsquo;enhanced cooperation&amp;rsquo; has since substantially contributed to rethinking of not only the global Internet governance mechanisms and its reconfigurations, but also the Indian government&amp;rsquo;s perspectives towards the same. It eventually led to the proposal made by a representative of Government of India at the UN General Assembly session on 26 October 2011 regarding the establishment of a UN Committee for Internet-Related Policies &lt;code&gt;[Singh 2011]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;internet-policies-and-censorship:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Internet Policies and Censorship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the earliest instances of censorship of online content in India was the blocking of several websites offering Voice over IP (VoIP) software, which can be downloaded to make low-cost international calls, during the late 1990s. The India-GII mailing list initiated by Arun Mehta, as mentioned above, started largely as a response to this blocking move by Videsh Sanchar Nigam Limited (VSNL), the government-owned Internet Service Provider (ISP). Additionally, Mehta filed a case against VSNL for blocking these e-commerce websites, which might be identified as the first case of legal activism for Internet-related rights in India &lt;code&gt;[India-GII 2001]&lt;/code&gt;. During the war between India and Pakistan in 1999, the Indian government instructed VSNL to block various Pakistani media websites, including that of Dawn. As in the case of websites offering VoIP services, this blocking did not involve direct intervention with the websites concerned but only the ability of Indian users to access them &lt;code&gt;[Tanna 2004]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first well-known case of the Government of India blocking digital content for political reasons occurred in 2003 when a mailing list titled &amp;lsquo;Kynhun&amp;rsquo; was banned. The Department of Telecommunications instructed all the ISPs to stop Indian users from accessing the list, hosted don Yahoo! Group, but the previously deployed URL-blocking strategy did not work in this new situation. Blocking the URL of the list did not stop its members from continuing to share emails through it. The Government of India then approached Yahoo! directly to ensure that the mailing list was taken down, which Yahoo! declined to implement. This resulted in the imposition of a blanket block on all Yahoo! Groups pages across ISPs in India in September 2003. By November, Yahoo! decided to close down the mailing list, and the blanket block was repealed &lt;code&gt;[Tanna 2004]&lt;/code&gt;. Further blocking of several blogs and websites continued through 2006 and 2007, where the government decided to work in collaboration with various platforms offering hosted blog and personal web page services to remove access to specific sub-domains. In resistance to this series of blocking orders by the government, there emerged an important civil society campaign titled &amp;lsquo;Bloggers Against Censorship&amp;rsquo; led by the Bloggers Collective Group, a distributed network of bloggers from all across India &lt;code&gt;[Bloggers 2006]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks after the IGF Hyderabad, the Government of India passed the Information Technology (Amendment) Act 2008 on 22 December 2008 &lt;code&gt;[MoLaJ 2009]&lt;/code&gt;, although it was notified and enforced much later on 27 October 2009 &lt;code&gt;[MoCaIT 2009]&lt;/code&gt;. This amendment attempted to clarify various topics left under-defined in the Information Technology Act of 2000. However, as Pranesh Prakash of the Centre for Internet and Society noted, the casual usage of the term &amp;lsquo;offensive content&amp;rsquo; in the amendment opened up serious threats of broad curbing of freedom of online expression under the justification that it caused &amp;lsquo;annoyance&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;inconvenience&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2009]&lt;/code&gt;. Sections 66 and 67 of the amended Information Technology Act, which respectively address limits to online freedom of expression and legally acceptable monitoring of digital communication by government agencies, have since been the objects of strong protests by civil society organizations across India for enabling broad-brushed censorship and surveillance of the Internet in India. Section 66A has, in particular, allowed the government to make a series of arrests of Internet users for posting and sharing &amp;lsquo;offensive content&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[Pahwa 2015]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, the Government of India introduced another critical piece of policy instrument for controlling online expressions – the Information Technology (Intermediary Guidelines) Rules, 2011 &lt;code&gt;[MoCaIT 2011]&lt;/code&gt; – targeted at defining the functions of the intermediaries associated with Internet-related services and communication, and how they are to respond to the government&amp;rsquo;s directives towards taking down and temporarily blocking digital content. The draft rules were published in early 2011 and comments were invited from the general public. One of the responses, submitted by Privacy India and the Centre for Internet and Society, explicitly highlighted the draconian implications of the (then) proposed rules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This rule requires an intermediary to take immediately steps to remove access to information merely upon receiving a written request from “any authority mandated under the law”. Thus, for example, any authority can easily immunize itself from criticism on the internet by simply sending a written notice to the intermediary concerned. This is directly contrary to, and completely subverts the legislative intent expressed in Section 69B which lays down an elaborate procedure to be followed before any information can be lawfully blocked &lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2011]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy apparatus of controlling online expression in India took full form by the beginning of the decade under study here. The &amp;lsquo;chilling effect&amp;rsquo; of this apparatus was made insightfully evident by a study conducted by Rishabh Dara at the Centre for Internet and Society, where fake takedown notices (regarding existing digital content) were sent to seven important Internet intermediaries operating in India, and their responses were studied. The results of this experiment demonstrated that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[T]he Rules create uncertainty in the criteria and procedure for administering the takedown, thereby inducing the intermediaries to err on the side of caution and over-comply with takedown notices in order to limit their liability, and as a result suppress legitimate expressions. Additionally, the Rules do not establish sufficient safeguards to prevent misuse and abuse of the takedown process to suppress legitimate expressions &lt;code&gt;[Dara 2012]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgment:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to Anita Gurumurthy and Parminder Jeet Singh for their generous sharing of information and insights. Raman Jit Singh Cheema, Pranesh Prakash, and Sunil Abraham have also provided crucial suggestions. Extensive background research by P.P. Sneha has significantly enriched my efforts. The Wayback Machine of the Internet Archive deserves a very special thanks. Last but not the least, I am thankful to Kilnam Chon for this wonderful opportunity and his patient support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reference:6f3e254fa7e36617681563e9a0a54cad&#34;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Bloggers 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Bloggers Collective Group, Bloggers Against Censorship. Last updated on April 30, 2009‎. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://censorship.wikia.com/wiki/Bloggers_Against_Censorship&#34;&gt;http://censorship.wikia.com/wiki/Bloggers_Against_Censorship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Dara 2012]&lt;/code&gt; Dara, Rishabh, Intermediary Liability in India: Chilling Effects on Free Expression on the Internet. The Centre for Internet and Society. April 27. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/chilling-effects-on-free-expression-on-internet&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/chilling-effects-on-free-expression-on-internet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[DEF]&lt;/code&gt; Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF). Community Information Resource Centre. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://defindia.org/circ-2/&#34;&gt;http://defindia.org/circ-2/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[DEF b]&lt;/code&gt; Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF). Internet Rights. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://internetrights.in/&#34;&gt;http://internetrights.in/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[DEF c]&lt;/code&gt; Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF). Our Story. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://defindia.org/about-def/&#34;&gt;http://defindia.org/about-def/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[DEF d]&lt;/code&gt; Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF). Manthan Awards. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://defindia.org/manthan-award-south-asia-masa/&#34;&gt;http://defindia.org/manthan-award-south-asia-masa/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[FSFI]&lt;/code&gt; Free Software Foundation of India. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://fsf.org.in/&#34;&gt;http://fsf.org.in/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[FSMI]&lt;/code&gt; Free Software Movement of India. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fsmi.in/node&#34;&gt;http://www.fsmi.in/node&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2001]&lt;/code&gt; Gurumurthy, Anita, A Gender Perspective to ICTs and Development: Reflections towards Tunis. January 15. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.worldsummit2003.de/en/web/701.htm&#34;&gt;http://www.worldsummit2003.de/en/web/701.htm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2005]&lt;/code&gt; Gurumurthy, Anita, and Parminder Jeet Singh, WSIS PrepCom 2: A South Asian Perspective. Association for Progressive Communications. April 01. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apc.org/en/news/hr/world/wsis-prepcom-2-south-asian-perspective&#34;&gt;https://www.apc.org/en/news/hr/world/wsis-prepcom-2-south-asian-perspective&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Gurumuthy, Anita et al (eds.), Gender in the Information Society: Emerging Issues. UNDP Asia-Pacific Development Information Programme. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.genderit.org/sites/default/upload/GenderIS.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.genderit.org/sites/default/upload/GenderIS.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[India-GII 2001]&lt;/code&gt; India-GII, Status of VSNL Censorship of IP-Telephony Sites. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://members.tripod.com/~india_gii/statusof.htm&#34;&gt;http://members.tripod.com/~india_gii/statusof.htm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[India-GII 2005]&lt;/code&gt; India-GII. 2005. Last modified on May 24. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://india-gii.org/&#34;&gt;http://india-gii.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IDP]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Democracy Project. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://internetdemocracy.in/&#34;&gt;http://internetdemocracy.in/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003]&lt;/code&gt; International Telecommunication Union (ITU), Geneva Phase of the WSIS: List of Participants. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/summit_participants.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/summit_participants.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITU 2005]&lt;/code&gt; International Telecommunication Union (ITU), List of Participants (WSIS) – Update 5 Dec 2005. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/final-list-participants.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/final-list-participants.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITU 2005 b]&lt;/code&gt; International Telecommunication Union (ITU), Tunis Agenda for the Information Society. November 18. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/off/6rev1.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/off/6rev1.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2008]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum, Hyderabad Provisional List of Participants. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/index.php/component/content/article/385-hyderabad-provisional-list-of-participants&#34;&gt;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/index.php/component/content/article/385-hyderabad-provisional-list-of-participants&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum, Managing Critical Resources. IGF Sharm El Sheikh, Egypt . November 16. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/2009/sharm_el_Sheikh/Transcripts/Sharm%20El%20Sheikh%2016%20November%202009%20Managing%20Critical%20Internet%20Resources.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/2009/sharm_el_Sheikh/Transcripts/Sharm%20El%20Sheikh%2016%20November%202009%20Managing%20Critical%20Internet%20Resources.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Bangalore]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Society Bangalore Chapter. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocbangalore.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocbangalore.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Delhi]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Society Delhi Chapter. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocbangalore.org&#34;&gt;http://www.isocbangalore.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Chennai]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Society Chennai Chapter. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocbangalore.org&#34;&gt;http://www.isocbangalore.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Kolkata]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Society Kolkata Chapter. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://isockolkata.in/&#34;&gt;http://isockolkata.in/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Trivandrum]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Society Trivandrum Chapter. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.internetsociety.org/what-we-do/where-we-work/chapters/india-trivandrum-chapter&#34;&gt;http://www.internetsociety.org/what-we-do/where-we-work/chapters/india-trivandrum-chapter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITfC]&lt;/code&gt; IT for Change, About IT for Change. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itforchange.net/aboutus&#34;&gt;http://www.itforchange.net/aboutus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITfC b]&lt;/code&gt; IT for Change, Anita Gurumurthy. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itforchange.net/Anita&#34;&gt;http://www.itforchange.net/Anita&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITfC c]&lt;/code&gt; IT for Change, Gender and Citizenship in the Information Society: Southern Feminist Dialogues in Practice and Theory. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gender-is-citizenship.net/&#34;&gt;http://www.gender-is-citizenship.net/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITfC d]&lt;/code&gt; IT for Change, Internet Governance. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itforchange.net/Techgovernance&#34;&gt;http://www.itforchange.net/Techgovernance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITfC e]&lt;/code&gt; IT for Change, Our Field Centre. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itforchange.net/field_centre&#34;&gt;http://www.itforchange.net/field_centre&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[JNC]&lt;/code&gt; Just Net Coalition (JNC). Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://justnetcoalition.org/&#34;&gt;http://justnetcoalition.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Kumar 2007]&lt;/code&gt; Kumar, Sasi V. 2007. The Story of Free Software in Kerala, India. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://swatantryam.blogspot.in/2007/08/story-of-free-software-in-kerala-india.html&#34;&gt;http://swatantryam.blogspot.in/2007/08/story-of-free-software-in-kerala-india.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[MoLaJ 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Ministry of Law and Justice (MoLaJ), The Information Technology (Amendment) Act, 2008. The Gazette of India. February 05. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/downloads/itact2000/it_amendment_act2008.pdf&#34;&gt;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/downloads/itact2000/it_amendment_act2008.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[MoCaIT 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Ministry of Communications and Information Technology (MoCaIT), Notification. The Gazette of India. October 27. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/downloads/itact2000/act301009.pdf&#34;&gt;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/downloads/itact2000/act301009.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[MoCaIT 2011]&lt;/code&gt; Ministry of Communications and Information Technology (MoCaIT), Information Technology (Intermediaries Guidelines) Rules, 2011. The Gazette of India. April 11. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/GSR314E_10511%281%29.pdf&#34;&gt;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/GSR314E_10511%281%29.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Noronha 2002]&lt;/code&gt; Noronha, Frederick, Linking a Diverse Country: Mailing Lists in India. The Digital Development Network. May 22. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.comminit.com/ict-4-development/content/linking-diverse-country-mailing-lists-india&#34;&gt;http://www.comminit.com/ict-4-development/content/linking-diverse-country-mailing-lists-india&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Pahwa 2015]&lt;/code&gt; Pahwa, Nikhil, A List of Section 66A Arrests in India through the Years. Medianama. March 24. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medianama.com/2015/03/223-section-66a-arrests-in-india/&#34;&gt;http://www.medianama.com/2015/03/223-section-66a-arrests-in-india/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Prakash, Pranesh, Short Note on IT Amendment Act, 2008 . The Centre for Internet and Society. February. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/publications/it-act/short-note-on-amendment-act-2008/&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/publications/it-act/short-note-on-amendment-act-2008/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2011]&lt;/code&gt; Prakash, Pranesh, CIS Para-wise Comments on Intermediary Due Diligence Rules, 2011. The Centre for Internet and Society. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/blog/intermediary-due-diligence&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/blog/intermediary-due-diligence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Prakash 2011 b]&lt;/code&gt; Prakash, Pranesh, et al, Open Government Data Study. The Centre for Internet and Society. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/openness/blog/open-government-data-study&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/openness/blog/open-government-data-study&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[SFLC]&lt;/code&gt; Software Freedom Law Centre (SFLC). Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://sflc.in/&#34;&gt;http://sflc.in/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Shah 2011]&lt;/code&gt; Shah, Nishant. 2011. Digital AlterNatives with a Cause? The Centre for Internet and Society. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/digital-natives/blog/dnbook&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/digital-natives/blog/dnbook&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Singh 2011]&lt;/code&gt; Singh, Dushyant, India&amp;rsquo;s Proposal for a United Nations Committee for Internet-Related Policies. Sixty Sixth Session of the UN General Assembly, New York. October 26. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itforchange.net/sites/default/files/ItfC/india_un_cirp_proposal_20111026.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itforchange.net/sites/default/files/ItfC/india_un_cirp_proposal_20111026.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[SKC]&lt;/code&gt; Society for Knowledge Commons. About Us. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.knowledgecommons.in/about-us/&#34;&gt;http://www.knowledgecommons.in/about-us/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Asia Source]&lt;/code&gt; Tactical Technology Collective, Asia Source. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://tacticaltech.org/asiasource&#34;&gt;https://tacticaltech.org/asiasource&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Tanna 2004]&lt;/code&gt; Tanna, Ketan, Internet Censorship in India: Is It Necessary and Does It Work?. Sarai-CSDS Independent Fellowship. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ketan.net/INTERNET_CENSORSHIP_IN_INDIA.html&#34;&gt;http://www.ketan.net/INTERNET_CENSORSHIP_IN_INDIA.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[CIS]&lt;/code&gt; The Centre for Internet and Society. About Us. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/about/&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/about/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[CIS 2008]&lt;/code&gt; The Centre for Internet and Society. 2008. Annual Report. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/accessibility/annual-report-2008.pdf&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/accessibility/annual-report-2008.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Sarai 2005]&lt;/code&gt; The Sarai Programme, Contested Commons, Trespassing Publics. January 12. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://sarai.net/contested-commons-trespassing-publics/&#34;&gt;http://sarai.net/contested-commons-trespassing-publics/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Wikipedia 2015]&lt;/code&gt; Satish Babu. Wikipedia. Last modified on June 25. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satish_Babu&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Satish_Babu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Studying the Emerging Database State in India: Notes for Critical Data Studies - Accepted Abstract</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.net/studying-the-emerging-database-state-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2015 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.net/studying-the-emerging-database-state-in-india/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A paper abstract of mine has been provisionally accepted for publication in the upcoming special issue of &lt;a href=&#34;http://bds.sagepub.com/&#34;&gt;Big Data &amp;amp; Society&lt;/a&gt; journal on &amp;lsquo;Critical Data Studies.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://bigdatasoc.blogspot.co.uk/2015/06/call-for-proposals-special-theme-on.html&#34;&gt;call for papers&lt;/a&gt; of the issue notes that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critical Data Studies (CDS) is a growing field of research that focuses on the unique theoretical, ethical, and epistemological challenges posed by “Big Data.” Rather than treat Big Data as a scientifically empirical, and therefore largely neutral phenomena, CDS advocates the view that data should be seen as always-already constituted within wider data assemblages&amp;hellip; CDS questions the many assumptions about data that permeate contemporary literature on information and society by locating instances where data may be naively taken to denote objective and transparent informational entities. CDS may be viewed as an emerging field connected to Information Ethics, Software Studies, and Critical Information Studies in that it seeks to question the ethical import of information and Big Data for society&amp;hellip; We seek essays for this special volume that broaden these latest commitments in CDS to include new empirical research projects on information and communication technologies (ICTs) that fall under the umbrella of Big Data, while also seeking to question their attendant epistemological shifts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the last decade, the Government of India has given shape to an digital identification infrastructure, developed and operated by the Unique Identification Authority of India (UIDAI). The infrastructure combines the task of assigning unique identification numbers, called Aadhaar numbers, to individuals submitting their biometric and demographic details, and the task of authenticating their identity when provided with an Aadhaar number and associated data (biometric data, One Time Pin sent to the pre-declared mobile number, etc.). The aim of UIDAI is to provide universal authentication-as-a-service for all residents of India who approach any public or private agencies for any kind of service or transaction. Simultaneously, the Aadhaar numbers will function as unique identifiers for joining up databases of different government agencies, and hence allow the Indian government to undertake big data analytics at a governmental scale, and not only at a departmental one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, I am primarily motivated by the challenge of finding points and objects to enter into a critical study of such an in-progress data infrastructure. As I proceed with an understanding that data is produced within its specific social and material context, the question then is to read through the data to reflect on its possible social and material context. This is complicated when approaching a big data infrastructure that is meant to produce data for explicitly intra-governmental consumption and circulation. The problem then is not one of reading through available big data, but one of reading through the assemblage and imaginaries of big data to reflect on the kind of data it will give rise to, and thus on the politics of the data assemblage and the database state it enables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;logic-of-the-database-state:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Logic of the Database State&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Application of data to inform governmental acts have taken place at least since government has been understood as responsible for the welfare of the population and the territory. The measurement of the population and the territory – the number of people, their demographic features, amounts and locations of natural resources, and so on – have always been integral to the functioning of the modern nation-state. Database state is used in this paper to identify a particular mode of mobilisation of data within governmental acts, which is fundamentally shaped by the possibilities of big data extraction, appropriation, and analytics pioneered by a range of companies since late 1990s. The reason for not using big data state but database dtate is that big data refers to a body of technologies emerging in response to a set of data management and analysis challenges situated in a certain moment of development of information technologies, whereas database refers to a symbolic form (Manovich 1999): a form in which not only the population is made visible to the government (as a collection of visual, textual, numeric, and other forms of records), but also how the acts of government are made visible to the population (as a collection of performance indicators, budget allocation and utilisation tables, and other data visualised through dashboards, analog and digital).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data production and management logic of this database state is specifically inspired by the notion of platform introduced by the so-called Web 2.0 companies: providing a common service layer upon which various other applications may also run, but under specific arrangements (including distribution of generated user data) with the original common layer provider. Data assemblages of the database state are expected to enable the government to function as a platform, as an intensely data-driven layer that widely gathers data about population individuals and feeds it back selectively to various providers of public and private services. This transforms the data assemblage from one vertical of governmental activities to a horizontal critical infrastructure for modularisation of governmental activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;studying-the-emerging-database-state-in-india:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Studying the Emerging Database State in India&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government of India is presently debating the legal and technical validity of the digital identity infrastructure programme in the Supreme Court, while simultaneously carrying out the enrolment drive for the same, linking up assignment of unique identity numbers with a national drive for population registration, and rolling out citizen-facing services and applications that implement the Aadhaar number as a necessary key to access them. With the enrollment process going on and the integration with various governmental processes (termed seeding by Aadhaar policy literature) just beginning, I enter this study through two key sets of objects reflecting the imaginaries and the technical specifications of the emerging database state in India. The first entry point is through the various official documents of vision, intentions, plans, and reconsiderations, and the second entry point is through the Application Programming Interface (API) documentations published by UIDAI to specify how its identity authentication platform will collaborate with various public and private services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first section of the paper provides a brief survey of pre-UIDAI attempts by the Government of India to deploy unique identification numbers and Smart Cards for specific population groups, so as to understand the initial conceptualisation of this data assemblage of a digital identification platform. The second section foregrounds how this platform undertakes a transformation of the components and relations of the pre-existing data assemblage of the Government of India, as articulated in various official documents of promised utility and proposed collaborations. The third section studies the API documentations to track how such imaginaries are materially interpreted and operationalised through the design of protocols of data interactions with various public and private agencies offering services utilising the identity authentication platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;notes-for-critical-data-studies:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Notes for Critical Data Studies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expanding the early agenda note on Critical Data Studies by Craig Dalton and Jim Thatcher (2014), Rob Kitchin and Tracey P. Lauriault have taken steps towards emphasising the responsibility of this nebulous research strategy to chart and unpack the data assemblages (2014). This is exactly what I propose to do in this paper. While Kitchin and Lauriault provide a detailed list of the components of the apparatus of a data assemblage (2014: 7), I find the concepts of infrastructural components and infrastructural relations very useful in thinking through the emerging infrastructure of authentication. Thus, my approach to these tasks of charting and unpacking is focused on the infrastructural relations that the digital identity infrastructure re-configures, instead of the infrastructural components it mobilises (Bowker et al 2010). This tactical choice of focusing on the infrastructural relations is also necessitated by the practical difficulty in having comprehensive access to the individual components of the data assemblage concerned. Addressing questions of causality and quality becomes difficult when studying the assemblage sans the produced data, and rigorously analysing concerns of security and uncertainty pre-requires an actually existing data assemblage, with a public interface to investigating its leakages, breakages, and internal functioning. In the absence of such points of entry into the data assemblage, which I fear may not be an exceptional case, I attempt an inverted reading. Turning the data infrastructure inside out, in this paper I describe how the digital identity platform is critically reshaping the basis of governmental acts in India, through a specific model of production, extraction and application of big data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bibliography:40c338b75009a5f195a16708e4e4a3ea&#34;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bowker, Geoffrey C., Karen Baker, Florence Millerand, &amp;amp; David Ribes. 2010. Toward Information Infrastructure Studies: Ways of Knowing in a Networked Environment. Jeremy Hunsinger, Lisbeth Klastrup, &amp;amp; Matthew Allen (Eds.) International Handbook of Internet Research. Springer Dordrecht Heidelberg London New York. Pp. 97-117.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dalton, Craig, &amp;amp; Jim Thatcher. 2014. What does a Critical Data Studies Look Like, and Why do We Care? Seven Points for a Critical Approach to ‘Big Data.’ Society and Space. May 19. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://societyandspace.com/material/commentaries/craig-dalton-and-jim-thatcher-what-does-a-critical-data-studies-look-like-and-why-do-we-care-seven-points-for-a-critical-approach-to-big-data/&#34;&gt;http://societyandspace.com/material/commentaries/craig-dalton-and-jim-thatcher-what-does-a-critical-data-studies-look-like-and-why-do-we-care-seven-points-for-a-critical-approach-to-big-data/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kitchin, Rob, &amp;amp; Tracey P. Lauriault. 2014. Towards Critical Data Studies: Charting and Unpacking Data Assemblages and their Work. The Programmable City Working Paper 2. July 29. National University of Ireland Maynooth, Ireland. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2474112&#34;&gt;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2474112&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manovich, Lev. 1999. Database as Symbolic Form. Convergence. Volume 5, Number 2. Pp. 80-99.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opening Government Data through Mediation</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.net/opening-government-data-through-mediation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2015 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.net/opening-government-data-through-mediation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;report-produced-as-part-of-the-exploring-the-emerging-impacts-of-open-data-in-developing-countries-http-opendataresearch-org-emergingimpacts-project-of-the-open-data-research-network-http-opendataresearch-org-managed-by-the-world-wide-web-foundation-and-supported-by-the-international-development-research-centre-canada:d228ae7112f637e5efb26e3cab82dc7b&#34;&gt;Report produced as part of the &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://opendataresearch.org/emergingimpacts&#34;&gt;Exploring the Emerging Impacts of Open Data in Developing Countries&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; project of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://opendataresearch.org/&#34;&gt;Open Data Research Network&lt;/a&gt;, managed by the World Wide Web Foundation and supported by the International Development Research Centre, Canada.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://data.gov.in/sites/default/files/NDSAP.pdf&#34;&gt;National Data Sharing and Accessibility Policy (NDSAP)&lt;/a&gt; was approved by the Government of India in early 2012 to encourage and govern publication of government created and owned datasets, from various agencies of the central government of India, in open digital formats and through a single national data portal. The Policy extended the mandate of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rti.gov.in/rti-act.pdf&#34;&gt;Right to Information Act of 2005&lt;/a&gt; by establishing the principles and procedures of proactive disclosure of government data in India. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://data.gov.in/&#34;&gt;Open Government Data Platform of India&lt;/a&gt; was launched later in 2012 to collect and publish open government data. This study explores the existing practices of accessing and using government data in India to understand what challenges this Policy and its implementation measures must overcome to actualise the open data agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study surveys selected non­governmental and non­commercial data intermediary organisations, across sectors, that enable other organisations to better work with (access, use, and share) government and non­government data. Interviewing representatives of these organisations and understanding their actual data practices, the study attempts to respond to three key objectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;to undertake a provisional mapping of government data related activities across different sectors to understand the nature of the “open data community” in India,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;to enrich government data/information policy discussion in India by gathering evidence and experience of (non-governmental) data intermediaries regarding their actual practices of accessing and sharing government data, and their utilisation of the provisions of NDSAP and RTI act, and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;to critically reflect on the nature of open data practices in India.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;project-report:d228ae7112f637e5efb26e3cab82dc7b&#34;&gt;Project Report&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project website can be accessed here: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/&#34;&gt;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project Report - Executive Summary: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/report/sumandro_oddc_executive_summary.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/report/report_summary.html&#34;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project Report - Complete: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/report/sumandro_oddc_project_report.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/report/report_01_introduction.html&#34;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-materials:d228ae7112f637e5efb26e3cab82dc7b&#34;&gt;Other Materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timeline of open government data in India: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/resources/timeline.html&#34;&gt;URL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mapping data practices of (potential) data intermediary organisations in India: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/resources/mapping_data_practices.html&#34;&gt;URL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey questionnaire document: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/resources/sumandro_oddc_questionnaire_final.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>