<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Social Media on Sumandro</title>
    <link>https://ajantriks.net/tags/social-media/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Social Media on Sumandro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 20:09:56 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ajantriks.net/tags/social-media/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Note on Regulation of Internet-based Social Media in India, 1999-2013</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.net/note-on-regulation-of-internet-based-social-media-in-india-1999-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.net/note-on-regulation-of-internet-based-social-media-in-india-1999-2013/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;early-history:a19ffca54ac01f3aea041ddbfa5c0bb6&#34;&gt;Early History&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kargil War in 1999 marked the coming of Internet censorship in India, as Pakistani websites, including the online edition of the newspaper Dawn, were blocked. In this pre-social-media era of Internet, the uniqueness of Internet as a communication space was already evident. Blocking of Pakistani websites involved censoring media artifacts beyond the physical territory of India, which also determined the strategy of censorship – not of the media artifact itself but of its access by Indian viewers/users. Even before the Kargil War, VSNL is known to have undertaken blocking of specific e-commerce sites that were providing low-cost international call service though VoIP (Voice over IP) technology. Along with the political case for censorship, this economically motivated censorship by VSNL exemplifies media governance in an era of confusion regarding functional and regulatory boundaries of each media technology &lt;code&gt;[01]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first well documented case of Internet censorship took place on 23rd September 2003. A Yahoo Group named &amp;lsquo;Kynhun&amp;rsquo;, associated with the &amp;lsquo;Hynniewtrep National Liberation Council,&amp;rsquo; an outlawed separatist group from Meghalaya supporting the case of the Khasi tribe, was banned. Department of Telecommunications ordered implementation of the ban through Indian Internet Service Providers (ISPs). But this strategy proved to be faulty as blocking access to the site itself did not stop emails passing through the mailing list. Ministry of Communications approached Yahoo Inc. directly to get the mailing group banned. As Yahoo Inc. declined to remove the group from its domain, in September 2003 the Government of India instructed all ISPs to completely ban Yahoo Groups. The threat worked and the mailing group was discontinued from November 2003 &lt;code&gt;[02]&lt;/code&gt;. In 2006 was the next big wave of Internet censorship measures taken by the government. Like the last time, technical inability of the ISPs to block specific sub-domains of popular blogging and personal web sites such as Geocities and Typepad led to blanket blocking of these platform, resulting in widespread popular protests. Learning from this event, the government decided to work with, rather than against, Google in 2007 when pursuing Orkut to take down content critical of Bal Thackrey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-of-cyber-laws-in-india:a19ffca54ac01f3aea041ddbfa5c0bb6&#34;&gt;Making of Cyber Laws in India&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Information Technology Act of 2000 &lt;code&gt;[03]&lt;/code&gt; was the first policy on cyber law in India, specifically addressing legal recognition and governance of transaction carried out through electronic media. Additionally, the government notified two supporting documents: (1) The Information Technology (Certifying Authorities) Rule 2000, governing mechanisms of authenticating electronic transactions through digital signatures and security guidelines for the same, and the (2) Cyber Regulations Appellate Tribunal (Procedure) Rules 2000. The Cyber Regulations Advisory Committee was also instituted in the same year to support the policy making and regulatory decisions of the government &lt;code&gt;[04]&lt;/code&gt;. While these documents lay the legal and administrative framework for governing electronic commerce in India, the focus was much too biased towards the software standards and data exchange procedures. Thus cyber crimes such as hacking, damaging codes, stealing data, fraudulent e-commerce were much easily addressed by these documents, than the questions of defamatory, inflammatory, anti-nationalist, and hurtful content. The Computer Emergency Response Team (CERT-IN) was formally instituted in 2004 as an unique technical executive body to deal with cyber emergencies. The government attempted to make CERT-IN responsible for censorship of content over Internet, on the basis of a notification under sections 67 and 88 of the IT Act 2000 &lt;code&gt;[05]&lt;/code&gt;. But this remained an administrative difficulty since those sections, or the IT Act itself, did not mandate creation of any such super-vigilant authorities. The first half of 2000s also saw creation of city-based cyber crime units, such as the Cyber Crime Investigation Cell of the Mumbai Police, which have specifically targeted public Internet usage at Cyber Cafes through various measures such as keeping log of users, installing softwares for content-specific censorship and various licensing mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Information Technology (Amendment) Act of 2008 &lt;code&gt;[06]&lt;/code&gt; brought much needed clarifications on governance of difficult topics such as child pornography &lt;code&gt;[07]&lt;/code&gt;. The sections 66A and 69A of the Act, respectively, defines the identification and control of &amp;lsquo;offensive&amp;rsquo; content over electronic/digital media, and empowers the government to “issue directions for blocking of public access to any information through any computer resource”. The Act kept undefined the precautions to be taken in either case, in identifying &amp;lsquo;offensive content&amp;rsquo; and implementing blockage of digital information broadcasting. This lack of guidelines has led to rather arbitrary usage of the power to censor, without making it either accountable or effective. Further, the Act legally recognised the act of &amp;lsquo;transmitting&amp;rsquo; (in the context of &amp;lsquo;offensive&amp;rsquo; messages) as a punishable one. This was a major change in the earlier regulation model applicable to offensive content, including pornography, where the producer of the content, and not the consumers of the same, was legally liable to punitive action. The concept of &amp;lsquo;transmission&amp;rsquo; is especially problematically vague in the context of Internet-based social media, where even a criticism of a certain content, for example through commenting on the blog post, may result in additional circulation of the content (due to the design of social media platforms like Facebook) thus making the commentator liable for the content that s/he was protesting against. This &amp;lsquo;transmission&amp;rsquo; logic also premised the Act&amp;rsquo;s censorship strategy centered around information intermediaries. The IT (Intermediaries Guidelines) Rules 2011 &lt;code&gt;[08]&lt;/code&gt; were approved in April 2011 to supplement the IT (Amendment) Act 2008. As the name suggests the IT Rules 2011 focused on governance of IT intermediaries. As the act of &amp;lsquo;transmission&amp;rsquo; was made punitive, it also became the site of control and the onus was put on the IT intermediaries, including ISPs, web-based media platforms and cyber cafes, to ensure that blockage of content is undertaken at the level of information transmissions &lt;code&gt;[09]&lt;/code&gt;. This creates a distorted situation of censorship where the intermediaries who are not legally liable for content accessed using their services and products are turned into a second-level regulator, often self-imposing content filtering, while the producers of the content are kept out of the loop of censorship action, making it difficult for them to even know whether and why content written or shared by them have been blocked &lt;code&gt;[10]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice-of-censorship-and-its-discontents:a19ffca54ac01f3aea041ddbfa5c0bb6&#34;&gt;Practice of Censorship and its Discontents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This problem, inherent in the existing digital media regulation framework, has become explicit in recent incidents of Internet censorship – from public harassment of a Facebook user for sharing caricature of the Chief Minister of West Bengal, to arresting of two girls in Mumbai, one for writing an &amp;lsquo;offensive&amp;rsquo; status message on Facebook regarding Bal Thackrey and the other for commenting on the same, to the series of URL blocking orders related to curb circulation of hateful content (in the case of blocking modified or falsely attributed images of violence), content affecting public order and peace (in the case of mass exodus of people from the North-East across large cities), defamatory content (in the case of blocking IIPM-related posts), anti-national content (in the case of blocking posts criticising capital punishment of Afzal Guru). The essence of the contradiction here is that the work of censorship should take place very differently in each of these cases (and others) but the government decides to use an unified, and almost authoritative, policy framework to enact it. The gravity of issues such as defamation of a private institute (IIPM) or that of an individual woman (Bindu Krishna), distribution of false images to incite communal anger (images of mutilated bodies and fatal threats), harassment in social media spaces leading to suicide and other extreme acts (a girl in Jalandhar and elsewhere), content critical of government&amp;rsquo;s decisions (hanging of Afzal Guru) and parody accounts of government offices (Twitter account of Dr. Maunmohan Singh) etc., and the broader legal frameworks (including freedom of speech and sedition law) of addressing them are substantially varied. Instead of devising a suitably diverse strategy for controlling public discourse on social media, the government has increasingly focused Google, Facebook and other large digital media businesses to monitor and regulate the content being produced and shared on their platform. The exemplary failure of this strategy of responding to requests for blockage of digital content without verifying the merit of the request has been the recent blocking of a notice on the University Grants Commission website that clarified that Indian Institute of Planning and Management is not a certified university. Without investigating the content of the UGC notice, it was ordered to be blocked for &amp;lsquo;defaming&amp;rsquo; IIPM &lt;code&gt;[11]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that this domestic move towards a tightly governed and monitored Internet-based social media space, complements the global initiative taken by the Government of India. The digital architecture of Internet and the key agencies governing it, like ICANN (Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers), are in theory governed by global multi-stakeholder processes, involving country heads and representatives of the international telecommunication industry. In reality, the decision-making processes and legal actions, especially of the extra-territorial kind, is significantly shaped by the United State of America in particular and the OECD nations in general. As understood from the early days of Internet censorship in India during the VoIP ban and the Kargil War situation, Internet as a media poses a critical challenge to the sovereignty of the state. Internet involves not only producers, distributors and consumers of content across the world to intermingle, shape and give platform to those from India, it involves the digital expressions and transactions of Indian users to be subjected to extra-territorial laws and executive actions. India&amp;rsquo;s recent proposal at the United Nations for institution of a UN Committee on Internet-Related Policies (UN-CIRP) to democratise global Internet governance, is motivated by this deep sense of discomfort with the existing architecture of Internet &lt;code&gt;[12]&lt;/code&gt;. The difficulty experienced by the Government of India in subjecting U.S.-based digital media houses like Google, Facebook and Twitter to force to take down content from their platforms, perhaps, also inform this move to create a global regulatory body for Internet. It is unfortunate that in it domestic practice, the government does not practice the same multi-stakeholder model of regulating media practices that it champions at the international level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;media-technological-challenges:a19ffca54ac01f3aea041ddbfa5c0bb6&#34;&gt;Media-Technological Challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Internet-based media regulation situation, as it stands after a decade since the first Information Technology Act, is a confusing one, even for the government. The rapid amplification and distribution of content though digital social media space remains a genuine cause of anxiety for the government, especially in the context of contents that incite violent reactions and involve false accusations. The anxiety is not only caused by the sheer speed and multi-directionality of sharing such content across the digital media space but also regarding the technical incapacity of the existing Internet architecture. It is important to remember that throughout the history of Internet specific technological modifications, such as distribution of IP addresses according political geographic boundaries, took place due to the demands of governance. The present situation of the media makes usual strategies of blocking online content, like URL-based blocking, difficult to implement as the publishing platform can always post the same content with a different URL. Stopping contents at the very moment of entering the digital media space is also problematic with born digital content, since in that case censorship must be carried out at individual media device level, such as developing word processor softwares that rejects writing of certain words. Further, excessive monitoring and surveillance in popular media platforms such as Twitter and Facebook is likely to force its user groups to shift to other competitive platforms. For example, the limitation of five SMSs per day enforced to stop circulation of messages threatening violence against people from the North-East led to rapid popularity of the messaging software named &amp;lsquo;WhatsApp.&amp;rsquo; This fast moving media software economy makes its policy and directive-based regulation very challenging. On the other hand, the architecture of Internet as a global media system and dominance of certain media platform businesses increasingly play a greater role on the actual working of the media space than the country-specific regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the level of everyday media practices, Internet-based social media interactions are intricately entwined with our daily practices and experiences. Further, the very acts of engaging with this digital social media sphere is substantially different than experiences of prior forms of media. Do the changed media practice and its possibilities also change the engagement with the content/message? Simultaneously, is censorship today produced more technologically than legally or administratively? Does radical visibility of one&amp;rsquo;s social media presence create a situation of continuous participatory surveillance, where the very social media act is premised upon inviting censorship? On the other hand, the government is clearly out of depth in the Internet-based social media spaces. Its efforts of organising press meetings within Twitter and enlisting Digital Volunteers for amplifying the government&amp;rsquo;s voice on the Internet, seems to emerge from an understanding that the Internet can be reformed from within. The government is also aware of the fact that Internet-based social media is finally a business, though not an even or static one. It is simultaneously interested in attracting IT businesses, of both home-grown and imported varieties, and struggling against implementation of laws in a media situation where consumers and distributors and interaction platforms and servers are dispersed across the world. The sovereignty question looms large on the issue of censorship but the question is not simply of territorial reach of legal actions. The idea of sovereign control over Internet-based social media now underlies technological, economical, welfare and diplomatic activities of the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;endnotes:a19ffca54ac01f3aea041ddbfa5c0bb6&#34;&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[01]&lt;/code&gt; Tanna, Ketan. 2004. &lt;em&gt;Internet Censorship in India: Is It Necessary and Does It Work?&lt;/em&gt;. Sarai-CSDS Independent Fellowship. Accessed from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ketan.net/INTERNET_CENSORSHIP_IN_INDIA.html&#34;&gt;http://www.ketan.net/INTERNET_CENSORSHIP_IN_INDIA.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[02]&lt;/code&gt; Ibid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[03]&lt;/code&gt; Ministry of Law, Justice and Company Affairs. 2000. &lt;em&gt;The Information Technology Act, 2000&lt;/em&gt;. The Gazette of India. Friday, June 9. New Delhi. Accessed from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dot.gov.in/Acts/itbill2000.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.dot.gov.in/Acts/itbill2000.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[04]&lt;/code&gt; Tanna. 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[05]&lt;/code&gt; Ibid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[06]&lt;/code&gt; Ministry of Law and Justice. 2009. &lt;em&gt;The Information Technology (Amendment) Act, 2008&lt;/em&gt;. The Gazette of India. Thursday, February 5. New Delhi. Accessed from &lt;a href=&#34;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/downloads/itact2000/it_amendment_act2008.pdf&#34;&gt;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/downloads/itact2000/it_amendment_act2008.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[07]&lt;/code&gt; Prakash, Pranesh. 2011. &amp;lsquo;Short note on IT Amendment Act, 2008&amp;rsquo;. The Centre for Internet and Society. Accessed from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/publications/it-act/short-note-on-amendment-act-2008&#34;&gt;http://cis-india.org/internet-governance/publications/it-act/short-note-on-amendment-act-2008&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[08]&lt;/code&gt; Ministry of Law and Justice. 2011. &lt;em&gt;The Information Technology (Intermediaries Guidelines) Rules, 2011&lt;/em&gt;. The Gazette of India. Monday, 11 April. New Delhi. Accessed from &lt;a href=&#34;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/GSR314E_10511%281%29.pdf&#34;&gt;http://deity.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/GSR314E_10511%281%29.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[09]&lt;/code&gt; Prakash. 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[10]&lt;/code&gt; Prakash, Pranesh. 2012. &amp;lsquo;Invisible Censorship – How India Censors Without Being Seen.&amp;rsquo; Kafila. January 11. Accessed from &lt;a href=&#34;http://kafila.org/2012/01/11/invisible-censorship-how-the-government-censors-without-being-seen-pranesh-prakash&#34;&gt;http://kafila.org/2012/01/11/invisible-censorship-how-the-government-censors-without-being-seen-pranesh-prakash&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[11]&lt;/code&gt; Pahwa, Nikhil. 2013. &amp;lsquo;DoT Issues Orders To Block 78 URLs; 73 URLs With IIPM Content&amp;rsquo;. Medianama. Accessed from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medianama.com/2013/02/223-dot-block-iipm/&#34;&gt;http://www.medianama.com/2013/02/223-dot-block-iipm/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[12]&lt;/code&gt; Singh, Parminder Jeet. 2012. &amp;lsquo;India&amp;rsquo;s Proposal Will Help Take the Web out of U.S. Control.&amp;rsquo; The Hindu. May 17. Accessed from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thehindu.com/todays-paper/tp-opinion/article3427042.ece&#34;&gt;http://www.thehindu.com/todays-paper/tp-opinion/article3427042.ece&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>