<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Asia on Sumandro</title>
    <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/tags/asia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Asia on Sumandro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 20:09:56 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/tags/asia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Civil Society Organisations and Internet Governance in Asia, 2000-2010</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/civil-society-organisations-and-internet-governance-in-asia-2000-2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/civil-society-organisations-and-internet-governance-in-asia-2000-2010/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;this-is-a-book-section-written-for-the-asia-internet-history-third-decade-2001-2010-volume-edited-by-prof-kilnam-chon-the-book-was-published-both-in-print-and-as-an-online-open-access-version-in-december-2015-access-the-book-here-https-sites-google-com-site-internethistoryasia-book3-https-sites-google-com-site-internethistoryasia-book3:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;This is a book section written for the &lt;em&gt;Asia Internet History - Third Decade (2001~2010)&lt;/em&gt; volume edited by Prof. Kilnam Chon. The book was published, both in print and as an online open access version, in December 2015. Access the book here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/internethistoryasia/book3&#34;&gt;https://sites.google.com/site/internethistoryasia/book3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparations-for-the-world-summit-on-the-information-society:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Preparations for the World Summit on the Information Society&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) conferences organized by the United Nations in Geneva (2003) and Tunis (2005) initiated crucial platforms and networks, some temporary and some ongoing, for various non-governmental actors to intensively and periodically take part in discussions of governance of the Internet and various related activities. Many of the civil society organisations taking part in WSIS conferences, as well as various regional and thematic preparatory meetings and seminars, had little prior experience in the topic of Internet governance. They were entering these conversations from various backgrounds, such as local developmental interventions, human and cultural rights activism, freedom and diversity of media, and gender and social justice. Members of such civil society organisations often faced difficult challenges in articulating their experiences, insights, positions, and suggestions in terms of the (then) emerging global discourse of Internet governance that was driven by inter-governmental dynamics of technology and infrastructure governance. At the WSIS, Asian Response Meeting in 2002, Susanna George, (then) Executive Director of Isis International, Manila, succinctly expressed this challenge being faced by the members of civil society organisations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some feminist activists, however, including myself, it has felt like trying to squeeze my concerns into a narrow definition of what gender concerns in ICTs are. I would like it to Cinderella’s ugly sister cutting off her toe to fit into the dainty slipper of gender concerns in ICTs. The development ball, it seems, can only accommodate some elements of what NGO activists, particularly those from the South, are concerned about in relation to new information and communications technologies &lt;code&gt;[George 2002]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seminar, held in Bangkok on 22-24 November 2002, was a crucial early meeting for the representatives from Asian civil society organisations to share and shape their understanding and positions before taking part in global conversations during the following years. The meeting was organized by Bread for All (Switzerland), Communication Rights in the Information Society Campaign (Netherlands), Forum Asia (Thailand), and World Association for Christian Communication (United Kingdom), as a preparatory meeting for the Asia Pacific Regional Conference of WSIS, with 34 organisations from 16 Asian countries taking part. The Final Document produced at the end of this seminar was quite remarkable. It highlighted the simultaneity of Asia as one of the global centres of the information economy and the everyday reality of widespread poverty across Asian countries, and went on to state that the first principle for the emerging global information society should be that &amp;lsquo;[c]ommunication rights are fundamental to democracy and human development&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2002]&lt;/code&gt;. It proposed the following action items for efforts towards a global inclusive information society: 1) strengthen community, 2) ensure access, 3) enhance the creation of appropriate content, 4) invigorate global governance, 5) uphold human rights, 6) extend the public domain, 7) protect and promote cultural and linguistic diversity, and 8) ensure public investment in infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately after this conference, several Asian civil society organisations attended the Asian Civil Society Forum, organized as part of the Conference of Non-governmental Organizations in Consultative Relations with the United Nations (CONGO), held in Bangkok on 9-13 December 2002. Representatives of Dhaka Ahsania Mission (Bangladesh), OneWorld South Asia (India), GLOCOM (Japan), Foundation for Media Alternative (Philippines), Korean Progressive Network – JINBONET (South Korea), Friedrich Naumann Foundation (Singapore), International Federation of University Women (Switzerland), and Forum Asia (Regional) drafted a Joint Statement emphasising that a &amp;lsquo;broad-based participation of civil society, especially from those communities which are excluded, marginalized and severely deprived, is critical in defining and building such a [true communicative, just and peaceful] society [that is being envisaged through initiating the WSIS process.]&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[Aizu 2002]&lt;/code&gt;. In the very next month, the Asia Pacific Regional Conference was held in Tokyo, during 13-15 January 2003, &amp;lsquo;to develop a shared vision and common strategies for the “Information Society” &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003d]&lt;/code&gt;. The conference was attended by representatives from 47 national governments, 22 international organisations, 54 private sector agencies, and 116 civil society organisations across the Asia-Pacific region. The Tokyo Declaration, the final document prepared at the conclusion of the Conference, recognised that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[T]he Information Society must &amp;hellip; facilitate full utilization of information and communication technologies (ICT) at all levels in society and hence enable the sharing of social and economic benefits by all, by means of ubiquitous access to information networks, while preserving diversity and cultural heritage &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003d]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, it highlighted the following priority areas of action: 1) infrastructure development, 2) securing affordable, universal access to ICTs, 3) preserving linguistic and cultural diversity and promoting local content, 4) developing human resources, 5) establishing legal, regulatory and policy frameworks, 6) ensuring balance between intellectual property rights (IPR) and public interest, 7) ensuring the security of ICTs, and 8) fostering partnerships and mobilizing resources. It is not difficult to see how the focus of necessary actions shifted from an emphasis on concerns of community and human rights, need for investments and to bridge digital divides, and the idea of the Internet as a public commons, towards legal and policy mechanisms, multi-partner delivery of services, and intellectual property rights. Several civil society organisations felt sidelined in this conference and decided to issue a joint statement to ensure that their positions are effectively presented. The first two topics mentioned in this document were: 1) &amp;lsquo;[c]ommunication rights should be fully recognized as a fundamental and universal human right to be protected and promoted in the information society,&amp;rsquo; and 2) &amp;lsquo;[t]he participation of civil society in the information society at all levels should be ensured and sustained, from policy planning to implementation, monitoring, and evaluation&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[UNSAJ 2003]&lt;/code&gt;. The joint statement was endorsed by 30 civil society organisations: UDDIPAN (Bangladesh); COMFREL (Cambodia); ETDA (East Timor); The Hong Kong Council of Social Services (Hong Kong); Food India, IT for Change (India); Indonesian Infocom Society (Indonesia); Active Learning, CPSR, Forum for Citizens&amp;rsquo; Television and Media, JTEC, Kyoto Journal, Ritsumeikan University Media Literacy Project, UNSAJ (Japan); Computer Association Nepal, Rural Area Development Programme (Nepal); APC Women&amp;rsquo;s Networking Support Programme, Foundation for Media Alternatives, ISIS International (Philippines); Citizens&amp;rsquo; Action Network, Korean Progressive Network – Jinbonet, Labor News Production, ZAK (South Korea); e-Pacificka Consulting (Samoa); National University of Singapore (Singapore); Public Television Service, Taiwan Association for Human Rights (Taiwan); Asian-South Pacific Bureau for Adult Education, Forum Asia, and TVE Asia Pacific (Regional) &lt;code&gt;[UNSAJ 2003]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;participation-in-the-wsis-process:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Participation in the WSIS Process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first WSIS conference was held in Geneva on 10-12 December 2003. Through the processes of organizing this conference, and the second conference in Tunis in 2005, the United Nations operationalized a much-appreciated mandate for facilitating wider participation of non-governmental actors from the private sector, civil society, academia, and media, along with governmental organisations, in international policy-setting processes. At the first meeting of the WSIS Preparatory Committee (PrepCom-1) in Geneva, during 1-5 July 2002, civil society organisations argued that they should be allowed to co-shape the key subjects of discussion during the first conference (2003). There was already an Inter-Governmental Subcommittee on Contents and Themes, but no equivalent platform for the civil society organisations was available. With the approval of the Civil Society Plenary (CSP), the Civil Society Subcommittee on Content and Themes (WSIS-SCT) was instituted during PrepCom-1 &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003b]&lt;/code&gt;. At the second WSIS Preparatory Committee meeting (PrepCom-2), held in Geneva during 17-28 February 2003, the WSIS-SCT produced a summary of the views of its members titled &amp;lsquo;Vision and Principles of Information and Communication Societies,&amp;rsquo; as well as a one-page brief titled &amp;lsquo;Seven Musts: Priority Principles Proposed by Civil Society&amp;rsquo; to be used for lobbying purposes &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003b]&lt;/code&gt;. This brief mentioned seven key principles of Internet governance identified by the civil society organisations taking part in the WSIS process: (1) sustainable development, (2) democratic governance, (3) literacy, education, and research, (4) human rights, (5) global knowledge commons, (6) cultural and linguistic diversity, and (7) information security &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asian civil society organisations that took part in the PrepCom-2 meeting included United Nations Association of China (China); CASP - Centre for Adivasee Studies and Peace, C2N - Community Communications Network (India); ICSORC - Iranian Civil Society Organizations Resource Center (Iran); GAWF - General Arab Women Federation (Iraq); Daisy Consortium, GLOCOM - Center for Global Communications (Japan); Association for Progressive Communication, Global Knowledge Partnership (Malaysia); Pakistan Christian Peace Foundation (Pakistan); WFEO - World Federation of Engineering Organization (Palestine); Asian South Pacific Bureau of Adult Education, Foundation for Media Alternatives, ISIS International – Manila (Philippines); Korean Progressive Network - Jinbonet (South Korea); IIROSA - International Islamic Relief Organization (Saudi Arabia); and Taking IT Global (India, Indonesia, Malaysia, Philippines, and Turkey) &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these efforts led to the development of the Civil Society Declaration to the World Summit on the Information Society, which was prepared and published by the Civil Society Plenary at the Geneva conference, on 8 December 2003. The Declaration was titled &amp;lsquo;Shaping Information Societies for Human Needs&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003c]&lt;/code&gt;. The Asian civil society organization that took part in the Geneva conference were BFES - Bangladesh Friendship Education Society, Drik, ICTDPB - Information &amp;amp; Communication Technology Development Program, Proshika - A Center for Human Development (Bangladesh); China Society for Promotion of the Guangcai Programme, Chinese People&amp;rsquo;s Association for Friendship with Foreign Countries, United Nations Association of China (China); The Hong Kong Council of Social Service (Hong Kong); CASP - Centre for Adivasee Studies and Peace, Childline India Foundation / Child Helpline International, DAWN - Development Alternatives with Women for a New Era (India); Communication Network of Women&amp;rsquo;s NGOs in Iran, Green Front of Iran, ICTRC - Iranian Civil Society Organizations Training and Research Center, Islamic Women&amp;rsquo;s Institute of Iran, Institute for Women&amp;rsquo;s Studies and Research, Organization for Defending Victims of Violence (Iran); ILAM - Center for Arab Palestinians in Israel (Israel); Citizen Digital Solutions, Forum for Citizens&amp;rsquo; Television and Media, GLOCOM - Center for Global Communications, JCAFE - Japan Computer Access for Empowerment, Soka Gakkai International (Japan); LAD-Nepal - Literary Academy for Dalit of Nepal (Nepal); Asia-Pacific Broadcasting Union, Global Knowledge Partnership (Malaysia); PAK Educational Society / Pakistan Development Network, SMEDA - Small &amp;amp; Medium Enterprize Development Authority (Pakistan); Palestine IT Association of Companies (Palestine); Isis International – Manila, Ugnayan ng Kababaihan sa Pulitika / Philippine Women&amp;rsquo;s Network in Politics and Governance (Philippines); Citizen&amp;rsquo;s Alliance for Consumer Protection of Korea, Korean Civil Society Network for WSIS (South Korea); Youth Challenge (Singapore); Association for Progressive Communications (India and Philippines), CITYNET - Regional Network of Local Authorities for the Management of Human Settlements (India. Mongolia, and Philippines), Taking IT Global (India and Philippines) &lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003b]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the preparatory meetings and consultations towards the second WSIS conference advanced during the next year, civil society organizations from Asia attempted to engage more directly with the global Internet governance processes on one hand, and the national Internet and ICT policy situations on the other. Writing about their encounters at and before the second Preparatory Committee meeting for the Tunis conference, held in Geneva during 17-25 February 2005, Anita Gurumurthy and Parminder Jeet Singh made several early observations that have continued to resonate with the experiences of Asian civil society organizations throughout the decade &lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2005]&lt;/code&gt;. First, they indicated that the government agencies present in the dialogs tend to take diverging positions in international events and domestic contexts. Second, there was a marked absence of formal and informal discussions between the governmental and the civil society representatives of the same country present at the meeting. The government agencies were clearly disinterested in involving civil society organizations in the process. Third, the civil society actors present at the meeting were mostly from the ICT for Development sector, while the organizations working in more &amp;lsquo;traditional&amp;rsquo; sectors – such as education, health, governance reform, etc. – remained absent from the conversations. This is especially problematic in the case of such developing countries where there does not exist strategic linkages between civil society organizations focusing on topics of technologized developmental interventions, and those involved in more &amp;lsquo;traditional&amp;rsquo; development practices. Rekha Jain, in a separate report on the Indian experience of participating in the WSIS process, reiterated some of these points &lt;code&gt;[Jain 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. She highlighted that &amp;lsquo;[w]hile the Secretary, [Department of Telecommunications, Government of India] was involved in (PrepCom-1) drafting the initial processes for involvement of NGOs, at the national level, this mechanism was not translated into a process for involving the civil society or media.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general lack of interest of national governments, especially in Asian countries, to engage with civil society organizations on matters of policies and projects in Internet governance and ICTs for development &lt;code&gt;[Souter 2007]&lt;/code&gt;, further encouraged these organization to utilize the global discussion space opened up by the WSIS process to drive the agendas of democratization of Internet governance processes, protection of human rights, and advancement of social justice. The second WSIS conference held in Tunis during 16-18 November 2005, however, did not end on a positive note for the civil society organizations as a whole. The sentiment is aptly captured in the title of the Civil Society Statement issued after the Tunis Conference: &amp;lsquo;Much more could have been achieved&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2005b]&lt;/code&gt;. Apart from producing this very important critical response to the WSIS process, within a month of its conclusion, civil society organizations played a key role in shaping one of the more longer-term impacts of the process – the establishment of the Internet Governance Forum (IGF). After the publication of the Report of the Working Group on Internet Governance &lt;code&gt;[Desai 2005]&lt;/code&gt; in June 2005, the Center for Global Communications (GLOCOM), Japan, acting on behalf of the Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus, came forward with public support for &amp;lsquo;the establishment of a new forum to address the broad agenda of Internet governance issues, provided it is truly global, inclusive, and multi-stakeholder in composition allowing all stakeholders from all sectors to participate as equal peers&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2005]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;asian-civil-society-organizations-at-the-igfs:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Asian Civil Society Organizations at the IGFs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, the WSIS Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus was reformed and established as a permanent &amp;lsquo;forum for discussion, advocacy, action, and for representation of civil society contributions in Internet governance processes&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[Civil 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. Representatives from Asian civil society organizations have consistently played critical roles in the functionings of this Caucus. Youn Jung Park of the Department of Technology and Society, SUNY Korea, co-founded and co-coordinated the original caucus in 2003. Adam Peake of the Center for Global Communications (GLOCOM), International University of Japan, was co-coordinator of the original caucus from 2003 to 2006. Parminder Jeet Sing of IT for Change, India, was elected as one of the co-coordinators of the newly reformed caucus in 2006, and held the position till 2008. Izumi Aizu of the Institute for HyperNetwork Society and the Institute for InfoSocinomics, Tama University, served as the co-coordinator of the caucus during 2010-2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first IGF, held in Athens during 30 October - 2 November 2006, saw participation from only a few Asian civil society organizations, mostly from Bangladesh and Japan &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. The second Internet Governance Forum in Rio de Janeiro, during 12-15 November 2007, had a larger representation from Asian civil society organizations: Bangladesh NGOs Network for Radio and Communication, BFES - Bangladesh Friendship Education Society, VOICE – Voices for Interactive Choice and Empowerment (Bangladesh); China Association for Science and Technology, Internet Society of China (China); University of Hong Kong (Hong Kong); Alternative Law Forum (via Association for Progressive Communications - Women&amp;rsquo;s Networking Support Programme), Indian Institute of Technology in Delhi, IT for Change (India); GLOCOM, Kumon Center, Tama University (Japan); Sustainable Development Networking Programme (Jordan); Kuwait Information Technology Society (Kuwait); Association of Computer Engineers – Nepal, Rural Area Development Programme, Nepal Rural Information Technology Development Society (Nepal); Bytesforall – APC / Pakistan, Pakistan Christian Peace Foundation (Pakistan); Foundation for Media Alternatives, Philippine Resources for Sustainable Development Inc. (Philippines); and LIRNEasia (Sri Lanka). At the Open IGF Consultations in Geneva, on 26 February 2008, the Internet Governance Caucus made two significant submissions: 1) that, although structuring the IGF sessions in Athens and Rio de Janeiro around the large themes of access, openness, diversity, and security have been useful to open up the multi-stakeholder dialogues, it is necessary to begin focused discussions of specific public policy issues to take the IGF process forward &lt;code&gt;[Civil 2008]&lt;/code&gt;, and 2) that the Multi-Stakeholder Advisory Group (MAG), which drives the IGF process and events, should be made more proactive and transparent, and expanded in size so as to better include the different stakeholder groups who may self-identify their representatives for the MAG &lt;code&gt;[Civil 2008b]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one hand, the IGF Hyderabad, held during 3-6 December 2008, experienced a decline in the percentage of participants from civil society organizations and a rather modest increase in the percentage of participants from Asian countries, especially since this was the first major international Internet governance summit held in an Asian country. See Table 6-2 for further information. On the other hand, the Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus succeeded to bring forth the term &amp;lsquo;enhanced cooperation,&amp;rsquo; as mentioned in the Tunis Agenda, to be addressed and discussed in one of the main sessions of the Forum &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2008]&lt;/code&gt;. The next IGF held in Sharm El Sheikh, during 15-18 November 2009, saw a further decline of participation from both the representatives of civil society organizations and attendees from Asian countries. See Table 6-2 for further information. The fall in participation reflects a feeling among civil society organizations that the IGF process is not allowing specific and effective dialogues about critical policy and governance concerns around Internet and digital media. In this context, Youn Jung Park made the following statement in the Stock Taking session of the summit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a co-founder of WSIS Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus in 2003, I would like to remind you &amp;hellip; [that] Internet Governance Forum was created as a compromise between those who supported the status quo Internet governance institution under one nation&amp;rsquo;s status provision, and those who requested for more balanced roles for governments under international supervision of the Internet. While IGF has achieved a great success of diluting of such political tension between those who have different views of how to institutionalize Internet governance, ironically Internet governance forum became a forum without governance&amp;hellip; [We] have to admit [that] IGF failed to deliver another mandate of the U.N. WSIS: Continuing discussion of how to design Internet governance institutions&amp;hellip; The current IGF continues to function as knowledge transfer of ICANN&amp;rsquo;s values to other stakeholders, while those who want to discuss and negotiate on how to design Internet governance institutions should have another platform for that specific U.N. WSIS mandate &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2009]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Asia Pacific regional Internet Governance Forum (APrIGF) was held in Hong Kong on 14-16 June 2010. The organising committee included three civil society / academic organizations – Center for Global Communications (GLOCOM), Internet Society Hong Kong, and National University of Singapore – and three independent experts – Kuo-Wei Wu (Taiwan), Norbert Klein (Cambodia), and Zahid Jamil (Pakistan). Though the forum was largely attended by governmental and private sector participants, several representatives from Asian civil societies and academic organizations spoke at the main sessions: Ang Peng Hwa (Singapore Internet Research Centre, Nanyang Technological University), Charles Mok (Internet Society Hong Kong), Christine Loh (Civic Exchange), Chong Chan Yau (Hong Kong Blind Union), Clarence Tsang (Christian Action), Ilya Eric Lee (Taiwan E-Learning and Digital Archives Program, and Research Center for Information Technology Innovation), Izumi Aizu (Institute for HyperNetwork Society, and Institute for InfoSocinomics, Kumon Center, Tama University), Oliver &amp;lsquo;Blogie&amp;rsquo; Robillo (Mindanao Bloggers Community), Parminder Jeet Singh (IT for Change), Priscilla Lui (Against Child Abuse in Hong Kong), Tan Tin Wee (Centre for Internet Research, National University of Singapore), and Yap Swee Seng (Asian Forum for Human Rights and Development). As Ang Peng Hwa noted at the beginning of the summit, its key objective was to provide a formal space for various stakeholders from the Asia-Pacific region to discuss and provide inputs to the IGF process &lt;code&gt;[APrIGF 2010]&lt;/code&gt;. The regional forum was successful in enabling newer civil society entrants from the Asia-Pacific region to familiarize themselves with the IGF process, and to contribute to it. For example, IGF Vilnius, held during 14-17 September 2010, was the first IGF summit attended by Oliver &amp;lsquo;Blogie&amp;rsquo; Robillo, where he presented the recommendations from Southeast Asian civil society organizations. In his speech, he emphasized the following topics: 1) openness and freedom of expression are the basis of democracy, and state-driven censorship of the Internet in the region is an immediate threat to such global rights; 2) coordinated international efforts need to address and resolve not only global digital divides, but also the divides at regional, national, and sub-nationals scales; 3) the right to privacy is an integral part of cybersecurity, as well as a necessary condition for exercising human rights; 4) global Internet governance efforts must ensure that national governments do not control or restrict abilities of citizens to express through digital means, and this should be aligned with the universal human rights agenda, and 5) even after 5 years of the IGF process, a wider participation of civil society organizations, especially from the Asia-Pacific regions, remains an unachieved goal, which can only be achieved if specific resources are allocated and processes are implemented &lt;code&gt;[IGF 2010]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;internet-censorship-and-civil-society-responses:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Internet Censorship and Civil Society Responses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the decade of 2001-2010, censorship of the Internet and restriction of digital expression remained crucial Internet rights concerns across the world and especially in Asian countries. One of the earliest global reports on the topic was brought out by Reporters without Borders. In 2006, they published a list of sixteen countries marked as &amp;lsquo;Internet Enemies,&amp;rsquo; out of which eleven were from Asia: China, Iran, Maldives, Myanmar, Nepal, North Korea, Saudi Arabia, Syria, Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan, and Vietnam &lt;code&gt;[Reporters 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. The list was updated in 2007, and three of these countries – Libya, Maldives, and Nepal – were removed. The unique contradictions of the Internet and ICTs landscape of the Asian region were insightfully highlighted in the 2006-07 report on Internet censorship by OpenNet Initiative:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the most and least connected countries in the world are located in Asia: Japan, South Korea, and Singapore all have Internet penetration rates of over 65 percent, while Afghanistan, Myanmar, and Nepal remain three of thirty countries with less than 1 percent of its citizens online. Among the countries in the world with the most restricted access, North Korea allows only a small community of elites and foreigners online. Most users must rely on Chinese service providers for connectivity while the limited number North Korean–sponsored Web sites are hosted abroad&amp;hellip; [T]hough India’s Internet community is the fifth largest in the world, users amounted to only about 4 percent of the country’s population in 2005. Afghanistan, Myanmar, and Nepal are among the world’s least-developed countries. Despite the constraints on resources and serious developmental and political challenges, however, citizens are showing steadily increasing demand for Internet services such as Voice over Internet Protocol (VoIP), blogging, and chat &lt;code&gt;[Wang 2007]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report further described the strategy used by various Asian governments of &amp;lsquo;delegation of policing and monitoring responsibilities to ISPs, content providers, private corporations, and users themselves&amp;rsquo; &lt;code&gt;[Wang 2007]&lt;/code&gt;. This is an effective method of enforcing self-surveillance and self-censorship under the threats of loss of commercial license, denial of services, and even criminal liability. Defamation suits and related civil and criminal liability have also been used by several Asian governments to silence influential critics and protesters. Direct technical filtering of Internet traffic (especially incoming traffic) and blocking of URLS via government directives sent to Internet Service Providers (ISPs) have been common practices in several Asian countries &lt;code&gt;[Wang 2007]&lt;/code&gt;. Expectedly, such experiences of oppression led to widespread campaigns by the Asian civil society organizations, as can be surmised from the submission mentioned above by Oliver &amp;lsquo;Blogie&amp;rsquo; Robillo at IGF Vilnius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among Asian countries, the comprehensive technologies of censorship developed and deployed by China have been studied extensively. The Golden Shield Project was initiated by the Ministry of Public Security of China in 1998 to undertake blanket blocking of incoming Internet traffic based on specific URLs and terms. Evidence of the project being operationalised became available in 2003 &lt;code&gt;[Garden 2004]&lt;/code&gt;. Censorship of Internet in China, however, has not only been implemented using such macro-scale technological systems, non-automated mechanisms have also been used at the ground level. In 2003, it was made mandatory for all residents of Lhasa, Tibet, to use a specific combination of user name and password, which was directly linked to their names and address, to access the Internet. An Internet ID card was issued by the government to implement this &lt;code&gt;[International 2004]&lt;/code&gt;. Tibet Action Institute has been a key civil society organization at the forefront of the cyber offense of the Chinese government. A recent documentary by the institute, titled &amp;lsquo;Tibet: Frontline of the New Cyberwar,&amp;rsquo; narrates how it has worked closely with Citizen Lab, Munk School of Global Affairs, University of Toronto, to identify, trace, and resist malware and other cyber-attacks experienced by the civil society actors and websites in favor of independence of Tibet &lt;code&gt;[Tibet 2015]&lt;/code&gt;. The Tibetan case is not an exceptional one. Digital security training has emerged as an important aspect of the life of civil society organizations during the decade. Asian organizations such as Bytes for All (Pakistan) and Myanmar ICT for Development Organization (Myanmar), as well as international organizations including Front Line Defenders and Citizen Lab have educated and supported civil society activities much beyond the Internet governance sphere with tools and techniques for effectively using digital channels of communications, and defending themselves against cyber-threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The combination of traditional forms of civil society mobilizations and digital techniques has often been used to resist attempts by Asian governments to control the online communication space. In Pakistan, as the government took harsh steps towards control of both traditional and online media in 2007-2008, Huma Yusuf extensively studied the emergence of hybrid media strategies among citizen journaalists and civil society activits, using both old media channels such as newspapers and new media channels like blogs and video sharing platforms &lt;code&gt;[Yusuf 2009]&lt;/code&gt;. She has carefully traced how possibilities of new forms of information and media sharing enabled by the Internet were initially identified and implemented by citizen journalists and student activists, which was quickly learned and re-deployed by more formal organisations, such as print and electronic news companies, and civil society organizations like those involved in election monitoring. Malaysia also experienced fast-accelerating conflict between the government and a civil society during 2007-2010, as the former started intervening directly into censoring blogs and newspaper websites. On one hand, the government took legal actions against critical bloggers, either directly or indirectly, and on the other it instructed ISPs to block &amp;lsquo;offensive content.&amp;rsquo; It also borrowed the &amp;lsquo;Singapore-model&amp;rsquo; to mandate registration of bloggers with government authorities, if they are identified as writing on socio-political topics. Civil society actors responded to these oppressive steps by setting up a new blog dedicated to coverage of the defamation cases (filed against prominent bloggers), and publicly sharing instructions for circumvention of the blocks imposed by ISPs. The National Alliance of Bloggers was soon formed, which organized the Blogs and Digital Democracy Forum on 3 October 2007 [Thien 2011]. Similarly, the Bloggers Against Censorship campaign took shape in India in 2006 as the government first directed ISPs to block specific blogs hosted on Blogspot, TypePad, and Yahoo! Geocities, and then sought complete blocking of Yahoo! Geocities as the ISPs failed to block specific sub-domains of the platform &lt;code&gt;[Bloggers 2006]&lt;/code&gt;. Learning from this experience, the following year the Indian government decided to work directly with Orkut to take down &amp;lsquo;defamatory content&amp;rsquo; about a politician &lt;code&gt;[Economic 2007]&lt;/code&gt;. This is common for other Asian governments too, as they have continued to develop more legally binding and technically sophisticated measures to monitor and control online expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &amp;lsquo;Internet Enemies Report 2012,&amp;rsquo; Reporters without Borders listed 12 countries as &amp;lsquo;enemies of the Internet,&amp;rsquo; out of which 10 were from Asia – Bahrain, China, Iran, Myanmar, North Korea, Saudi Arabia, Syria, Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan, and Vietnam – and it named 14 countries that were conducting surveillance on its citizens, out of which 7 were from Asia – India, Kazakhstan, Malaysia, South Korea, Sri Lanka, Thailand, and United Arab Emirates &lt;code&gt;[Reporters 2012]&lt;/code&gt;. At the APrIGF held in Tokyo during 18-20 July 2012, a group of delegates from civil society organizations working in the South-East Asian region issued a joint statement with a clear call for global action on the shrinking space for freedom of (digital) expression in the region &lt;code&gt;[Thai 2012]&lt;/code&gt;. They specifically noted the following national acts as examples of the legislative mechanisms being used by different Asian governments to criminalize online speech and/or to harass public dissenters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burma – The 2004 Electronic Transactions Act&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cambodia – The 2012 Draft Cyber-Law, the 1995 Press Law, and the 2010 Penal Code&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malaysia – The 2012 Amendment to the Evidence Act and the 2011 Computing Professionals Bill&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indonesia – The 2008 Law on Information and Electronic Transaction and the 2008 Law on Pornography&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Philippines – The 2012 Data Privacy Act&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thailand – The 2007 Computer Crimes Act, the Article 112 of the Penal Code, and the 2004 Special Case Investigation Act&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vietnam – The 1999 Penal Code, the 2004 Publishing Law, the 2000 State Secrets Protection Ordinance, and the 2012 Draft Decree on Internet Management. (Ibid.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statement was co-signed by Thai Netizen Network, Thai Media Policy Centre, The Institute for Policy Research and Advocacy (ELSAM), Southeast Asian Press Alliance (SEAPA), Southeast Asian Centre for e-Media (SEACeM), Victorius (Ndaru) Eps, Community Legal Education Center (CLEC), Sovathana (Nana) Neang, and Asian Forum for Human Rights and Development (Forum Asia), and was endorsed by ICT Watch (Indonesian ICT Partnership Association).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;annexe-tables:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Annexe – Tables&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;table-1-participation-from-asian-countries-and-of-representatives-from-asian-civil-society-organisations-in-igfs-2006-2010:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Table 1: Participation from Asian Countries and of representatives from Asian civil society organisations in IGFs, 2006-2010&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Event&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Participants from Asian Countries&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Participants from Civil Society Organizations&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IGF Athens 2006&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;29%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IGF Rio de Janeiro 2007&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;32%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IGF Hyderabad 2008&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;56% from India, and 15% from other Asian countries&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;25%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IGF Sharm El Sheikh 2009&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19%&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IGF Vilnius 2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not Available&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not Available&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: Reports available on &lt;a href=&#34;http://igf.wgig.org/cms&#34;&gt;Internet Governance Forum website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;table-2-internet-society-chapters-in-asia:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Table 2: Internet Society Chapters in Asia&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Chapter&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Year of Establishment&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;URL&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Afghanistan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;In formation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not available&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bahrain&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bis.org.bh/&#34;&gt;http://www.bis.org.bh/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Bangladesh&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.org.bd/dhaka/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.org.bd/dhaka/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hong Kong&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2005&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.hk/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.hk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;India (Bangalore)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocbangalore.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocbangalore.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;India (Chennai)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocindiachennai.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocindiachennai.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;India (Delhi)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2002. Rejuvenated in 2008.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocdelhi.in/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocdelhi.in/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;India (Kolkata)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2009&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://isockolkata.in/&#34;&gt;http://isockolkata.in/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;India (Trivandrum)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2015&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not available&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Indonesia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.or.id/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.or.id/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Israel&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1995&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.org.il/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.org.il/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Japan&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1994&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.jp/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.jp/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lebanon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.org.lb/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.org.lb/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Malaysia&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.my/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.my/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nepal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.internetsociety.org.np/&#34;&gt;http://www.internetsociety.org.np/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pakistan (Islamabad)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocibd.org.pk/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocibd.org.pk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Palestine&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2002&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.ps/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.ps/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philippines&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1999. Rejuvenated in 2009.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/isoc.ph/&#34;&gt;https://www.facebook.com/isoc.ph/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Qatar&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.qa/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.qa/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Republic of Korea&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2014&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Not available&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Singapore&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://isoc.sg/&#34;&gt;http://isoc.sg/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sri Lanka&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.lk/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.lk/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Taipei&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1996&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc.org.tw/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc.org.tw/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Thailand&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1996&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isoc-th.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.isoc-th.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;United Arab Emirates&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.isocuae.com/&#34;&gt;http://www.isocuae.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yemen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2013&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://isoc.ye/&#34;&gt;http://isoc.ye/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source: Details of chapters available on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.internetsociety.org/&#34;&gt;Internet Society website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;acknowledgment:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to Anita Gurumurthy and Parminder Jeet Singh for their generous sharing of information and insights. Raman Jit Singh Cheema, Pranesh Prakash, and Sunil Abraham have also provided crucial suggestions. Extensive background research by P.P. Sneha has significantly enriched my efforts. The Wayback Machine of the Internet Archive deserves a very special thanks. Last but not the least, I am thankful to Kilnam Chon for this wonderful opportunity and his patient support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reference:74194dbe5ca94fbec8ae596294b28d60&#34;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Aizu 2002]&lt;/code&gt; Aizu, Izumi et al. 2002. Joint Statement from Asia Civil Society Forum Participants on World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS). December 13. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsisasia.org/wsis-acsf2002/wsis-acsfdec13f.doc&#34;&gt;http://www.wsisasia.org/wsis-acsf2002/wsis-acsfdec13f.doc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[APrIGF 2010]&lt;/code&gt; Asia Pacific Regional Internet Governance Forum (APrIGF). 2010. APrIGF Roundtable – June 15th, 2010: Session 1 – Welcome Remarks and Introduction – Real Time Transcript. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://2010.rigf.asia/aprigf-roundtable-june-15th-2010-session-1/&#34;&gt;http://2010.rigf.asia/aprigf-roundtable-june-15th-2010-session-1/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Bloggers 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Bloggers Collective Group. 2006. Bloggers Against Censorship. Last updated on April 30, 2009‎. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://censorship.wikia.com/wiki/Bloggers_Against_Censorship&#34;&gt;http://censorship.wikia.com/wiki/Bloggers_Against_Censorship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Civil 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus. 2006. Internet Governance Caucus Charter. October 14. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC-charter_final-061014.html&#34;&gt;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC-charter_final-061014.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Civil 2008]&lt;/code&gt; Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus. 2008. Inputs for the Open IGF Consultation, Geneva, 26th February, 2008 – Statement II: Main Session Themes for IGF, Hyderabad. February 26. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC%20-%20Main%20themes%20for%20IGF%20Hyd.pdf&#34;&gt;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC%20-%20Main%20themes%20for%20IGF%20Hyd.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Civil 2008b]&lt;/code&gt; Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus. 2008. Inputs for the Open IGF Consultation, Geneva, 26th February, 2008 – Statement III: Renewal / Restructuring of Multi-stakeholder Advisory Group. February 26. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC%20-%20MAG%20Rotation.pdf&#34;&gt;http://igcaucus.org/old/IGC%20-%20MAG%20Rotation.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Desai 2005]&lt;/code&gt; Desai, Nitin, et al. 2005. Report of the Working Group on Internet Governance. United June. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wgig.org/docs/WGIGREPORT.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.wgig.org/docs/WGIGREPORT.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Economic 2007]&lt;/code&gt; The Economic Times. 2007. Orkut&amp;rsquo;s Tell-All Pact with Cops. May 01. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2007-05-01/news/28459689_1_orkut-ip-addresses-google-spokesperson&#34;&gt;http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2007-05-01/news/28459689_1_orkut-ip-addresses-google-spokesperson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Garden 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Garden Networks for Freedom of Information. 2004. Breaking through the “Golden Shield.” Open Society Institute. November 01. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.opensocietyfoundations.org/sites/default/files/china-internet-censorship-20041101.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.opensocietyfoundations.org/sites/default/files/china-internet-censorship-20041101.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[George 2002]&lt;/code&gt; George, Susanna. 2002. Women and New Information and Communications Technologies: The Promise of Empowerment. Presented at The World Summit on the Information Society: An Asian Response Meeting, November 22-24. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsisasia.org/materials/susanna.doc/&#34;&gt;http://www.wsisasia.org/materials/susanna.doc/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gurumurthy 2005]&lt;/code&gt; Gurumurthy, Anita, &amp;amp; Parminder Jeet Singh. 2005. WSIS PrepCom 2: A South Asian Perspective. Association for Progressive Communications. April 01. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apc.org/en/news/hr/world/wsis-prepcom-2-south-asian-perspective&#34;&gt;https://www.apc.org/en/news/hr/world/wsis-prepcom-2-south-asian-perspective&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum (IGF). 2006. Athens 2006 – List of Participants. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intgovforum.org/PLP.html&#34;&gt;http://www.intgovforum.org/PLP.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2008]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum (IGF). 2008. Arrangements for Internet Governance, Global and National/Regional. IGF Hyderabad, India. December 5. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20130621205004/http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/hyderabad_prog/AfIGGN.html&#34;&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20130621205004/http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/hyderabad_prog/AfIGGN.html&lt;/a&gt; [Original URL: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/hyderabad_prog/AfIGGN.html&#34;&gt;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/hyderabad_prog/AfIGGN.html&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum (IGF). 2009. Taking Stock and Looking Forward – On the Desirability of the Continuation of the Forum, Part II. IGF Sharm El Sheikh, Egypt. November 18. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/2009/sharm_el_Sheikh/Transcripts/Sharm%20El%20Sheikh%2018%20November%202009%20Stock%20Taking%20II.txt&#34;&gt;http://www.intgovforum.org/cms/2009/sharm_el_Sheikh/Transcripts/Sharm%20El%20Sheikh%2018%20November%202009%20Stock%20Taking%20II.txt&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[IGF 2010]&lt;/code&gt; Internet Governance Forum (IGF). 2010. Taking Stock of Internet Governance and the Way Forward. IGF Vilnius, Lithuania. September 17. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://igf.wgig.org/cms/component/content/article/102-transcripts2010/687-taking-stock&#34;&gt;http://igf.wgig.org/cms/component/content/article/102-transcripts2010/687-taking-stock&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[International 2004]&lt;/code&gt; International Campaign for Tibet. 2004. Chinese Authorities Institute Internet ID Card System in Tibet for Online Surveillance. April 30. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.savetibet.org/chinese-authorities-institute-internet-id-card-system-in-tibet-for-online-surveillance/&#34;&gt;http://www.savetibet.org/chinese-authorities-institute-internet-id-card-system-in-tibet-for-online-surveillance/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003]&lt;/code&gt; International Telecommunication Union (ITU). 2003. PrepCom-2 / 17-28 February 2003 – Final List of Participants. February 28. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/participation/prepcom2/prepcom2-cl.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/participation/prepcom2/prepcom2-cl.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[ITU 2003b]&lt;/code&gt; International Telecommunication Union (ITU). 2003. Geneva Phase of the WSIS: List of Participants. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/summit_participants.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/summit_participants.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Jain 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Jain, Rekha. 2006. Participation of Developing Countries in the World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) Process: India Case Study. Association for Progressive Communications. March. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://rights.apc.org/documents/wsis_india.pdf&#34;&gt;http://rights.apc.org/documents/wsis_india.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Reporters 2006]&lt;/code&gt; Reporters without Borders. 2006. List of the 13 Internet Enemies. Last updated on August 28, 2007. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.rsf.org/list-of-the-13-internet-enemies-07-11-2006,19603&#34;&gt;http://en.rsf.org/list-of-the-13-internet-enemies-07-11-2006,19603&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Reporters 2012]&lt;/code&gt; Reporters without Borders. 2012. Internet Enemies Report 2012. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.rsf.org/IMG/pdf/rapport-internet2012_ang.pdf&#34;&gt;http://en.rsf.org/IMG/pdf/rapport-internet2012_ang.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Souter 2007]&lt;/code&gt; Souter, David. 2007. WSIS and Civil Society. In: Whose Summit? Whose Information Society? Developing Countries and Civil Society at the World Summit on the Information Society. With additional research by Abiodun Jagun. Association for Progressive Communications. Pp. 72-89. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://rights.apc.org/documents/whose_summit_EN.pdf&#34;&gt;http://rights.apc.org/documents/whose_summit_EN.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Thai 2012]&lt;/code&gt; Thai Netizen Network et al. 2012. Southeast Asian Civil Society Groups Highlight Increasing Rights Violations Online, Call for Improvements to Internet Governance Processes in the Region. Statement of Civil Society Delegates from Southeast Asia to 2012 Asia-Pacific Regional Internet Governance Forum (APrIGF). July 31. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;https://freedomhouse.org/sites/default/files/AprIGF-Joint%20Statement-FINAL.pdf&#34;&gt;https://freedomhouse.org/sites/default/files/AprIGF-Joint%20Statement-FINAL.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Thien 2011]&lt;/code&gt; Thien, Vee Vian. 2011. The Struggle for Digital Freedom of Speech: The Malaysian Sociopolitical Blogosphere’s Experience. In: Ronald Deibert et al. (eds.) Access Contested. OpenNet Initiative. Pp. 43-63. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://access.opennet.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/accesscontested-chapter-03.pdf&#34;&gt;http://access.opennet.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/accesscontested-chapter-03.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Tibet 2015]&lt;/code&gt; Tibet Action Institute. 2015. Tibet: Frontline of the New Cyberwar. YouTube. January 27. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yE3AQqbGVkk&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yE3AQqbGVkk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[UNSAJ 2003]&lt;/code&gt; UNSAJ et al. 2003. Civil Society Observations and Response to the Tokyo Declaration. Asia-Pacific Regional Conference on the World Summit on the Information Society. January 15. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsisasia.org/wsis-tokyo/tokyo-statement.html&#34;&gt;http://www.wsisasia.org/wsis-tokyo/tokyo-statement.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Wang 2007]&lt;/code&gt; Wang, Stephanie. 2007. Internet Filtering in Asia in 2006-2007. OpenNet Initiative. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://opennet.net/studies/asia2007&#34;&gt;https://opennet.net/studies/asia2007&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2002]&lt;/code&gt; The World Summit on the Information Society: An Asian Response. 2002. Final Document. Accessed on July 08, 2015 from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsisasia.org/materials/finalversion.doc&#34;&gt;http://www.wsisasia.org/materials/finalversion.doc&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Civil Society Subcommittee on Content and Themes. 2003. “Seven Musts”: Priority Principles Proposed by Civil Society. February 25. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.movimientos.org/es/foro_comunicacion/show_text.php3%3Fkey%3D1484&#34;&gt;http://www.movimientos.org/es/foro_comunicacion/show_text.php3%3Fkey%3D1484&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003b]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Civil Society Subcommittee on Content and Themes. 2003. Final Report on Prepcom-2 Activities of the Civil Society on Content and Themes. March 27. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/pcip/misc/cs_sct.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/pcip/misc/cs_sct.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003c]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Civil Society Plenary. 2003. “Shaping Information Societies for Human Needs” – Civil Society Declaration to the World Summit on the Information Society. December 8. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/civil-society-declaration.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/wsis/docs/geneva/civil-society-declaration.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2003d]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Executive Secretariat. 2003. Report of the Asia-Pacific Regional Conference for WSIS (Tokyo, 13-15 January 2003). WSIS. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.itu.int/dms_pub/itu-s/md/03/wsispc2/doc/S03-WSISPC2-DOC-0006!!PDF-E.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.itu.int/dms_pub/itu-s/md/03/wsispc2/doc/S03-WSISPC2-DOC-0006!!PDF-E.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2005]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus. 2005. Initial Reactions to the WGIG Report. Contribution from GLOCOM on behalf of the WSIS Civil Society Internet Governance Caucus. July 19. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from www.itu.int/wsis/%20docs2/pc3/contributions/co23.doc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[WSIS 2005b]&lt;/code&gt; WSIS Civil Society Plenary. 2005. “Much more could have been achieved” – Civil Society Statement on the World Summit on the Information Society. December 18. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/contributions/co13.pdf&#34;&gt;https://www.itu.int/wsis/docs2/tunis/contributions/co13.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Yusuf 2009]&lt;/code&gt; Yusuf, Huma. 2009. Old and New Media: Converging during the Pakistan Emergency (March 2007 - February 2008). MIT Centre for Civic Media. January 12. Accessed on July 08, 2015, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://civic.mit.edu/blog/humayusuf/old-and-new-media-converging-during-the-pakistan-emergency-march-2007-february-2008&#34;&gt;https://civic.mit.edu/blog/humayusuf/old-and-new-media-converging-during-the-pakistan-emergency-march-2007-february-2008&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital Activism in Asia Reader</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/digital-activism-in-asia-reader/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2015 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/digital-activism-in-asia-reader/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;co-edited-with-prof-nishant-shah-http-cdc-leuphana-com-people-nishant-shah-and-puthiya-purayil-sneha-http-cis-india-org-about-people-our-team-sneha:8d1467b8da1a03f3ba8d40454c48961f&#34;&gt;Co-edited with &lt;a href=&#34;http://cdc.leuphana.com/people/#nishant-shah&#34;&gt;Prof. Nishant Shah&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://cis-india.org/about/people/our-team#sneha&#34;&gt;Puthiya Purayil Sneha&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../img/daar_cover.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;code&#34; title=&#34;Digital Activism in Asia Reader - Cover&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Digital Activism in Asia Reader took shape over two workshops with a diverse range of participants, including activists, change-makers, and scholars, organised by the Researchers at Work (RAW) programme in June 2014 and March 2015. During the first workshop, the participants identified the authors, topics, and writings that should be included/featured in the reader, based upon their relevance in the grounded practices of the participants, who came from various Asian countries. The second workshop involved open discussions regarding how the selected readings should be annotated, from key further questions to strategies of introducing them, followed by development of the annotations by the participants of the workshop. The full list of contributors, annotators, and editors is mentioned at the end of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Reader is edited by Nishant Shah, Puthiya Purayil Sneha, and I, with support from Anirudh Sridhar, Denisse Albornoz, and Verena Getahun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are grateful to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://meson.press/about/&#34;&gt;Meson Press&lt;/a&gt; for its generous and patience support throughout the development process of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please download, read, and share this open-access book from the Meson Press website: &lt;a href=&#34;http://meson.press/books/digital-activism-in-asia-reader/&#34;&gt;http://meson.press/books/digital-activism-in-asia-reader/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;excerpt-from-the-foreword:8d1467b8da1a03f3ba8d40454c48961f&#34;&gt;Excerpt from the Foreword&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compiling this Reader on Digital Activism in Asia is fraught with compelling challenges, because each of the key terms in the formulation of the title is sub-ject to multiple interpretations and fierce contestations. The construction of ‘Asia’ as a region, has its historical roots in processes of colonial technologies of cartography and navigation. Asia was both, a measured entity, mapped for resources to be exploited, and also a measure of the world, promising anorientation to the Western World’s own turbulent encounters. As Chen Kuan-Hsing points out in his definitive history of the region, Asia gets re-imagined as­ a­ ‘method’ in cold-war conflicts, becoming the territory to be assimilated through exports of different ideologies and cultural purports. Asia does not have its own sense of being­ a­region. The transactions, interactions, flows and exchanges between different countries and regions in Asia have been so entirely mediated by powers of colonisation that the region remains divided and reticent in its imagination of itself. However, by the turn of the 21st century, Asia has seen­ a­ new awakening. It finds­ a­ regional identity, which, surprisingly did not emerge from its consolidating presence in global economics or in globalised structures of trade and commerce. Instead, it finds­ a­ presence, for itself, through a series of crises of governance, of social order, of political rights, and of cultural productions, that binds it together in unprecedented ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The digital turn might as well be marked as an Asian turn, because with the new networks of connectivity, with Asian countries marking themselves as informatics hubs, working through a circulated logic of migrant labour and dis-tributed resources, there came a sense of immediacy, proximity, and urgencythat continues to shape the Asian imagination in a new way. In the last decade or so, the rapid changes that have emerged, creating multiple registers of modernity, identity, and community in different parts of Asia, accelerated by a­ seamless exchange of ideas, commodities, cultures, and people have created a new sense of the region as emerging through co-presence rather than competition and conflict. Simultaneously, the emergence of global capitals of information, labour and cultural export, have created new reference points by which the region creates its identities and networks that are no longer subject to the tyranny of Western hegemony&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the digital remains crucial to this shaping of contemporary Asia, both in sustaining the developmental agenda that most of the countries espouse, and in opening up an inward looking gaze of statecraft and social organisation, the digital itself remains an ineffable concept. Largely because the digital is like­ a­ blackbox that conflates multiple registers of meaning and layers of life, it becomes important to unengineer it and see what it enables and hides. The economic presence of the digital is perhaps the most visible in telling the story of Asia in the now. Beginning with the dramatic development of Singapore as the centre of informatics governance and the emergence of a range of cities from Shanghai to Manilla and Bangalore to Tehran, there has been an accelerated narrative of economic growth and accumulation of capital that is often the global face of the Asian turn. However, this economic reordering is not a practice in isolation. It brings with it, a range of social stirrings that seek to overthrow traditional structures of oppression, corruption, control, and injustice that have often remained hidden in the closed borders of Asian countries. However, the digital marks a particular shift where these questions are no longer being excavated by the ICT4D logic, of the West’s attempts to save Asia from itself. These are questions that emerge from the ground, as more people interact with progressive and liberal politics and aspire not only for higher purchase powers but a better quality of rights. The digital turn has opened up a range of social and political rights based discourses, practices, and movements, where populations are holding their governments and countries responsible, accountable, and culpable in the face of personal and collective loss and injustice&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of this multiplicity of digital sites and usages that are reconfiguring Asia, it is obvious then, that the very nature of what constitutes activism is changing as well. Organised civil society presence in Asia has often had a strong role in shaping modern nation states, but more often than not these processes were defined in the same vocabulary as that of the powers that they were fighting against.­ Marked by­ a­ strong sense of developmentalism and often working in complement to the state rather than keeping a check on the state’s activities, traditional activism in Asia has often suffered from the incapacity to scale and the inability to find alternatives to the state-defined scripts of development, growth and progress. In countries where literacy rates have been low, these movements also suffer from being conceived in philosophical and linguistic sophistry that escapes the common citizen and remains the playground of the few who have privileges afforded to them by class and region. Digital Activism, however, seems to have broken this language barrier, both internally and externally, allowing for new visualities enabled by ubiquitous computing to bring various stakeholders into the fray… At the same time, the digital itself has introduced new problems and concerns that are often glossed over, in the enthralling tale of progress. Concerns around digital divide, invasive practices of personal data gathering, the nexus of markets and governments that install the citizen/consumer in precarious conditions, and the re-emergence of organised conservative politics are also a part of the digital turn. Activism has had to focus not only on digital as a tool, but digital also as a site of protest and resistance&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Reader does not offer an index of the momentous emergence with the growth of the digital or a chronological account of how digital activism in Asia has grown and shaped the region. Instead, the Reader attempts a crowd-sourced compilation that presents critical tools, organisations, theoretical concepts, political analyses, illustrative case-studies and annotations, that an emerging network of changemakers in Asia have identified as important in their own practices within their own contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>