<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data And Development on Sumandro</title>
    <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/categories/data-and-development/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data And Development on Sumandro</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2015 20:09:56 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/categories/data-and-development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Opening Government Data through Mediation</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/opening-government-data-through-mediation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2015 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/opening-government-data-through-mediation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;report-produced-as-part-of-the-exploring-the-emerging-impacts-of-open-data-in-developing-countries-http-opendataresearch-org-emergingimpacts-project-of-the-open-data-research-network-http-opendataresearch-org-managed-by-the-world-wide-web-foundation-and-supported-by-the-international-development-research-centre-canada:d228ae7112f637e5efb26e3cab82dc7b&#34;&gt;Report produced as part of the &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://opendataresearch.org/emergingimpacts&#34;&gt;Exploring the Emerging Impacts of Open Data in Developing Countries&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; project of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://opendataresearch.org/&#34;&gt;Open Data Research Network&lt;/a&gt;, managed by the World Wide Web Foundation and supported by the International Development Research Centre, Canada.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://data.gov.in/sites/default/files/NDSAP.pdf&#34;&gt;National Data Sharing and Accessibility Policy (NDSAP)&lt;/a&gt; was approved by the Government of India in early 2012 to encourage and govern publication of government created and owned datasets, from various agencies of the central government of India, in open digital formats and through a single national data portal. The Policy extended the mandate of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rti.gov.in/rti-act.pdf&#34;&gt;Right to Information Act of 2005&lt;/a&gt; by establishing the principles and procedures of proactive disclosure of government data in India. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://data.gov.in/&#34;&gt;Open Government Data Platform of India&lt;/a&gt; was launched later in 2012 to collect and publish open government data. This study explores the existing practices of accessing and using government data in India to understand what challenges this Policy and its implementation measures must overcome to actualise the open data agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study surveys selected non­governmental and non­commercial data intermediary organisations, across sectors, that enable other organisations to better work with (access, use, and share) government and non­government data. Interviewing representatives of these organisations and understanding their actual data practices, the study attempts to respond to three key objectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;to undertake a provisional mapping of government data related activities across different sectors to understand the nature of the “open data community” in India,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;to enrich government data/information policy discussion in India by gathering evidence and experience of (non-governmental) data intermediaries regarding their actual practices of accessing and sharing government data, and their utilisation of the provisions of NDSAP and RTI act, and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;to critically reflect on the nature of open data practices in India.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;project-report:d228ae7112f637e5efb26e3cab82dc7b&#34;&gt;Project Report&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project website can be accessed here: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/&#34;&gt;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project Report - Executive Summary: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/report/sumandro_oddc_executive_summary.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/report/report_summary.html&#34;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project Report - Complete: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/report/sumandro_oddc_project_report.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/report/report_01_introduction.html&#34;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-materials:d228ae7112f637e5efb26e3cab82dc7b&#34;&gt;Other Materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timeline of open government data in India: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/resources/timeline.html&#34;&gt;URL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mapping data practices of (potential) data intermediary organisations in India: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/resources/mapping_data_practices.html&#34;&gt;URL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Survey questionnaire document: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/resources/sumandro_oddc_questionnaire_final.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Open Data Agenda for Post-2015 Sustainable Development Goals</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/an-open-data-agenda-for-post-2015-sustainable-development-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2014 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/an-open-data-agenda-for-post-2015-sustainable-development-goals/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;this-is-the-text-of-a-submission-note-prepared-by-me-in-response-to-the-call-from-the-independent-expert-advisory-group-on-data-revolution-and-sustainable-development-of-united-nations-it-includes-contributions-from-tim-davies-zacharia-chiliswa-and-gisele-s-craveiro:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;This is the text of a submission note prepared by me in response to the call from the Independent Expert Advisory Group on ‘data revolution and sustainable development’ of United Nations. It includes contributions from Tim Davies, Zacharia Chiliswa, and Gisele S. Craveiro.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The submitted document can be accessed here: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ajantriks/docs/blob/master/sumandro_ieag_datarevolution_submission_2014.10.15.pdf?raw=true&#34;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#1-an-open-data-agenda-for-post-2015-sustainable-development-goals:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;1. An Open Data Agenda for Post-2015 Sustainable Development Goals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;2-embracing-open-data-in-data-revolution-for-sustainable-development:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2. Embracing Open Data in ‘Data Revolution for Sustainable Development’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;2-1-openness-in-data-production:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2.1. Openness in Data Production&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;2-2-openness-in-data-publication:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2.2. Openness in Data Publication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;2-3-openness-in-data-usage:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2.3. Openness in Data Usage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;3-references:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;3. References&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;4-profiles:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;4. Profiles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-an-open-data-agenda-for-post-2015-sustainable-development-goals:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;1. An Open Data Agenda for Post-2015 Sustainable Development Goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data revolution’ has been one of the most remarkable categories of imagination and exploration to emerge from the report of the United Nation’s High Level Panel on the Post-2015 Development Agenda &lt;code&gt;[1]&lt;/code&gt;. The identification of availability of data on the global status of human development as a key problem area is not surprising given the experiences of measuring, monitoring and implement the Millennium Development Goals. Nonetheless, the recommendation by the High Level Panel for massive restructuring of infrastructures for generating global, reliable, comparable, and timely data is significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A brief note prepared by the High Level Panel explains that the ‘data revolution’ has two key objectives: ‘1) the integration of statistics into public and private sector decision making; and 2) building trust between society and state through transparency and accountability’ &lt;code&gt;[2]&lt;/code&gt;. The note also lists nine strategic interventions required to achieve these objectives. Only one of which, however, addresses the second main objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This submission suggests that an accountable and transparent revolution of global collection and utilisation of data for sustainable development must embrace openness as a fundamental pre-condition of the data concerned. In other words, a data revolution for sustainable development must be based upon global collection, usage, and publication of open data (relevant for purposes of sustainable development).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Independent Expert Advisory Group on ‘data revolution for sustainable development’ (henceforth, IEAG) has already addressed the question of open data through defining one of its consultation areas around the concept of ‘Accessible Data,’ which comprises of topics related to open data, accountability, and data literacy. This submission, however, proposes that open data must be considered as a cross-cutting principle and instrument of ensuring transparency, trust and security spanning all the constituent areas of the ‘data revolution’ — measuring of sustainable development goals, innovation through big data and new technologies, and addressing system challenges throughout the data landscape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reiterate, this submission finds the decision of the IEAG to dedicate an entire consultation area to ‘Accessible Data’ most encouraging and praiseworthy. However, it is necessary to simultaneously ensure that the concern for and transformative potential of open data is not contained within one consultation area within, but is discussed and deployed across the various aspects of the ‘data revolution.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-embracing-open-data-in-data-revolution-for-sustainable-development:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2. Embracing Open Data in ‘Data Revolution for Sustainable Development’&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discourse of ‘open data’ have emerged primarily from a ‘developed world’ context, and this has informed the efforts to define the term in terms of legal and technological considerations. The ‘8 Principles of Open Government Data’ prepared by Tim O’Reilly, Carl Malamud and others mention qualities regarding the nature of the published data (‘complete’ and ‘primary’), how it is published (‘timely,’ ‘accessible,’ and ‘machine- processable’), and the legal status of the published data (‘non-discriminatory’, ‘non- proprietary,’ and ‘license-free’) &lt;code&gt;[3]&lt;/code&gt;. The ‘Open Definition,’ largely accepted as a necessary and sufficient definition of ‘open data,’ also approaches ‘open data’ as data without any legal and technological constraints upon how it can be accessed, used, modified, and shared (for any purpose) &lt;code&gt;[4]&lt;/code&gt;. While such emphasis upon legal and technological concerns in defining ‘open data’ is necessary, operationalisation of ‘open data’ in the global development context requires consideration of other principles that may ensure the accountability of the the data production and publication processes, and the effective and transparent usage of the published data. Some of such principles have already emerged in mainstream (‘developed world’) discussion of open data. Such as the ‘7 additional principles’ listed by Tim O’Reilly, Carl Malamud and others that include critical issues like ‘open by default,’ ‘documentation,’ and incorporation of ‘public inputs’ &lt;code&gt;[5]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section highlights several other principles the importance of which have emerged from my own survey of research and advocacy organisations in India and their practices of accessing, using and sharing (open) government data &lt;code&gt;[6]&lt;/code&gt; and various studies undertaken as part of the ‘Exploring the Emerging Impacts of Open Data in Developing Countries’ project of the Open Data Research Network managed by World Wide Web Foundation and supported by International Development Research Centre &lt;code&gt;[7]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-1-openness-in-data-production:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2.1. Openness in Data Production&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.1.1. Open Procedures of Data Collection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– The principle of openness must be implemented from the very beginning of the data lifecycle – from the collection (or production) of data for purposes of sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Open production of data for sustainable development involves implementation of open documentation of data collection methods, prioritisation of free and open source softwares, hardwares and data formats for data collection, as well as ensuring sufficiently detailed description of the categories and assumptions employed in the data collection process. Unless these conditions are satisfied, it will not be possible to subject the collected data to public scrutiny and will undermine accountability of the collected data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.1.2. Openness Regarding Potential Uses of Collected Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Openness in collection of data must also be implemented in terms of explicitly communicating the reason for collection and potential usages of collected data to the individual or collective sources of data (from whom the data is collected). Though not commonly included in understanding of open data, this is an absolutely critical condition in the context of interventions towards global sustainable development. The individual and collective sources of data (to be used for purposes of sustainable development) must be effectively informed of the potential usages of the collected data, as absence of this can fundamentally damage the social trust between citizens and governmental agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.1.3. Openness for Big Data from Social Networks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– The above points are especially crucial when considering web-based social networks as sources of collection of data to be used for informing and measuring actions towards global sustainable development. Openness in the methods, assumptions, software and hardware employed in collection of data, and prior knowledge of the those who created/shared the data regarding its potential usages, must be strictly implemented when collecting data from such networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-2-openness-in-data-publication:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2.2. Openness in Data Publication&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.2.1. Open Data as an Universal Principle for Data Revolution, or ‘Open by Default’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– All data collected and utilised (by public, private, academic, or civic organisations) for purposes of interventions towards global sustainable development must be published as open data. This principle should cover data used both at the international level and also at the national level for such purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– ‘Open by default’ is a necessary (but not sufficient) condition for building trust through ensuring accountability and transparency in the strategies and techniques of ‘data revolution for sustainable development.’ ‘Open by default’ in this context emphasises treatment of the above as universal and ‘normal’ guiding principle for all data relevant to the processes of ensuring global sustainable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Implementing ‘open by default’ for all data collected and utilised for the purpose of informing and/or measuring sustainable development actions will require an expanded understanding of ‘open data,’ possibly augmenting the dominant understanding formulated by Open Definition &lt;code&gt;[8]&lt;/code&gt;. The legal and technological understanding of ‘open data’ needs to be expanded by (1) an understanding of the entire lifecycle of the data concerned, as mentioned above, (2) carefully assessed inclusion of existing practices of accessing, using and re-sharing government data and information that are available publicly or in semi-public networks, (3) responsiveness to different modes of consuming, analysing and acting upon (disaggregated and aggregated) data across regions, sectors, disciplines, etc., and (4) an acknowledgement that ‘openness’ of data is not simply defined by conditions under which it is published, but ‘openness’ must also apply to its various moments of usage and interpretation. Of course, this is not an exhaustive list of concerns but an indicative one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Further, it is crucial to consider globally produced data for the purpose of informing and measuring sustainable development as common resources and not as an asset. This principle highlights the need for making such data available as open data, but also to restrict (and/or regulate) the commercial usage of that data in cases where commercial use may negatively impact one or more sustainable development goals and/or basic human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.2.2. Proactive and Reactive Disclosure of Data and Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Proactive and reactive disclosure of data and information must be treated as essential complements. While, proactive disclosure of data and information is generally categorised as ‘open data’ and reactive disclosure of the same is called ‘right to information’ or ‘freedom of intervention,’ there is a threat in treating either policies of proactive or reactive disclosure as a substitute of the other. Proactive disclosure reduces public efforts in requesting for and gathering data and information on one hand, and reduces administrative efforts in re-sharing to already disclosed data and information on the other. Reactive disclosure ensures publication of such data and information that are most valuable in the context of public interests (including those concerning accountability and transparency of governance). Both the types of policies must be enforced nationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Data and information sharing by government agencies are often governed by a complex and specific (to the national system) sets of policies, acts, rules, and other directives. Policies for proactive and reactive disclosure of data and information, and governance guidelines for national portals to host the disclosed data, should effectively cross-reference all such relevant documents. This is critical for avoiding intra-governmental conflicts in publishing open government data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.2.3. Anonymity as a Strict Condition of Openness of Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Personally identifiable information in an open data set, that is information that can lead to a person (or a family) being identified from a dataset, or easily de-anonymisable open data set has the potential to cause irreversible damage to human security and well-being. Data to be used for the purpose of informing and/or measuring global sustainable development interventions, under no circumstances, should be collected, stored, analysed and shared in a form that either contains personally identifiable information or that allows easy de-anonymisation of the identities of the individuals and families mentioned in the data. It is absolutely critical that this is treated as a fundamental principle of any data under the purview of ‘data revolution for sustainable development.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Further, joining up of various data sets referring to the same population of individuals or families may potentially reveal the real identity(ies) of one or more members of the population. This also poses similar threat as above. To ensure that such triangulation of real identities is not possible by combining multiple data sets, all data sets used within the purview of ‘data revolution for sustainable development’ must necessarily contain only internally-consistent unique identifiers of each individuals or families (to whom the data refer to). In other words, unique identifiers used to represent a particular individual or family in a specific data set, under no circumstances, may refer to the same individual or family in another data set. This principle can be only relaxed in cases where data is collected about the same individual or family at different points of time, and hence consistent unique identifier is needed to generate a temporal analysis of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.2.4. National Open Data Portals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Neither are national open data portals substitutes for open data policies. While introducing an open data portal before a fully-formed (national) open data policy can have its benefits (such as accelerating the publication and usage of open government data), national open data portal cannot be sustained effectively in medium- and long-run without an open data policy to operationalise the portal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– This is of course not to take away focus from the critical need to build public data infrastructures, not only to host open data shared by various government agencies, but also providing common archival support to host open data shared by private, academic and civic organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– For successful implementation of national open data portals it is crucial to understand the deep backend of such a data portal that rests across multiple government agencies and sometime conflicting claims (within government) regarding ownership and control priviledges regarding data. Establishment of a national open data portal, hence, must not be seen as building an additional public-facing (and government-facing) component of government, but as an opportunity to re-configure very processes of management of data across agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– A government-wide incorporation of the notion and practice of open data is needed to ensure success of the national data portals. This requires re-designing the processes of data production and circulation within the government, including re-creating incentive structures towards publication of open, reliable and timely data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– It is fundamental that introduction of open data practices within government is not appropriated as a mechanism of greater surveillance and control of activities of lower levels of bureaucracy by higher levels of bureaucracy. Adoption of open government data means opening up data produced at all levels of government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– A commonly provided reason (by government agencies) for non-publication of government data is either bad quality or bad format of the data. Restructuring of government data practices towards making it more open must emphasise upon publication of all data that is identified as ‘bad quality’ or ‘badly formatted’ by the government agencies. Opening up of such data and establishment of feedback mechanisms are the most effective method to improve their quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Further, for citizens and development professionals to effectively participate in global sustainable development discussions, decision-making, and actions, it is critical that they have access to open government data at the national level, and comparable open data sets at the global level. Also, they must, as required, be provided technological support to publicly host and share (local, regional or other) primary data collected by them to inform the global discussions and actions. Both these tasks can be ably performed by a network of national and international (perhaps sectoral) data portals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.2.5. Creating Spaces for Open Data Intermediaries&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Government-run data portals are not sufficient to reach out to all the potential users of data in the world, nor should they aspire to do so. Open data intermediary organisations – that is organisations that specialise in mediating access, use and re-sharing of open data by other organisations – must be provided space in the national and international strategies of data revolution to augment and amplify the supply of national and international open data, as well as its availability across various media forms – digital and analog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– There is a rich range of organisations across the world that perform this role of mediating access, use, and re-sharing of government data by other organisations. While all such organisations may play productive roles in supporting other organisations and individual to work with open data, it is crucial to ensure that these intermediary organisations does not stop the flow (that is, re-sharing) of open data in the process of offering value-added services around open data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– In creating institutional support and partnerships between government and open data intermediary organisations, special support and capacity building processes must be employed to ensure that organisations that have been working with government data for long are able to preserve and build on their expertise as data-driven policy discussions and decision-making shift from paper-based to web-based media .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-3-openness-in-data-usage:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;2.3. Openness in Data Usage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.3.1. Openness in Usage of Data for Global Sustainable Development&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Creating global trust through accountability and transparency of data-driven processes of measuring development indicators, and of designing and monitoring development interventions require open documentation of these processes and availability of open data that are used to drive them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Any data used for taking local, regional, national, and global development decisions must be open data, that is it must be available for public scrutiny. This is a necessary principle for ensuring accountability of ‘data revolution.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Following the examples of data bank maintained by United Nations, World Bank, and other international agencies, the Sustainable Development Goal monitoring agency should create an online data archive to host disaggregated (as opposed to ‘country-level averages’) data utilised in the processes of measuring Sustainable Development Goals indicators, and informing and monitoring relevant development interventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.3.2. Opening up Public Participation in Data Discussions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– To ensure a truly broad-based revolution in the use of data for understanding and acting upon development needs, it is necessary to reach out to various communities working with data and information in the contexts of public accountability, sustainable development, human and community rights, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– While the ‘data revolution’ and also the ‘open data’ agenda focus on an imaginary of data as digital, numerical and disaggregated, it is crucial to keep in mind the multiplicity of forms in which data is accessed, used, shared and acted upon by individual citizens and various collectives. The data revolution will be truly successful if it empowers and mobilises all such circulations and usages of data, towards achieving global sustainable development. Openness of data is crucial step in enabling that, but is must be supported through public consultation processes of various kinds — from requesting inputs for technical design (of semantic standards, technical standards, data portal architectures, etc.) decisions, to educating individuals and various groups in effectively accessing, using and re-sharing data and information to ensure public accountability and informed development interventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Further and in reference to earlier discussion of ‘open procedures of data collection’ (#2.1.1.), to ensure effective use of open data by various individuals and collectives, it is critical to involve them from the very beginning of the data lifecycle, that is from its collection. Various forms of analysis and uses of the data require it to be available not only in specific forms (say, CSV or XML) but also the data structure to have specific qualities (say, inclusion of geo-referencing of each unit source of data). Such usage requirements are best resolved by involving actors at an early stage of conceptualising the structure of data to be collected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Effective usage of open data for purposes of development not only requires ‘data literacy’ but also enabling institutional contexts and civic skills and capacities to take advantage of such institutional contexts. The success of the ‘data revolution for sustainable development,’ hence, depends not only on systematic production of global, reliable and timely data on topics of sustainable development, and open publication of such data to enable public, private, academic and civic agencies to participate in the global development discussion, but also on the commitment of the governments to engage in and respond to data-driven discussion and decision-making processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.3.3. Opening Up Political Representation and Claim-Making through Use of Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– The previous point envisages the ‘data revolution for sustainable development’ promoting data-driven discussions and decision-making regarding global interventions towards sustainable development. This is of course not to suggest that all global sustainable development related discussions and decisions should solely be taken on the basis of available data. What is measured and what is not measured is a political decision to begin with, and often not all members of the population have equal abilities or priviledges to be included or represented within the collected data. One of the key barriers faced by disadvantaged groups globally while accessing welfare services is the need to belong to a government and/or official data set that determines one’s status as a beneficiary or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Thus, it is crucial for a successful ‘data revolution’ to faciliatate empowerment of individuals and communities to use not only existing open data, but also to use (locally and globally accepted) methods and techniques of creating open data to enter processes of claim making and of accessing welfare services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– To reiterate, it is absolutely crucial that lack of ability, capacity, resources, or priviledges to represent oneself in data terms, or in terms acceptable to the data-driven mechanisms of global sustainable development interventions, does not prevent any individual or collective from accessing the benefits of global sustainable development or from bettering one’s human wellbeing. In other words, while the ‘data revolution’ initiates struggles to bring down ‘data divides’ &lt;code&gt;[9]&lt;/code&gt; and the various other ‘divides’ that it is determined by (and determine back), in the meantime it must not allow individual and collective to be denied of development interventions and welfare services for their lack of capability to use and belong to datasets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.3.4. Essential Question – Who is Empowered by Using (Opened Up) Data?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– An essential governing question while taking decisions regarding conceptualisation and operationalisation of the ‘data revolution for sustainable development’ is who is empowered by collection and opening up of the specific data concerned? The ‘data revolution for sustainable development’ framework may mandate collection, archival, usage, and open sharing of only such data about human, infrastructural and ecological conditions that when used will lead to empowerment of people towards greater and sustainable wellbeing. This is a fundamental principle for two reasons – (1) falling costs of collection and archival of data at a global scale creates a strong attraction towards gathering of as much data as possible without specific objectives for their collection, and (2) availability of open data regarding human wellbeing conditions at a global scale has massive commercial value, unlocking of which may not necessarily lead to positive impacts in terms of global sustainable development goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Strict adherence to the notion of ‘open data’ as data that can be accessed, used, modified, and shared for any purpose need to be re-considered especially in the context of global sustainable development. The emphasis on any purpose specifically ensures the legal possibility of commercial use of the data concerned. While any re-consideration of the any purpose principle must allow for commercial activities such development experts undertaking analysis of published data (that is, commercial creation of data derivatives), but usage of such data for commercial decision making purposes (such as, differential rates for agricultural loans using environmental data) can be regulated. One possible legal instrument for ensuring open data use in public interest is the requirement that open data collected and published for the purpose of sustainable development can only be combined with data itself published as open data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-references:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;3. References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[1]&lt;/code&gt; High Level Panel – The Post 2015 Development Agenda. 2013. Retrieved October 14, 2014, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post2015hlp.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.post2015hlp.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[2]&lt;/code&gt; High Level Panel on the Post-2015 Development Agenda. 2013. What is Data Revolution? Retrieved October 14, 2014, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post2015hlp.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/What-is-the-Data-Revolution.pdf&#34;&gt;http://www.post2015hlp.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/What-is-the-Data-Revolution.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[3]&lt;/code&gt; The Annotated 8 Principles of Open Government Data. 2013. Retrieved on October 14, 2014, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://opengovdata.org/&#34;&gt;http://opengovdata.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[4]&lt;/code&gt; Open Definition. Retrieved on October 14, 2014, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://opendefinition.org/&#34;&gt;http://opendefinition.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[5]&lt;/code&gt; See &lt;code&gt;[3]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[6]&lt;/code&gt; Chattapadhyay, Sumandro. 2014. Opening Government Data through Mediation: Exploring Roles, Practices and Strategies of (Potential) Data Intermediary Organisations in India. Retrieved on October 14, 2014, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/&#34;&gt;http://ajantriks.github.io/oddc/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[7]&lt;/code&gt; Open Data Research Network. Retrieved on October 14, 2014, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://opendataresearch.org/&#34;&gt;http://opendataresearch.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[8]&lt;/code&gt; See &lt;code&gt;[4]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[9]&lt;/code&gt; Gurstein, Michael. 2011. A Data Divide? Data “Haves” and “Have Nots” and Open (Government) Data. July 11. Retrieved on October 15, 2014, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://gurstein.wordpress.com/2011/07/11/a-data-divide-data-%E2%80%9Chaves%E2%80%9D-and-%E2%80%9Chave-nots%E2%80%9D-and-open-government-data/&#34;&gt;http://gurstein.wordpress.com/2011/07/11/a-data-divide-data-%E2%80%9Chaves%E2%80%9D-and-%E2%80%9Chave-nots%E2%80%9D-and-open-government-data/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-profiles:49bbada6216088fec8de32596d3c0062&#34;&gt;4. Profiles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sumandro Chattapadhyay&lt;/strong&gt; is a Research Associate with The Sarai Programme at the Centre for the Study of Developing Societies, New Delhi, India. His academic interests include history and politics of informatics in post-independence India, science and technology studies, and political economy. He is associated with DataMeet, an organisation of open data and data science enthusiasts from India, and Open Data Research Network, a community of researchers from ‘developing countries’ working on themes related to open data. He also frequently works with the Centre for Internet and Society, Bangalore, India. Website: &lt;a href=&#34;http://ajantriks.net/&#34;&gt;ajantriks.net&lt;/a&gt;. E-mail: mail[at]ajantriks[dot]net.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tim Davies&lt;/strong&gt; is coordinator of the Open Data Research Network for the World Wide Web Foundation, and is a PhD Candidate the University of Southampton focussing on the democratic dimensions of open data policy. Websites: &lt;a href=&#34;http://webfoundation.org/&#34;&gt;http://webfoundation.org/&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.opendataresearch.org/&#34;&gt;http://www.opendataresearch.org/&lt;/a&gt;. E-mail: timdavies[at]webfoundation[dot]org.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zacharia Chiliswa&lt;/strong&gt; is the programmes Manager at Jesuit Hakimani Centre responsible for coordinating and supporting implementation of JHC programmes and projects. His areas of interest are communication for development, open governance and public policy. Website: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jesuithakimani.net/&#34;&gt;http://www.jesuithakimani.net/&lt;/a&gt;. E-mail: zchiliswa[at]yahoo[dot]com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gisele da Silva Craveiro&lt;/strong&gt; is a Computer Science Bachelor, has Master degree in Computer Science and PhD in Computer Systems. Since 2005 is University of São Paulo assistant professor. Coordinates the research group Colaboratory of Development and Participation (Colab-USP). She is also in the Open Government Partnership Latin American Civil Society advisor committee. She is Open Knowledge Brazil board chairwoman. Her national and international projects and publications are focused in open budget, ranging from government transparency portals analysis, data extraction, standardization of budgetary data disclosure on the web, civic application development and open data initiatives impact research. E-mail: giselesc[at]usp[dot]br.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The note is authored by Sumandro Chattapadhyay and is shared under Creative Commons &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20150401221441/http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&#34;&gt;Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International&lt;/a&gt; license. In this note, the author does not claim to represent any of the organisations and networks he is associated with. The articulated agenda is his own, and it includes ideas shared by the three contributors — Tim Davies, Zacharia Chiliswa, and Giselse Craveiro. The author takes full responsibility for reworking and rephrasing the ideas of the contributors into the note.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Revolution for Sustainable Development - Readings</title>
      <link>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/data-revolution-for-sustainable-development-readings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2014 20:09:56 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ajantriks.github.io/dotnet/data-revolution-for-sustainable-development-readings/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;With the policy period of the Millennium Development Goals (MDGs) coming to an end in 2015, United Nations instituted a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post2015hlp.org/&#34;&gt;High Level Panel&lt;/a&gt; to advise on the framing of the discussion on post-2015 global development framework and the design of the Sustainable Development Goals. The Panel submitted its &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post2015hlp.org/the-report/&#34;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; in May 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report highlights &lt;a href=&#34;http://report.post2015hlp.org/five-transformative-shifts.html&#34;&gt;five transformative shifts&lt;/a&gt; as core foci of the post-2015 development agenda, and identifies &amp;lsquo;data revolution&amp;rsquo; as a necessary and fundamental component of operationalising such an agenda. This identification is directly compelled by the experiences of measuring, monitoring and implement the MDGs. To quote from a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post2015hlp.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/What-is-the-Data-Revolution.pdf%22&#34;&gt;brief note on &amp;lsquo;data revolution&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt; published by the Panel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, the availability quality and accessibility of the data we have today just aren’t good enough. Too often, development efforts are hampered by a lack of the most basic data about the social and economic circumstances in which people live. This requires a commitment to changing the way we collect and share data, both from the bottom up and the top down&amp;hellip; The availability of information has improved during the implementation of the MDGs, but much better data are necessary. We have yet to establish an accurate picture of how many people are living in extreme poverty today; without that, it is very hard to work out the best ways to move that number to zero by 2030.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the challenge of absent and unreliable of global development data is a very critical one, the question here is if &amp;lsquo;data revolution&amp;rsquo; is being conceptualised robustly enough to address it. The same note explains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its heart, the data revolution comprises two main objectives: 1) the integration of statistics into public and private sector decision making; 2) building trust between society and state through transparency and accountability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The note lists nine strategic interventions required to achieve these objectives. Only one of which, however, addresses the second &lt;em&gt;main&lt;/em&gt; objective of building trust through transparency and accountability. Five interventions focus on resource moblisation, infrastructural development, and capacity building to upgrade national statistical systems, so as to generate reliable and timely data at national scale, as well as to extract data through new technological apparatuses such as social media networks, and national identity card systems. Two strategies highlight the need to engage public and private sector leaders to implement cross-sector transparency initiatives and sharing of open data and information. One strategy calls for a fresh round of collection of baseline data on development (by 2016) to inform the monitoring of post-2015 development goals. And only a single strategy focuses on the need to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create space for civil society to ensure these promises are fulfilled, and especially that we ‘Leave No One Behind’ and that the rights of marginalized groups are ensured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prepare recommendations for strategies towards a &amp;lsquo;data revolution in sustainable development,&amp;rsquo; UN has established an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.undatarevolution.org/&#34;&gt;Independent Expert Advisory Group&lt;/a&gt;. The Group formed on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.undatarevolution.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/PR-Announcement_Secretary-Generals-Independent-Expert-Advisory-Group-on-Data-Revolution.pdf&#34;&gt;August 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and is currently seeking submissions from the public, and is expected to present its final report by the end of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is set of background readings to inform engagements with the idea of &amp;lsquo;data revolution&amp;rsquo; and what can be its location within the post-2015 development agenda. Comments and suggestions of absent essential readings are very much welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-revolution-introduction:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Data Revolution - Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High Level Panel on the Post-2015 Development Agenda , UN - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post2015hlp.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/What-is-the-Data-Revolution.pdf&#34;&gt;What is the Data Revolution?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Johannes Jütting, Manager, PARIS21 Secretariat - &lt;a href=&#34;http://post2015.org/2014/08/14/data-revolution-in-development-countries-come-first/&#34;&gt;Data Revolution in Development: Countries Come First!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Claire Melamed - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/global-development/poverty-matters/2014/jan/31/data-development-reliable-figures-numbers&#34;&gt;Development Data: How Accurate are the Figures?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-revolution-national-statistical-systems:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Data Revolution - National Statistical Systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PARIS21 - &lt;a href=&#34;http://paris21.org/NSDS&#34;&gt;National Strategies for the Development of Statistics (NSDS)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;African Union - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.au.int/en/sites/default/files/AFRICAN_CHARTER_ON_STATISTICS.pdf&#34;&gt;African Charter on Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OECD - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oecd.org/dac/POST-2015%20P21.pdf&#34;&gt;Strengthening National Statistical Systems to Monitor Global Goals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-realise-the-data-revolution:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;How to Realise the Data Revolution?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morten Jerven - &lt;a href=&#34;http://post2015.org/2013/11/05/new-blog-series-what-kind-of-data-revolution-do-we-need-for-post-2015/&#34;&gt;What Kind of Data Revolution do We Need?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centre for Global Development and The African Population and Health Research Centre - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cgdev.org/sites/default/files/CGD14-01%20complete%20for%20web%200710.pdf&#34;&gt;Delivering on the Data Revolution in Sub-Saharan Africa: Final Report of the Data for African Development Working Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open Data Institute, Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation, DFID, Development Initiatives, ONE, Paris21, UNDP, USAID and World Bank - &lt;a href=&#34;http://post2015.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/data-revolution-expert-workshop-outcome-document1.pdf&#34;&gt;Towards a Strategy for the Data Revolution: Outcomes from the July 11–12 Experts’ Workshop&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-revolution-and-big-data:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Data Revolution and Big Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UN Global Pulse - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unglobalpulse.org/sites/default/files/BigDataforDevelopment-UNGlobalPulseJune2012.pdf&#34;&gt;Big Data for Development: Challenge and Opportunities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emmanuel Letouzé - &lt;a href=&#34;http://post2015.org/2014/04/01/the-big-data-revolution-should-be-about-knowledge-security/&#34;&gt;The Big Data Revolution should be about Knowledge Security&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bellagio Big Data Workshop - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rockefellerfoundation.org/uploads/files/c220f1f3-2e9a-4fc6-be6c-45d42849b897-big-data-and.pdf&#34;&gt;Big Data and Positive Social Change in the Developing World: A White Paper for Practitioners and Researchers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-disclosure-privacy:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Data, Disclosure, Privacy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vijay Pandurangan - &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@vijayp/of-taxis-and-rainbows-f6bc289679a1&#34;&gt;On Taxis and Rainbows: Lessons from NYC’s Improperly Anonymized Taxi Logs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arvind Narayanan and Edward W. Felten - &lt;a href=&#34;http://randomwalker.info/publications/no-silver-bullet-de-identification.pdf&#34;&gt;No Silver Bullet: De-Identification Still doesn&amp;rsquo;t Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Executive Office of the President, Government of USA - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/docs/big_data_privacy_report_5.1.14_final_print.pdf&#34;&gt;Big Data: Seizing Opportunities, Preserving Values&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-information-transparency:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Data, Information, Transparency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aruna Roy and Nikhil Dey, MKSS Rajasthan - &lt;a href=&#34;http://ibsa.cgg.gov.in/Articles/1.pdf&#34;&gt;The Right to Information: Facilitating People’s Participation and State Accountability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publish What You Fund - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.publishwhatyoufund.org/files/2010/05/BP1_Why-Aid-Transparency-Matters_FINAL.pdf&#34;&gt;Why Aid Transparency Matters, and the Global Movement for Aid Transparency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Access Info Europe and Open Knowledge Foundation - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.access-info.org/documents/Access_Docs/Advancing/Beyond_Access_7_January_2011_web.pdf&#34;&gt;Beyond Access: Open Government Data and the Right to (Re)use Public Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-data-introduction:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Data - Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim G. Davies and Zainab Ashraf Bawa - &lt;a href=&#34;http://ci-journal.net/index.php/ciej/article/view/929/955&#34;&gt;The Promises and Perils of Open Government Data (OGD)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harlan Yu and David G. Robinson - &lt;a href=&#34;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2012489&#34;&gt;The New Ambiguity of &amp;lsquo;Open Government&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Gurstein - &lt;a href=&#34;http://gurstein.wordpress.com/2011/07/11/a-data-divide-data-%E2%80%9Chaves%E2%80%9D-and-%E2%80%9Chave-nots%E2%80%9D-and-open-government-data/&#34;&gt;A Data Divide? Data ‘Haves’ and ‘Have Nots’ and Open (Government) Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-data-principles-and-definition:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Data - Principles and Definition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim O&amp;rsquo;Reilly, Carl Malamud and others - &lt;a href=&#34;http://opengovdata.org/&#34;&gt;The Annotated 8 Principles of Open Government Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open Data Handbook - &lt;a href=&#34;http://opendatahandbook.org/en/what-is-open-data/index.html&#34;&gt;What is Open Data?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rufus Pollock - &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.okfn.org/2014/09/30/why-the-open-definition-matters-for-open-data-quality-compatibility-and-simplicity/&#34;&gt;Why the Open Definition Matters for Open Data: Quality, Compatibility and Simplicity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-government-data-declarations-and-policies:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Government Data - Declarations and Policies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Executive Office of the President, Government of USA - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.whitehouse.gov/sites/default/files/omb/memoranda/2013/m-13-13.pdf&#34;&gt;Open Data Policy - Managing Information as an Asset&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;European Commission - &lt;a href=&#34;http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=COM:2011:0882:FIN:EN:PDF&#34;&gt;Open Data: An Engine for Innovation, Growth and Transparent Governance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ministry of Science and Technology, Government of India - &lt;a href=&#34;http://data.gov.in/sites/default/files/NDSAP.pdf&#34;&gt;National Data Sharing and Accessibility Policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-government-data-implementation-guidelines:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Government Data - Implementation Guidelines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centre for Technology in Government, University of Albany - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ctg.albany.edu/publications/reports/opendata&#34;&gt;The Dynamics of Opening Government Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UNESCO - &lt;a href=&#34;http://fas.org/sgp/library/unesco_govinfo.pdf&#34;&gt;Policy Guidelines for the Development and Promotion of Governmental Public Sector Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephan Shakespeare and others - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/198752/13-744-shakespeare-review-of-public-sector-information.pdf&#34;&gt;Shakespeare Review - An Independent Review of Public Sector Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-government-data-global-surveys:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Government Data - Global Surveys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open Knowledge Foundation - &lt;a href=&#34;http://global.census.okfn.org/&#34;&gt;Global Open Data Index&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;World Wide Web Foundation - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.opendataresearch.org/project/2013/odb&#34;&gt;Open Data Barometer 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southern Voice and others - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post2015datatest.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/Post2015-Data-Test-Methodology-Guide.pdf&#34;&gt;The Post-2015 Data Test: Country Level Experiences - Methodology and Implementation Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-government-data-regional-surveys:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Government Data - Regional Surveys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Becky Hogge, Transparency and Accountability Initiative - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.transparency-initiative.org/reports/open-data-study-new-technologies&#34;&gt;Open Data Study – New Technologies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara Ubaldi, OECD - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oecd-ilibrary.org/governance/open-government-data_5k46bj4f03s7-en&#34;&gt;Open Government Data: Towards Empirical Analysis of Open Government Data Initiatives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waltraut Ritter, Knowledge Dialogues - &lt;a href=&#34;http://knowledgedialogues.files.wordpress.com/2014/07/open-data-asia-09-2014.pdf&#34;&gt;Open Data in Asia: An Overview of Open Data Policies and Practices in 13 Countries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-data-selected-sectoral-portals:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Data - Selected Sectoral Portals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://opencorporates.com/&#34;&gt;Open Corporates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://aiddata.org/&#34;&gt;AidData - Open Data for International Development&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://landmatrix.org/en/&#34;&gt;Land Matrix - The Online Public Database on Land Deals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-data-supply-and-implementation:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Data - Supply and Implementation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UN Public Administration Programme - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unpan.org/DPADM/EGovernment/OpenGovernmentDataandServices/tabid/1536/language/en-US/Default.aspx&#34;&gt;Guidelines on Open Government Data for Citizen Engagement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Robinson, Harlan Yu,William P. Zeller and Edward W.Felten - &lt;a href=&#34;http://yjolt.org/sites/default/files/robinson-11-YJOLT-.pdf&#34;&gt;Government Data and the Invisible Hand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marijn Janssen, Yannis Charalabidis &amp;amp; Anneke Zuiderwijk - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.academia.edu/2852526/Benefits_Adoption_Barriers_and_Myths_of_Open_Data_and_Open_Government&#34;&gt;Benefits, Adoption Barriers and Myths of Open Data and Open Government&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-data-political-economy:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Data - Political Economy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Manyika and others, McKinsey Global Institute - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mckinsey.com/insights/business_technology/open_data_unlocking_innovation_and_performance_with_liquid_information&#34;&gt;Open Data: Unlocking Innovation and Performance with Liquid Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jo Bates - &lt;a href=&#34;http://ci-journal.net/index.php/ciej/article/view/845/916&#34;&gt;‘This is what modern deregulation looks like’: Co-optation and Contestation in the Shaping of the UK&amp;rsquo;s Open Government Data Initiative&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Governance Lab, New York University - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.opendata500.com/&#34;&gt;The Open Data 500&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-data-technological-concerns:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Data - Technological Concerns&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim Berners-Lee - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/LinkedData.html&#34;&gt;Linked Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timothy G. Davies and Mark Frank - &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.soton.ac.uk/352115/&#34;&gt;There’s no such thing as raw data:’ Exploring the Socio-Technical Life of a Government Dataset&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Civicus - &lt;a href=&#34;http://civicus.org/thedatashift/background/&#34;&gt;The Big Development DataShift&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-data-critiques:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Open Data - Critiques&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Gurstein - &lt;a href=&#34;http://firstmonday.org/article/view/3316/2764&#34;&gt;Open Data: Empowering the Empowered or Effective Data Use for Everyone?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tom Slee - &lt;a href=&#34;http://crookedtimber.org/2012/06/25/seeing-like-a-geek/&#34;&gt;Seeing Like a Geek&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rob Kitchin - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.maynoothuniversity.ie/progcity/2013/11/four-critiques-of-open-data-initiatives/&#34;&gt;Four Critiques of Open Data Initiatives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-algorithm-governance:a731412c9a3351285bbc47254e5dbb28&#34;&gt;Data, Algorithm, Governance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evgeny Morozov - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/technology/2014/jul/20/rise-of-data-death-of-politics-evgeny-morozov-algorithmic-regulation&#34;&gt;The Rise of Data and the Death of Politics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Eaves - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slate.com/articles/technology/future_tense/2012/09/open_data_movement_how_to_keep_information_from_being_politicized_.single.html&#34;&gt;Lies, Damned Lies, and Open Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Alan Johnson - &lt;a href=&#34;http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10676-014-9351-8&#34;&gt;From Open Data to Information Justice&lt;/a&gt; [Behind paywall]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>